Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore, joined by Kyle Helson, and today we are talking to Ashton Lambie. So before we get started, if you have any questions or comments or coaching inquiries, please send an email to empiricalcycling at gmail.com. And without further ado, let's start talking to Ashton Lambie. So Kyle, you actually remember watching Ashton at T-Town in like 2017, right? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you probably don't remember me. But I went up for a couple, you know, a couple of the Tuesday and Friday races in 2017. Yeah, I remember being like, who's that guy who I've never seen before in the like, kind of funny kit, like an arrow helmet and all the mass start races. Yeah, I remember going out there. I mean, that was it feels like ages ago, but
Yeah, that's kind of where I got a little more notice from the international track community. That was fun. And I think you you were there like the whole season, right? I think trying to think. Yeah, I was there for like a month. Yeah. Okay. Just like all the for all the UCI stuff. Yeah, that was when they had four weekends of UCI racing in a row. And I was like, trying to get enough points to go to World Cups and get noticed for the US national team. And so yeah, I went to all four of those. That was a big one. Nice.
How long had you been doing track slacking at that point? Since like January? Basically, it was like I went to Florida for their state track championships to try and get USAC points so that I could race nationals. And that was, it would have been, yeah, January of 2017. And the race, like I went down there and did really well and the race director saw me and he was like, oh, you just, just when you get home, go do your Cat 1 upgrade.
And so then it's, yeah, and that made it way easier. So I didn't really have to go do all those other USAC races. And that kind of freed me up to spend the whole month at T-Town and really focus on that at nationals as well. And so you really cut your teeth on track cycling and the grass track in Kansas, right? Yeah, that would have been summer of like 2016. It was kind of just, we did an Omnium series there and then they had the state track championships. So that kind of got me introduced to it.
But as far as racing, you know, a more conventional like wooden 250 or even an outdoor 333, that didn't start until like the next year. How was the learning curve for you on the wooden 250? Not bad. I started in Boulder. That was the first wooden 250 I rode. And I think the guy's name that helped me out there was Chris. I don't remember his last name, but he was super nice. And I told him I was like, oh, yeah, I've already done a safety course at this grass velodrome. And he was just like.
Does that really count? He was like, can we do that? I think he just made this up. Yeah, but he did a good job of getting me led into it. It was fun. We heard a rumor that you're building a grass track in your front lawn. Is that correct? I'm not currently doing it, but it's on the short list of things to do in my front lawn, yes. I know exactly where it's going to go. Today we had to plant...
Horseradishes and Raspberries, which are like more time sensitive than the grass velodrome. Do you think that there's a relationship between gravel racing and pursuiting that makes them both appeal to you and that makes you good at both? Oh, that's a good question. I feel like gravel is sort of, I mean, it's accessible, which is really nice. That's totally separate from track, but that's a huge factor for me.
I would say as far as like the commonalities probably a lot of the gravel races that I've done end up being sort of a time trial anyways and just like the sort of standard road tactics don't necessarily apply or like the bunch racing and that's what's drawn me specifically towards pursuing in the track it's just sort of like well let's just you know every lap just punch the shit out of each other and then like whoever wins wins like it's pretty simple you know.
I think gravel is a little bit that same way like every hill you just like you're riding with one guy or two guys and you're like just punching the shit out of each other every hill and finally somebody just blows and you're like well that's the race cool I mean do you have any ambitions to do mass start races on the track um not huge but I mean um I think I'll probably give it a shot especially we've got nationals this year um there's the the t-town omnium races I'll be there for two weeks this year
and I mean yeah it'd be good fitness just to try it out and I've done it in the past and had mild success but not as good as I am at pursuing I just don't have a good sense of tactics for road racing in general because it's more complicated than just like just beat the shit out of somebody every single lap or yourself every single lap yeah I actually wanted to ask you also
How would you describe the difference in the training between now your off-season doing gravel races and stuff as opposed to focusing on the individual pursuit? Well, I think it kind of follows just sort of a basic periodization thing that works out really well. So, I mean, for me, racing track, you know, say if that season starts like September or October, this year it starts a little earlier in like July.
Fortunately, I can still kind of train through some of those early season races. But this right now where we're at is technically like a base period for me. So, you know, in my talks with my coach Ben Sharp, I was like, oh, I've got these like these wicked bikepacking ideas, you know, like multi-day hundred mile trips. And he's like, that's fine. Do whatever dumb shit you want like that until like June, until you go to T-Town and then we'll start tacking on the intensity. And I was like, that's great. That sounds awesome. Yeah.
And that's kind of the gravel season too is right now. So it's not like I'm necessarily training for the gravel races. I'm using the gravel races to train for track season. So how do you feel that kind of riding supports you later in the season, later in the year when you get to those World Cups? I think, yeah, late in the year is huge. I think it's hard to sustain. I mean, last season was probably, I would say, the longest season I've had.
having more of that intensity and less of that volume starting earlier in the year I think kind of took its toll on me by the time I got to Worlds. I just like didn't necessarily have the big road case in the legs and that amount of time having them and then tacking the intensity on at the end. So yeah I mean it's just I think it's hard to sustain a peak for that long you know through basically the entire World Cup season but I think having that early season
Like right now, those big rides and those big blocks of just huge volume allows you to carry that a little bit longer into the season. I think you answered some of these questions in other universe too, but like, you know, you show up to Pan Ams, right? And I think you said before taking out the world record was not on the agenda. Is that right? Yeah, I wouldn't.
I wouldn't say it wasn't on the agenda. It was on the to-do list you keep on your nightstand that nobody else really knows about. It wasn't on the list on the fridge. It was sort of like there was a small part of me that thought it might be possible, but it wasn't as pertinent for me as winning and getting the national record. Sure, sure. And when?
Went along in the prep up to Pan Ams. Were you starting to think like, oh, this actually might be a possibility? I feel like the camp that we had. So we had a camp in Colorado Springs probably three or four weeks before Pan Ams. And so I had a good time at Nationals. Like I had improved over my previous season.
and that was also like I was training through nationals I'd raced the Omnium the day before I'd had gym you know two days before the individual pursuit at nationals so I was basically just training straight through it and I still shaved two seconds off after I peaked for it the year before and I was like okay like a 427 is still a shit time but like it's still two seconds better than I did last year yeah and you're fucking tired right like yeah yeah fuck yeah so it's like okay I'm
Obviously, at least two seconds better. I had ridden a 417, 419 at Worlds in Appledorn. And so I knew I would get, say, like three or four seconds going to altitude. And I was like, okay, that puts me at, you know, like, well within the national record. And then it was like, oh, well, have I gained three seconds in training?
This past year. Yeah, obviously, like, I've got two seconds right there. So all of those are like major assumptions, which is why it was so far back. I wasn't like walking up like, oh, yeah, I got this shit in the back. Sure. But it makes it realistic, right? You weren't rolling up only ever gone 419 and been like, yeah, 407, totally doable. Yeah, no, not at all. There were there were definite like, firm reasons why I thought it might be possible.
Prepping for the IP at Pan Ams, was that the primary focus and the team pursuit was kind of the backseat or do you kind of split between both of them? I think the TP was probably the bigger priority just because it's an Olympic level event. There was a lot. I mean, there's a lot riding on it all the time. But that was our first outing to go get Olympic points. So, yeah, definitely the priority was on that.
If you don't mind revealing trade secrets or something like that. Can you give us some of the workouts or something you did for IP prep? Or maybe something that stands out in your mind. Like, oh, we did this all the time. Or, oh, I really hated this. That's the thing. Up until basically track acclimation where I'm just doing some easy hit outs like a flying 2K or a flying 3K trying to find that IP pace on that specific track.
I don't really remember doing any specific IP work. I might have done two or three days of IP work in LA before nationals of 2018, but we didn't really do any at camp because we're doing double days of TP sessions. So it might be like if we did a flying 5K TP effort, I might sit off the back and that was sort of an IP effort at kind of race pace.
But there wasn't very much really specific IP work, like hardly any. So because it's not an Olympic-level event, it really kind of takes a backseat, and if you guys happen to do well there, it's just icing. Yeah, to some extent, yeah. Switching gears a little bit, for the team pursuit, you guys obviously do a lot of camps together, but do you see much of each other outside of those camps?
Yeah, I mean, like, we'll chat with each other, you know, stuff's going on, we have a group chat, but yeah, I'm sure, I think the guys in Colorado see each other quite a bit, and the guys racing road might see each other more, but I don't, yeah, I mean, I just chat with them, but yeah, not that much, because I also don't race roads, so it's like a bunch of people saw everybody else down at Sunny King, and I'm like, whoa, fuck. Yep, looks great.
Had fun watching it. Okay, well, so talking about Team Pursuit, when you started with the Team Pursuit team, how was it getting used to that type of racing and maintaining that tight formation? Because you coming from gravel and the individual events, more or less gravel and individual pursuit, how was the shift in gears for you?
Like just the technique? Yeah, the technique and, you know, riding an inch from the wheel in front of you and, you know, getting used to the changes and all of that. It was, I mean, I feel like I became like a bare minimum of adequate that, you know, everyone could trust me and like, oh, this guy probably isn't going to crash us. Like we can put him in a World Cup. I feel like that transition was pretty quick.
But I'm definitely still not to the level that someone, you know, like Gavin or Colby that have been riding for ages, or Eric, Sumi, like those guys really just have a lot more, I guess everybody on the team has a lot more technique and time in a tight group and probably on the track than I do. So, I mean, yeah, it's definitely something I'm still working on. I think the transition of just...
going to a time trial position that that's probably been the hardest thing for me and just like how to steer a bike in that position because I never really done it before IP like I've never raced time trials or anything so when USAC was trying to find the men's team pursuit riders at what point did you kind of get tagged as like oh hey this guy is you know someone we're going to keep inviting back and and
after I showed up and won national championships. Okay. So that was it? Like previously you had like no contact and then they were like, oh, hey, look at this guy. Yeah. No, seriously. Yeah. I emailed, I think I emailed Jim and Andy when they were both in the program. I didn't get started with the program until after Andy Sparks had left, but I remember emailing them. I think it would have been early.
Early in the season in 2017, rightfully so, they basically just told me to kick rocks. Where I am now and understanding where they were, that totally makes sense. I get that. I don't fault them for it at all, but they were like, dude, you just need to go race. We don't know who you are. You have no race resume.
Nobody really understands that you won the Pony Express 120 gravel race in Marysville, Kansas. What does that mean? So yeah, that was really the only contact I had and I knew that there were talent ID camps going on. But yeah, basically I showed up at nationals and people were like, who the fuck is this guy? Can somebody make him shave his mustache off? And then one IP and...
I think the first World Cup would have been Canada, which was still later that season, and Road IP at Pan Ams as well. So with the Team Pursuit team, I've seen the results, and you kind of watch the race results and stuff, and sometimes you guys run different groups of four. Are you still kind of trying to identify the best group of four, or are you trying to refine strategy with the different groups or things like that?
Yes, yes to all those I mean nobody is ever like super solid in their position it's not just like we never want to hit a level where we're like well this is our lineup and we're not willing to try new things like sometimes somebody might change position and then somebody sits on them really well like sits in their wheel and gets a really effective draft so stuff like that is kind of changing all the time and then yeah just finding the optimal like
getting the best person in each position for them to deliver their best performance. Like whatever that means, whether that's, you know, oh, this person, it's really hard to sit on their wheel, which is, that's usually me. So it's like, oh, well, who can we get to sit on Ashton's wheel and then still get the maximum number of turns out of them at the end? I was going to say, yeah. It's actually like the lineup is pretty complicated.
There's a lot of factors in play, definitely. If you don't mind, you don't have to reveal any trade secrets, but what kind of factors go into the order besides the draft and just getting comfortable? Are there more things that you guys consider? Yeah, I mean, there's subjective measurements and there's objective measurements where it's like, I like sitting this dude's wheel or I don't like sitting this dude's wheel. I think this guy's waterline doesn't match up with mine.
So there's sort of a bit of rider feedback there and then there's also just like the coach looking at it and saying okay well if we put rider A behind rider B we can get four laps out of them in the total race but if we move them to this position we can get five laps out of the whole race or oh well we can get five laps out of this guy in position four but we can only get two laps out of him in position one like is that a good trade-off does that make sense?
So sort of I kind of think of it as like a moneyball approach where it's like you have these super solid numbers you know how many KJs somebody can do on a ride and you're like okay well what's the best way to distribute those? Some riders are more anaerobic some riders are more aerobic so just trying to find everyone their best position If you had to pick the ideal slot for you what do you think that is?
I feel like I've been riding man one a lot lately and I feel I like that position. I feel good about that position. I think it allows me like I can start pretty well, maybe not as good specifically as some of our other guys that might be faster to the quarter lap, but I can do a start, get us up to the pace we need and then still contribute a lot in the back end. Yeah, to me it feels like a good position and then the way it plays in our choreography too.
Only see the front three times, and everybody else only has to do two pulls. So I can do the start, we go through the lineup, I do my second pull, we go back through the lineup, and then I finish. And so I assume some of that is also, you know, they're trying to minimize the number of changes as well, since you can lose, you know, half a lap, a lap, more than a lap sometimes if you change too often. Yeah, I mean, a change is about a tenth a second a lap.
You definitely want to minimize the number of changes you have. The goal I think that we're trying to get to is where we can go through our entire lineup twice. There's another question kind of related to this that I'm sure people are going to want to know what your experience is.
What's the difference between the personal coaches and the team coaches when you're training at home versus when you're at camp? Who's got a say in what and how does that get prioritized? For me, when I'm at home right now, I'm working with Ben Sharp and he's the one who writes all my coaching on a day-to-day basis. But I think there's sort of a dynamic. I also have a separate strength coach, strength and conditioning coach.
that I work with. He's based out of Lawrence, Kansas. That's sort of, you know, another division of telling me how my day is going to go. And then usually when we're at camp, Clay Worthington, our head coach, kind of dictates that. But he also talks to Ben and likewise Chris. You know, all three of them talk and try to figure out the optimal training camp and training stresses for each rider. You know, some guys in a different phase where
Half the team is doing ergo testing and they're like, well, this guy could probably use some more road case. Then it's, you know, that usually gets communicated pretty well. Well, that's good. Yeah, because, yeah, I think we've all heard about, you know, like national coaches and personal coaches either like not talking or butting heads and nobody's on the same page. And I mean, that's great that everybody kind of gets together and works together. Yeah, absolutely.
So what was it like for you the first time you went to the Olympic Training Center? Dude, it was nuts. It's wild. Yeah. Like, so like, like describe your walk on and your first day and kind of like discovering the facility and the people there. Well, yeah, just like driving out there. I mean, getting an email from Jim Miller that's like, oh, hey, we want you to come to this camp. I'm like, oh, my God, I'm going to fucking training camp. This is wild. Like, maybe I'll get to go to a World Cup. Oh, God, I hope I'm good enough to go to a World Cup.
So a friend of mine that did body work for me when I lived in Lawrence, Kansas, she was a massage therapist. So she had done some rotations at the OTC as well. And she was like, oh, when you get there, you got to meet Flower. Like she's this crazy chef. And so, you know, she'd kind of given me a layout and, you know, just going on there though and seeing it and being like, oh, this is the athlete entrance. Like this is where I go. Yeah, it's crazy, man.
Speaking of you getting found by people for being fast, how did the Hoob Wattbike, formerly Team KGF guys, find you? How was that connection made? My dad had talked, he came to watch us in Milton, and he had kind of talked with, I think, the marketing guy for Hoob, and just like, oh, Ashton thinks this program's really cool. Because I had seen them.
Race in Belarus would have been the last World Cup season and just been blown away. Those guys are so much further ahead than everyone else as far as different ways to think about going faster. I just thought that was crazy and super impressive. My dad had talked to them in Milton this year, so it would have been this World Cup season.
and then yeah Johnny Whale texted me just like hit me up on I think Instagram and was just like hey you want to come race uh Berlin and London with us and I was like dude I just woke up can you give me like like six hours to figure some shit out and we'll see and he's like yeah that's fine just let me know I was like fuck this is sweet yeah on a scale of one to ten what was your stoke level
Oh dude, definitely a 10. I was hyped. That's awesome. Yeah, definitely to go to London and Berlin to get a race with those guys. Yeah, it was awesome. And then the more I kept learning about it, I was like, oh my god, we get to go to Darby? This place looks fucking awesome.
With those guys, your position on the bike changed between before Hublot Bike and after. You definitely stand out on the American team as having a position that looks like those guys. Did they get you into the wind tunnel at the Boardman Center? No, we didn't do the wind tunnel. A lot of it was shockingly plug and play. I went in and kind of filled in for Jacob Tipper, who was just...
just having a rough time of season. I just got on his bike. I threw my saddle on. I threw my cranks on. I don't think we changed anything on the front end. I just rode his extension. I was like, this is close enough. Yeah, it was wild. All we did was set the saddle and everything was good. It's weird. A lot of it...
has transferred over to the felt, like the extensions that I got. And yeah, so it did kind of translate a little bit, but we never got to the wind tunnel to compare those two. We did all of the testing on the track as far as like dialing that position. Yeah. And so like, did you pick up on any aero lessons that you can pass on to anybody, like just by like hanging out with those guys?
I think the one thing that I took away was that there's no level of detail that's too small. I think a lot of coaches and riders will be like, oh, well, I'm not good enough for shoe covers. I'm not good enough for ceramic bearings. There's just this whole list of equipment that people are like, oh, you just need to get faster before you start worrying about disc wheels.
Okay, I get that. Like, that does kind of make sense. But there's no reason, like, it just seems like a real arbitrary line. And those guys just moved the line all the way to the other end. Because no one would show up to a World Cup on, like, a steel road bike. They'd be like, well, obviously you should get a better bike than that. And then there's the next line of, like, well, obviously you should get ceramic bearings in all your wheels and bottom brackets. And then just...
The next line is like, oh, you should aero test individual fabrics before you design any sort of suit. Like going just total everything, everything that comes into play on that bike is optimized for one goal, which is to go fast. Actually, that brings me to another question. How do I get one of those helmets? Dude, they're very, they're, you could probably contact Tube. They're getting pretty hard to find. I got mine on Amazon.
for a good deal from, like, some triathlon store. Because they're old helmets. Like, nobody wears them anymore. I think also it stands out with the U.S. team because you've got, you know, the old, I guess, like, it's an old POC helmet, right? Mm-hmm. It's a POC temple. And then everyone else has, you know, a Bell or a Giro or whatever. Giro, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, we've started doing, like, this kind of off-season, we've done more aero testing, and so I think you'll probably see more guys in different helmets.
Yeah. Because the tough thing too is that it doesn't just translate over where it's like, oh, well, let's just buy the whole team pox. Right. Because it's not that helmet. The reason it kind of died off is because it's really fast, but only in a very certain position. That's what even with the Hoob guys, like some of them were riding the Giros for a while before they could get their positions optimized for the pox. So yeah, the helmet, I mean, the helmet is different for every rider.
There's not just one helmet that's just the fastest helmet How much actual serious discussion did those guys have about the aerodynamics of the mustache? Oh, I wouldn't say that many serious discussions When they picked me up from the airport, they all had drawn mustaches on That's awesome Both John and Johnny were sitting on the couch with these big fake mustaches sharpied on their upper lip and I was just like
Well, I can tell it's going to be a big topic of conversation this whole trip. Yeah. Yeah, those guys seem to never stop giving each other shit on Instagram. Oh, it's so funny. It's constant. I love it. Did you get a chance to bring any lessons from them back to the American team? Yeah. I mean, I think the testing protocol and the testing ideas of how to...
I think we got an Alpha Mantis system in Colorado Springs and we were kind of like, well, how do we use this? Like you can't just throw something in and just be like, oh, well, this is our error testing. This is how we're going to do it. Like kind of having a protocol of like, well, this is how we're going to test things. This is how we're going to approach this. And this is what these numbers mean. I kind of tried to help with that and then get the, we weren't supplementing with caffeine or sodium bicarb.
and so I brought back some protocols on those and then we started using that well how much well obviously caffeine has a great ergogenic effect but so what do you notice about sodium bicarb because I've heard some horror stories about people dashing off while cutting their butt cheeks like two minutes before their race start oh god yeah I we never had any issues with it we had a pretty good protocol that worked really well for like
Delivery and timing and dosage and everything. I think it was Cambridge where we had three rounds in a day and like, you know, you don't feel great. I was like, fuck, I've had like what it would have been almost 50, like half or like, yeah, probably 50, 60 grams of bicarb and like almost an entire gram of caffeine that whole day. And I was like, well, I'm going to be out for tomorrow. Like, don't, don't expect much. Yeah.
Okay, so I have one more question about the Hoob Wattbike guys. There was a joke on Instagram about one of John Archibald's rides and he's the C-level IP world record holder and there was a joke about him not or maybe breaking a thousand watts in a start. Can he really not break a thousand watts? Have you watched the videos? No, I haven't. Watch a video, man. You watch a video and you're just like...
It'll all make sense because they do this thing where the man one changes to man three because John is so slow off the start that he leaves and he's going like just full tits and still leaves the bike length like every time. So the question is, sorry. The crazy thing is that, yeah, his heart rate will get lower as the ride goes on because that guy is just such a massive aerobic engine.
Okay, so what was your gear for the world record IP? One, I think it was 113. Did you have a pacing strategy going in? So the way it works is that the coach walks the line that's like on a specific pace. And so then if you're like over or under that pace, he'll walk, he'll like be standing in front of or behind the line. So you have to have some sort of basis of like what you're going to ride. And for me, that was five threes.
which would have been like a 4.11 or something, a 4.12. But I knew that 5.2 is when I needed to break the record. So I was like, oh, 5.3 seems pretty reasonable. And then usually call them up, like ride a little bit ahead of schedule. Yeah, so what was your power output for that particular ride? I don't remember. I don't remember exactly. It was like 4.80, 5.00, somewhere in there, I think. This is something I've always wondered and not been sure about.
At the Elite World Cup level, do you find that the top two, three, four qualifiers in either the individual pursuit or the team pursuit kind of sandbag the first ride because they know that if they back it off 98%, they can still qualify and they'll be through? Yes, absolutely.
I think if you're a team that knows you're going to make it in the top four, you do that, you go full gas. Because if you're seeded in the top four, that's the only way you can get to gold or silver. Right. So, I mean, there's some strategizing there about like, well, okay, how many other teams are here? What place do I want to slot into? Because like ideally...
if you know you're going to go through and you think like oh man the best I can do is qualify fourth because there's these three other teams here like you don't want to try and qualify fourth you want to try and qualify like fifth so you can get a shot at bronze or something right so like so saving energy really does matter is is you know between those two rides I guess is the takeaway and getting
I remember seeing a chart somewhere. Someone had done the fastest times, TP times, throughout the World Cup season. A shocking number of them were in round one. If you save energy in the qualifiers and get seated in a good spot, and you have a bunch of fresh guys and a team that you might already be five seconds up on qualifying, you're going to have a great time. But it's all part of the strategy of...
doing as little as possible and then saving it for when it really counts. Historically, I come from a competitive swimming background and all the big championships are trials finals. And that was what people would do. Like if you knew the, okay, so the major final is eight people. And so if you knew you were going to go through, yeah, you would just back it off a little bit in the morning. So dumb question. What crank length do you ride on your track bike? And is it the same?
I ride 165s on everything. Okay, one more dumb question. About what's your FTP most days? I don't feel like it's that high. I want to say around 380 or something. I don't feel like that's high. But I mean, I know other guys who are like, oh yeah, my FTP is like 400, 410. I'm just like, oh, shit. Something I want to know. What's something that you wish you knew about training?
earlier than the time you learned it. It was like something you wish you had at the beginning. How much fun Zwift is? Wow. I love Zwift, man. I wish I would have gotten on it sooner. It's fun. No, I think seriously, like I probably would have started doing strength stuff sooner, like going to the gym. Yeah, I feel like that's helped me a ton. Just like gym work in general, I think if I would have started doing that sooner, probably would have been even better.
In what way do you feel gym work makes your riding better? I feel like it's easier, like the starts are better. Like I'm just more stable in the saddle and more centered. It's easier to put down power. Yeah. And overall, like I just feel better on the bike. I have fewer like injuries or persistent aches and pains, that kind of thing. Okay. So what's your favorite lift in the gym? Ooh, I do really like deadlifts. It's a very...
Do you use that hex bar or straight bar? I feel like it's a really similar motion to starting and I feel like if I'm really primed for a good hard deadlift and like thinking about that at the start it's always like just flying out of the gate. How do you maintain your work-life balance? Like how do you prioritize everything like making sure you get enough time you know wherever you need it? I feel like I try to you know really focus on the essentials as far as like
And maintaining, you know, the first thing I do in the day is like, get coffee, get breakfast, and then do the training. And then if you get that stuff done early, then it's like you have the whole rest of the day to focus on the rest of your life, whether that's, I work a couple days of the week at the bike shop, we grow a lot of stuff, we have like, sort of a large garden slash farm. And so like, I think
Sort of using your energy throughout the day on the stuff that you need to get done. That usually works pretty well for me. I'm lucky enough that I get to do it full time and just like, you know, working two days a week at the bike shop is just for fun, which makes it a lot easier. So have you started to be recognized in more places as, oh, hey, that's the really, you know, really fast pursuiter or, you know, not quite yet? Honestly, like more at cycling events.
But less locally. When I was in Kansas and I did the Crossing Kansas thing, it was on the news, it was on the front page of the paper. People loved it. It was super cool. I had a ton of people recognize me from that. And then when I got the world record, it was on page six of the sports fashion. That was it. I think a news segment came out and I was like, oh, okay, I guess.
For someone in Nebraska, world championships for this weird niche event doesn't really mean as much as college football. It's a different level, but it's been fun. Right now, obviously, Tokyo is the big goal, but especially for Team USA and national team stuff, are they planning beyond that still? I know for some of the...
Team Pursuit guys. They're starting to get a little old, but then you have like, you know, Colby who's super young. Yeah. I think that's the plan as far as I know. Well, now that I was thinking more along the lines, now that we know that 2028 is going to be in LA. In LA, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I think that's definitely a goal for everybody because, you know, the guys, the young guys in the program would be like just the right age at that point, basically. Do you have any, uh,
Any Madison ambitions with this coming up as the new Olympic event? Oh, dude, no way. I would give Omnium a pretty decent look, but no way. Hard pass on the Madison. It's too bad for you that they changed the Omnium format. I never raced the old Omnium format. You're not the first person that's told me that, but from what I understand, I would agree. It would have been fun to race one. Yeah.
Because you get the kilo, the pursuit, you know. The flying lap. The flying lap, yeah. It's like it did a serious disservice to like Ed Clancy from GB. Yeah, basically if you're a really good points racer, you're by default a really good Omnium racer. Like you can just half-ass all the other races. Yeah, well and a tempo race is basically a points race, you know. Yeah, pretty much, yeah. So what is your favorite thing to be doing?
Not on the bike and not cycling related? Probably just working around the farm. Like we spent today planting, just like being outside. It was a super nice day. We planted potatoes, raspberries, and horseradish. And I was like, man, this is a good, like we just had a gym. And then, yeah, just planting stuff the rest of the day. And I was like, man, this is awesome. Super fun day. That's really cool.
That's quite the juxtaposition, right? Like world record track cycling to working on the farm and, you know. It's nice. I mean, I take, I really enjoy doing like, I don't want to say like menial physical labor, but just like chores. Yeah. Like cutting up wood to heat our house for the winter. I don't know, that kind of stuff. Growing our own food, canning our own food.
I totally understand there's something satisfying about being like, oh yeah, we did that. We got this work done. I would say that it's a simple task that is easy. It's very clear cut. It's like you start it and then you finish it. You put the potatoes in the ground and then you eat the potatoes. Although I sometimes wonder if that's not too different from...
You know, athletics and training and, you know, you go in, do your workout, you do the work, you get it done. Yeah. And you get the green box on TrainingPeaks. Yes, that's exactly how I think about it. And this is something I've been trying to get my athletes to do more, but do you use the emojis on TrainingPeaks? I just did that today. I thought about that. I did that today.
Oh, I was on, I was supposed to ride my track bike on the rollers and my seat post broke and I used like the little crying emoji and I was like, Ben's either not going to notice that or I'm going to get a text in like an hour and he's going to be like, come on man, emojis in the comments. Can you see him on the desktop? Yeah. Yeah. I actually, they're an integral part of evaluating how someone's training is going, at least for me.
I don't look at the performance management chart nearly as much as I do. How are the emojis trending this week? How old are most of your athletes? Because I don't feel like I use that many emojis. The youngest is, I think, 19 or 20, and the oldest is late 60s. Oh, and they still use them. And I get all of them. Oh, wow. Oh, yeah, every one. Interesting. Well, almost every one. I'm still working on a couple. That's good. I mean, it makes sense.
Yeah, well, I mean, like, there's a book came out recently called Good to Go. And it's like a pop science review of all the literature on recovery. And, like, at the end, you know, when the author's really getting down to the nitty gritty of like, okay, really, what works? And it's like, sleeping and eating. Shocker. Yeah.
and also like how does the athlete feel she was going over a training plan for a really successful ultra marathon runner and what she does is she just runs day after day after day a lot until she feels like she's tired and then she rests until she feels like she's ready again and she's phenomenal crazy
You can watch her emojis, I assume, trend from being very happy to very sad at the end of the training block and they come back up. Interesting. Well, yeah, we'll see what Ben thinks of this first emoji. Could be a new thing. One other question I have. So what's it like to ride the felt super bike versus the regular? Yeah, versus the TK1. It's wild. It's fast. Yeah, it's one of those things where like...
I don't feel like I'm someone that's super in tune with bikes. Just in general, like I remember when we were in Majorca for a pre-Worlds camp, we got all new campy discs, like the campy Ghibli discs. And sometimes, oh my god, this is so stiff. I can't believe how much better this is than the Mavic. And I was like, I don't know, man, it just feels like a disc.
Feels like we got wheels on. What do you want me to tell you? It rolls, yeah. Yeah, it's fine. But getting on the TK on the FRD, like, yeah, just the overall feel and kind of the snappiness of it. And I don't know how much of that is because of the bike and how much of that is because of, like, the geometry, the narrower dropouts. Like, I feel like the front end, I can definitely tell the narrower dropouts and the narrower base bars.
But it feels good. In the position, it feels fast. It feels responsive. It's good. I really like it. Did you get a chance to directly compare who bought bikes on the Argon? I know I haven't yet. It's on the list. Are those guys going to have you back next year? Or like you said, you were just covering for Tipper.
I think we're trying to make something work out. It depends on who's going to what World Cups and when everybody's busy. But yeah, I hope to ride with them again. I think there's a good chance. All right, man. Well, I really appreciate you coming on, man. Thanks for having me. This was fun.
Alright, so Ashton, thank you for coming on. Everybody, thank you for listening. If you would like to support the podcast, please head over to empiricalcycling.com and we have a donations page. We have a no advertising model, so if you want to support the podcast, buy us a coffee or something like that. We'd really appreciate it. So if you have any questions, comments, or coaching inquiries, please send an email to empiricalcycling at gmail.com So until next time, thank you all very much. Bye.