Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Coley Moore, and I want to thank everybody for listening as always. And I know it has been a little while since we released an episode, so thank you for coming back to listen again. Remember to please subscribe to the podcast if you have not yet already, and also share it with a friend because that really, really helps us out. And also iTunes ratings and reviews are very welcome as well. And also remember that we're an ad-free podcast, so if you'd like to support the show, you can donate at empiricalcycling.com slash donate.
We have the show notes up on the website. We don't have any notes today because we have an interview. And we've got some merch at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com. And if you have any coaching and consultation inquiries, questions, and comments, you can email me at empiricalcyclingatgmail.com. And if you are looking for a coach after this episode, I would definitely shoot me an email because we are interviewing one of the empirical cycling coaches. And he's a really smart guy. He's a really good guy. And he's a really good coach.
Working with him is highly recommended, obviously. And also remember that on Instagram, Weekend AMAs, at Empirical Cycling, of course. And if you want to participate in that, that's awesome. If you just want to read along, that's cool, too. And oh, before I forget,
Be sure to check out the Endurance Innovation Podcast because they invited me to be on. They asked me a bunch of questions about VO2Max and I answered and we had some interesting discussion. So that is probably worth a listen if you'd like to hear a couple more thoughts on that. And I want to thank them for having me on. That was a lot of fun. And so for today's episode of the Empirical Cycling Podcast, we are going to be talking about recovery and illness.
and this is a really cool discussion. I was really looking forward to it and I think it was probably one of the more fascinating conversations that I've had with somebody recently.
We get into things like, you know, what is the generalized immune response, the kind of above the neck, below the neck thing? Like, is that, you know, is that like a real thing that we can actually utilize to train or not train? You know, the best way to kind of come back from illness, you know, ways to prevent illness. We also talk a lot about the data of illness in the scientific literature. We talk about nutrition aspects of illness and all that kind of stuff. So it's a pretty wide range of conversation, but it's really fascinating.
He's a really knowledgeable guy and he's also a really, really good coach. So I think everybody's going to enjoy listening to this episode as much as I enjoyed having this conversation. Or at least I hope that's the case. So without any further ado, let's get into it. Fabiano, thanks for coming on the podcast.
Well, thank you for having me in. It's a pleasure always to share some knowledge. Yeah. Or should I say Dr. Fabiano? Don't worry about being too formal. It's okay. Well, so why don't we give folks a little bit of background. So take a minute to tell people like how you got into the sciences and, you know, the various degrees you have, because you have quite a few. And how you got started coaching. Well, I started medical school around 15 years ago.
and after doing the medical school I was I was always interested in sports medicine and after I finished my medical school I actually went to to a first master in human physiology and that was where I got back and more involved with cycling and that's when I hired a coach and that's at a certain point I I was progressing but then
I hit the wall and I was curious to know why my performance wasn't improving anymore as I would like to and then discussing with my former coach I couldn't find a reasonable answer and that was the point where I decided to study
more about exercise physiology and also when I decided to go for a second master at this point in the United States, at the University of Akron, and full-time with exercise physiology and also biomechanics. And after I finished this second master, I still didn't have the answer that I wanted for why my performance wasn't as good as I wanted.
One thing that I found out is that I probably didn't have chosen my parents well. And then I moved on. I got back to Brazil. I started my coaching business alone myself as a private practice.
Still looking for that answer, I went for a PhD, and this time looking at the genomics and the proteomics of performance and human performance, mostly human physiology, and I studied some of the aspects of the renin-angiotensin system and got some peer-reviewed publications out of that. Sorry, you studied, what was that, the renin-angiotensin system?
Exactly. So I was trying to understand the difference between the regulation of women and men on how some proteins could regulate this system differently because you know we have some specific genes for men and women. And so we did a lot of experimental
some research on some experiments and trying to find that difference we found something and that was really computational biology in syndical experimental experiments and and it was a lot of fun and also a lot of learning on how complex actually it really became clear to me how complex is the human biology and and I as I learned more and more and I start bringing these concepts to
My coaching practice actually I finally could understand better why my performance was as expected but at the same time as I was getting more and more experience with my athletes I was trying to help them too because as you know most of our amateur athletes don't have the external performance they would like to have but they want to have their
Ultimate Performance, the best performance they can have in their life and then understanding where the limiters are and how we could at least go to the limit on their physiology and get their best performance is always my goal with my athletes and because of that approach I started to really look into the numbers of the performance with like power and I've been following all the
the work with PowerData and Coogan and others. And because of that, I was more and more involved with the WKO team. And that's where I got to met you. And we started working on some advanced projects on the WKO software, first of WKO 4 and now WKO 5. And at some point I was...
I started listening to this wonderful podcast and I said, I told myself, why not contact Koli and see if we could work together? And I said, well, let's discuss that and I think it worked, right? Yeah, I think it's worked out very well, actually. And you are an excellent coach and I'm really happy to have you with Empirical Cycling.
And actually, I think we actually met even before the special projects because you were on, I think you had translated my PMAX and FRC webinar into Portuguese. Yes. And you had contacted me with some questions specifically like to clarify things.
Exactly, yeah, I had this volunteer work as a coach educator for TrainingPeaks, so I translated, I think at this point, almost, I think it's eight webinars, four from the WKO4 and now four from the WKO5, and two of them are, you organized them, which were about the PMX and all the sprinting analysis, so yeah, I read to you and said, well, could you explain me more about that because...
I don't have a lot of experience with sprinting but I was always curious to understand how to make a better decision and informed decision about sprinters and how to analyze their data because it's very
interesting aspect of the cycling short durations. Yeah, and actually we should talk about that another time because today I really want to use your medical background to discuss illness and performance. And we were going to do this a while ago discussing COVID, but I asked you to look into that and look up some stuff that we could discuss with that. And you and I chatted quickly before the podcast about, you said that there's a lot that we just don't know with that and that the data is not there, right?
Yes, as a lot of topics in medicine, we wish we had more strong evidences to take our decisions, be more scientific, but still, just as in coaching, we still have a lot of personal decisions and art, I would say, in medicine, and the same with, for example, acute illnesses, like respiratory tract illnesses,
So respiratory tract illnesses like common cold and flu, bronchitis, that kind of stuff? Exactly. But even if the evidence is not the best as we would like to have, it still doesn't mean that we will not use it. We are using it on an everyday basis. But what I want to mean is that we have to listen to the athlete, understand his reality,
Work with the science to make sure we have the best decision. For example, when someone has a flu or a cold, should we rest? Should we go for another workout? And that kind of stuff. Yeah. And let's actually let's get right into that because, you know, there's this this rule of thumb that you hear a lot of the time. Like, should you train? Should you rest? And it's the neck thing. Like you can train.
If your symptoms are above the neck, like if you have a runny nose or a cough or something like that, sore throat, but if your symptoms move below the neck, then you should not train. I've never actually asked a doctor about this before, and I've always been curious because I always get upper respiratory tract infections. I get really bad sinus infections probably once a year, and I've always thought, should I train through this? Should I not train through this? I've never really had a good answer, and I've done both, and I don't think there's...
I don't know the answer. So what do you think? Generally speaking, is that a good rule of thumb or not? Yes, it is. So that's what we call the neck check. So for example, if you still have more overall symptoms that affect your full body, like fever or myalgia, like muscle pain, chest pain, or resting tachycardia. So myalgia is muscle pain?
Yes. So the symptoms that are below your neck, I would say, that's a strong sign that you should avoid and go for full resting. And one interesting observation here is that some people tend to say, oh, maybe you don't go for that two hour or three hour long ride cycling workout, but you may go for a 30 minute workout at the gym. No, ideally you should. We don't have a lot of, again,
There's a lot of evidence about if it's safer to go for a gym, but based on what we have, the best decision is to take a day off, maybe a few days off. Why? Because the sooner you stop spending your hand.
Precious Energy on your exercise and the body will have more energy to invest, I would say, on the immune system and then it will speed up your recovery and avoid some consequences of doing exercise before you get rid of the below the neck symptoms. Yeah, like I...
I'll tell a quick story here where I my first serious cross season, I think I did like 20 races in like the span of two months to two and a half months, something like that. I was pretty much racing like twice a weekend or once or twice a weekend for a while. And I had a really bad cough when I started and I just didn't stop. And and it got really, really, really, really bad. I wanted to race a full cross season, but like if I.
kept going like I had. I was really just going to dig myself into a horrible hole. And it really took me like probably a month and a half, two months to like get over that cough because I was told it was walking pneumonia, which I don't know if that was, you know, I think it was like from the ER visit or something like that because it was really, really bad. So the lesson is don't do that, right?
Exactly, yeah, and that's a mistake that we are always trying to avoid because the sooner you stop exercising and rest yourself, make sure you are well hydrated and eating what you have to do, a balanced diet, the sooner you get better and the sooner you can get back to training, return to play and also return to competition because if you don't that...
Soon Enough. What you risk is that it is exactly what you just said. You can get a worse infection, worse illness, and then it will take much more time to recover from that. And then you are really risking your season maybe for a few months. And that's what we want to avoid as a...
Athletes, coaches, and doctors. Yeah, and the training gets really, really bad when you're like half sick too. Like one of my athletes this year...
He was half sick. He couldn't quite kick a cough. I was pulling the training back as we went, and he was like, yeah, I'm good to train. It was just one of those things where I should have just rested. That's one of those things where I'm usually a very conservative coach, and I wasn't that time because there were some big goals coming up, and that was actually the wrong call. Yeah, so exactly what you're talking about. It's better to pull it back and rest.
But I think this actually brings up another interesting point, though, which is that the immune system does take a lot of energy, right? Or it seems to. Yes. Because, like, especially when people are training really, really, really hard, you know, after their peak performance, a lot of folks get sick. And there was actually that famous marathon study where they followed marathon runners, and the people who trained for it and didn't actually run it got sick at a much lower rate. You remember that one, right?
Yeah, and we have some conflicts on the literature about how much, and for example, the training load that many people monitor these days. You probably heard about the J-curve also, which is... I've not actually, no. No, it's a J-curve, just like the letter, and for a long time it's supposed to...
to say if you are really untrained, you are more prone to get colds and flus. And once you get some training, you go to the bottom of the curve, which means on the y-axis is how much you get sick, and on the x-axis is how much you are trained. And then so once you go a little bit more trained, you get a little bit more protection, especially
At these days, we tend to look more at modern training, but as you go and you increase your training load, you get more and more, you start to go up on the J curve. So you start to reach your limits. So as you get more training load, more workload from each workout, you tend to overload your immune system more often than would like. So that's where we are reaching that.
Peak performance for a race for example but at the same time we are pushing the limits on the intensity on the volume and also trying to reach our best performance but that may have a price which is to become more susceptible for like infections respiratory infections and one interesting aspect of this J curve is that recently they have
I studied elite level athletes and actually they proposed another letter for their curve which is the S curve. So the S curve means that the elite level athletes may be more protected when they are more trained compared to amateur.
Athletes, which means the more they train, they may be more susceptible to infections. So at the end, what we may take as a take-home message is amateur athletes are very different from elite levels, not just in the performance levels, but maybe also how they recover and how their immune system deals with all the stressors, the training stress, the life stress.
which is usually higher on the amateur athletes how they have to cope with that and also nutrition wise which is actually a point that's very important how our body is dealing with all the energy levels and all the energy availability so maybe the elite level
Athletes have a better management of that energy levels and energy ingestion or availability compared to amateur athletes of course these are not perfect and that may not fit everyone but that's what the literature has been showing us lately that the elite level athletes may have a different approach and a different
Way to adapt to high performance and high volume, high intensity workouts compared to amateur or master athletes. Yeah, well, it makes sense that especially with amateurs that the life stress off the bike will really cause a compromise of your immune system because, I mean, this is something that I think we all have.
And generally, in our anecdotal experiences, when you're really, really stressed and you're also trying to train really hard, you always get that little sniffle or you always get that headache or whatever it is, especially if you're not sleeping well or you're not hydrating well or you're not eating well or the list goes on and on. And actually, I've heard about this in interviews with elite athletes, elite cyclists anyway, where they say,
When you're in really, really good shape, you can actually recover from crashes and illness a lot faster as long as you take that time off. And so even anecdotally for them, it seems like they've had a similar experience. And to them, being in shape is really, really good for recovering from illness somehow. Exactly. And the link to that, if you think about a flu or a cold, for example, and there are some...
Changes in our physiology that may, for example, here we have some complications of exercising when you have a fever. Besides the systemic symptoms like headache, muscle pain and joint pain, you also may have a higher risk for dehydration because you tend to sweat more and it seems like there is a diminished
Production of ADH, which is a diuretic hormone, which regulates how much you pee or you produce of urine. And then we also... So it makes you produce more urine? Less. Actually, more. You're right. Oh, so it makes you produce more urine. Okay. Yeah. So there is also some...
publications that show that during the fever, there is a higher protein catabolism, which is the breakdown of proteins, which is very important for your muscle because our immune system, immune cells need more amino acids and also more glucose to fight the infection. So that may lead to another nutritional deficiency, which is based on, again, more amino acids for immune cells, less
Availability of glucose and also we found in some studies the increase of peripheral vascular resistance which means as you know when you are exercising you need more blood to the muscles that are active so if you have an infection and it makes it harder to have this blood on the muscles and that may explain why some studies found up to a 25% reduction in endurance capacity and also
and some changes to the cardiovascular system, which you are very famous because of the VO2. Let's hold up there for a second. So a 25% reduction in endurance capacity, so that would be a test where they have somebody ride at 75% VO2 max, for instance, and if normally you can do that for 100 minutes, a 25% reduction would be like you can only do that for 75 minutes when you're sick, right?
Or you may have to reduce the intensity to tolerate for an hour. Right, right. Okay. And actually, I've talked about this in a couple of articles recently, I think, where fatigue just in general and being ill can manifest pretty much the same as fatigue, where your RPE, your perceived exertion for a given effort level will be...
And like normally if you can do 2x20 and that's like an 8 out of 10 and then you can do 2x20 and, you know, but it's like it becomes like a 10 out of 10 or you can only do like 1x20 and that's also like an 8 out of 10 then you can't do the other one, etc, etc. Like there's a lot of ways for a director capacity to be reduced. But actually I also want to...
Before we get back to that, I also want to touch on the nutrition thing. So do you have any nutritional recommendations for people when they're ill? Because I know a lot of people, you know, we generally get the advice like have chicken soup and hydrate. But, you know, is there any kind of truth to that kind of received wisdom from our mothers? Or, you know, is there other stuff that we can do as well?
Yes, and especially these days when we have several athletes that are playing or changing their nutritional reference, like with low carb or low fat or all these variations that we see around these days for diet. The studies that we have seen before regarding how, for example, carbohydrates influence show that, for example, there is a
A strong correlation between how much carbs you ingest and how that affect your immune system. Really? So, yes. They found that people, for example, that ingest the general recommendation, which is fluids like 6% of carbs solutions or fluids or even gels or whatever. Okay, so something like Scratch Mix or something like that.
Exactly. They tend to have a lower incidence of upper respiratory illnesses. Is that from the hydration or is that from the carbs or is it from like all of it and the electrolytes and better hydration or whatnot? Probably both, the carbs and the fluids. And then if you think in this link, that would apply also when you're sick.
So if you are sick you tend to be more dehydrated and also to have to need more glucose for the immune cells so the current science says that if you if you are sick don't try to be on a diet to lose weight for example make sure you are well rested before and eating a well-balanced diet include carbs and once you are
Well recovered from the illness, then you may consider going back to low carb again diet if you are that kind of athlete that enjoys or seems like it works for you. At least during the illness, I would recommend raising the carbohydrates diet and then reevaluate. So this is why, you know, chicken soup and crackers is actually a pretty good...
A pretty good recipe for helping to get better because you get electrolytes and hydration and you get some carbs and there you go. Or whatever soup, depending on your diet, I suppose. Sorry, vegetarians. Well, if you think about other countries, there might be other combinations for where they get most of the carbs. Like in Brazil, it's beans and rice. It's very common.
What also about protein? Because you mentioned that the protein breakdown rate is increased because, you know, immune cells, obviously, like you're making cells, you obviously need protein load. And, you know, the muscles are a very large and easily accessible place to get protein. Like, you know, if you see people who are starving, you know, they don't have, you know, they're not jacked. Like, they're very, very slim. They have very small muscles, especially if they've been...
Starving for a while, and that's where the body seems to get a lot of protein. So is there a protein recommendation while you're ill, just like normal amount, or do different types of proteins make a difference that you're aware of? Yeah, they have looked at, especially with some specific supplements for glutamine or some other amino acids, and although some report a positive effect on prevention, for example, at the end, the overall
recommendation is balanced diet. These days, I think the biggest concern we have as a doctor is the extremes where people may go like really low on carbs or maybe too much protein if they have their choices for what we will then get instead of the carbs. And for me, at least, and my experience in the clinics is having a well-balanced diet.
especially when you are sick and you need to recover is the best way I don't think any supplement is even like vitamin C or vitamin D they have some conflicting results on the literature and
if you have a well-balanced and access to a well-balanced diet usually is associated with rest and good hydration it should be enough for your fast recovery especially if you are well-trained as you mentioned before which it really accelerates everything and then get back to normal training and if you have a specific diet that may have some restrictions for weight loss or other aspects for like losing weight for a race and then you may
Reconsider that, at least in my experience, I would avoid extreme diets at this point if you are sick or have a illness. Yeah, so you also mentioned vitamin C and D, but especially vitamin C, a lot of folks seem to think it's going to actually help cure your cold or something like that.
In my experience in the literature, if something has equivocal results, if it's like 50-50, like half studies show some effect, half studies show no effect, it's probably just like flipping a coin. And it probably means that it's random chance. It's probably not going to help that much. And so really you're saying like...
Really stick to the simple stuff, like have a good diet. And actually, speaking of good diet, what about fats? Because I know that fats are really necessary for hormones, especially steroid hormones and D, A, K, and E. Some people like to cut out fats from their diet. I don't know why. But do you have any recommendations for fats intake for...
Or has the literature looked at it for anything? Like is there like a danger to having low fats or like too much fats, you know, other than like at the expensive carbohydrates or like is that the whole point is like just keep it balanced? Well, that's a good question because what I, again, what I am always worried is when I have an...
I'm following an athlete and he has these extreme diets like no fats or very low fat and as you mentioned well fats are important for the production of many hormones in our body and then I think a well-trained athlete that maybe already had like a low fat on his body composition with a low percentage of his body being fat if he again if he get
Sick, have a cold or a flu, maybe at least for that period I would again go get back to the well-balanced diet, healthy fatties, fatties that are healthier and like mono, not unsaturated fats like olive oil or from wild fish if you have the access to that and make sure you get
Really what's healthy from like some fruits and like avocado has good oils too. And that should be enough for you to get healthy again, get back, return to play. And then again, if you want to apply a restriction after you are in good health, that may be the case. Okay, cool. And so let's also talk about the general immune response.
because I haven't looked into this myself because obviously the immune system to me is actually terrifying because it's so complicated and you've had a lot more time with it than I have. So are the symptoms that we get when we are sick, like are most of those symptoms our immune system or like is some of that actually from an illness actually affecting how our body can function?
Excellent question and actually that's a discussion in the science because one thing that we don't know for example let's say you just completed a high intensity workout and after the high intensity workout you know there is like some injuries to the muscle fibers to many cells in your body because you are overloading them and then comes the question what's coming after this exercise boost high intensity especially is it
Inflammation because of the exercise or is it a problem because you overloaded your energy availability for example for carbs and proteins because that's going to be used on the recovery of the tissues like muscle tissue and then you have a decreased availability from glucose and carbs and amino acids for example for the immune system and then
It might be more prone to get an infection. And we don't know that yet. We are starting trying to understand this complex interrelation between immune system, physiology, the inflammation of the recovery. And, you know, there's a lot of discussion these days on diets that promote...
Inflammation, diets that help avoid inflammation and how you can recover faster if you have a diet that promotes, it's less... Reduces inflammation, yeah.
Yeah, reduces inflammation. And then, so we really don't have this discussion done yet. So it's a work in progress, but it's a really important question because it may dictate, for example, these days there is a strong body of evidence, especially with probiotics showing
Good and promising results on the information side and also the, for example, to avoid the recurrent illnesses or sickness and long term. So there is certainly a play between the immune system, the germs that live in your gut and how our diet can change that for good or for bad. But still, it's a recent work and we need more data and more information.
to get to the point where we can make more consistent and decisive recommendations. Also, you brought up inflammation too, and I was actually going to save this for another podcast and we can probably get into it another time. But since you touched on it, the post-exercise inflammation, I think a lot of people are actually terrified of inflammation in a lot of the time because it sounds like a big scary thing.
What's the difference between normal post-exercise inflammation and a chronic condition where it requires real medical treatment? Because my impression is that inflammation is just blood flow to tissue to clean up things, etc. And chronic inflammation that needs medical intervention is a condition that doesn't...
There's no like downtime. There's no like it's fixed. Now we can rest like after exercise, presumably. So what's the difference there? Well, the difference is that once you exercise and you again have the tissue injuries or like micro injuries that some people say is that that's actually what we need for our body to adapt and become stronger.
for a bigger overload in the next session or in the next month or in the next season. And actually, people have measured what changes after exercise or when you are sick. And there is, of course, a change in neutrophils or like the immune cells, lymphocytes, even the ratio between neutrophils and lymphocytes. Oh, these are scary words to me. Hold on. This is why I don't study the immune system.
So just real quick, so like those cells, like lymphocytes and neutrophils, you said? Yes. So like their function is like normal immune function, like they attack like six cells or damaged cells and clean them up, or like what's their exact function? Yes, that's our defense cells, so they are very complicated, there are several.
kinds and subtypes that are present in our body. And as you said, well, it's a very complicated... Yeah, we can stop right there. But yeah, they do both works. They maintain the tissues, healthy state, and also they fight the infections. For example, just a curious example. When you eat something, a lot of the pathogens or the germs... Sorry, pathogens?
Okay, yeah, just double-checking, all right. Okay, they cross the barrier in the gut, and people don't realize that. And the barrier goes to the bloodstream? Yeah. And does it also go to the lymph system, or no? Actually, they go to the liver. Oh, okay. Oh, right, right, right. And once they get there, we have, like, these specialized cells, the coupler or the mycophage cells. They are so efficient that less than 1% of the...
the germs or the pathogen that cross the barrier will actually get to the circulation. So then you think about how all the time that we are exercising and then also our nutrition and how it relates to our immune system. There must be this correlation of inflammation because the immune cells are the cells that are
Responsible for the inflammation, which is a physiological response after tissue injuries, even if it's like a wound or if you're just trained and was like a high intense training. And the limitation we have these days is that we don't have, at least the technology is not there yet, on ways to measure that.
Because if we had that technology, we could go to a lab every day and measure the ratio between natural fuels and lymphocytes. Yeah, maybe for elite level athletes, they do that. But for the average population, we don't. And then it's really difficult to find out when, for example,
Can you do three days in a row of high intensity workouts and be okay? Maybe you need just to one day and then an easy day and then again another hard day and then you can adjust the workload based on a weekly basis or daily basis based on how each immune system which is very different from person to person.
How they react to the inflammation after the exercise, which is a physiological system for recovery. And also the tendency to be more prone to get pathogens when you are recovering from a workout, which is no one wants, right? So what would be a good recommendation for somebody to do this at home to think, you know, how's my immune system reacting to really hard work? Like is the next day they just...
Would you expect they don't feel good? Or could they feel good and the workout's not great? Or what would be a good rule of thumb or a good way for somebody to guide themselves through that? Well, you know, a hard workout will always be hurtful, right? It always hurts. And you always think the next day, why I did that?
My suggestion and what I do with my athletes is always listen to your body. You see how, for example, how the performance is changing from day from after a high intense workout to the next day. Can you do another one without being sick and start to, especially if you work with a coach, start to discuss and that's where
I always tell my athletes very important after you finish the workout to really write down how you felt during the workout what were you feeling at the beginning at the end because with that information plus the objective data which is power heart rate or speed cadence whatever you can join the piece together
And as a coach you can decide, okay, this athlete usually handles this much of high-intensity workouts during a week. And that may change with family stressors or work stressors that may come up at some point. But if you don't have a clear communication with your coach or yourself, it's going to be hard for you to say, okay, it's time to back off. And it's usually when...
You have these type A personality athletes that push really hard and then they don't want to listen to their body and they think if they don't train hard they will lose their performance or their ability to go strong and actually they are doing the inverse. I always tell my athletes when they have an easy ride.
Today is when you get stronger, not when you are doing the hard workout. I love that. That's great. Actually, I don't know, in the last two weeks, I've told this story a couple times where I was actually consulting for a very, very type A athlete. And he was like, I do all the workouts to the T. I do them exactly the way they're written. And sometimes if I feel okay, I'll do a little more. So you're always going to get exactly what I'm given.
And then we start talking about his off-the-bike habits and...
and they were really not good. And I had to tell him, like, look, you think you're doing 100% of the training and you're only doing 50% of the training because off the bike is the other 50% of the training and you're basically at like 10% of that. And that is what's really going to drive your performance to the next level. And he actually didn't really want to hear that. But I couldn't not tell him because I...
The off-bike stuff is really so important. Reading your own body and your method of feedback is pretty much the same thing that I do and that Alex does and that my new assistant coach does. Everybody at Empirical Cycling is on the same page. This is obviously one of the reasons that I thought you'd be a good fit here, and you are. Also, coaching inquiries, get in touch. Fabiano's awesome. Great.
It's, you know, my girlfriend and I lately haven't, we've got this joke about, it takes more mental toughness to get yourself to rest than it does to do hard work. I agree. Yeah, like we joke about that, but like we really mean it, like it takes more mental toughness to do that. So the next thing I want to touch on actually is what
Can people do like, what's the best way to manage being sick? Like, because I know you're going to say prevention is to not get sick in the first place. So what methods would you tell somebody?
to not get sick in the first place. Like does, you know, obviously like, you know, all the stuff that we've learned during COVID, like, you know, should you wear a mask outside, for instance, if you don't want to get sick? Or, you know, is that more so you don't get to get other people sick? Like what's the deal with that? Should you wash your hands so much? You know, what should you do? Like does dieting make people prone to being sick? You know, travel on airplanes, going to like movie theaters now that that's starting to happen again here in the U.S. Like what are your, like what recommendations do you have?
very broadly and baby specifically. Okay, so that's very similar to what we have been saying all the time during the COVID-19 pandemics, which is frequent hand washing. If you have a chance, use masks indoors because, you know, it's a respiratory infection. And actually, that's a good point because most of the infections...
that elite athletes get, for example, during the Olympic Games are respiratory infections. So that's why we tend to... And then the second one is gastrointestinal infections from the gut. So also applies some of the same concepts. So like food poisoning kind of stuff? Yes. And so avoid contact between hands, eyes, and nose, which applies the same for COVID. If possible, if you are going to sneeze or...
Cough, cover your mouth and nose with your capital fossa, the elbow. So that avoids to spread all the germs. Yeah, because I see people coughing into their hands and it's like, oh God, wash it, wash it. Then they go touch something. I'm like, I got to leave the store. Exactly. Yeah, don't need to be.
So extreme, but yeah, if you cuff to your hand, go wash it and then wash maybe the surfaces or apply some alcohol and make sure you clean it or ethanol. And then if you are like on a sports team, try to avoid sharing water bottles, towels and equipment. And also...
One last recommendation is, many people don't like that, but avoid excessive and binge drinking after winning a race, for example.
Yeah, the alcohol really impairs the immune function for several hours and especially after some external training or intense exercise or competition and that's usually when people want to celebrate, right? Just want a really tough competition and they want to celebrate which is not a problem but if you do
Be moderate, if that's the same recommendation. Actually, I have a funny story about my own stupidity. Again, this is how I learn lessons. I remember back in the mid-aughts or the late aughts, I forget when it was exactly, but it was when bird flu was in the U.S. And it wasn't...
The death toll wasn't nearly as bad as with coronavirus. And so I remember when it was in universities, their recommendation was just stay in your dorm, don't go anywhere. And so I think I had it because I was sicker than I've ever been for like a week straight. I was out of work and I had all the muscle soreness. I had a high fever, but I was doing okay. I didn't need to go to the hospital. But after a week, I thought I was completely through it.
and I had a beer to celebrate. And by the time I was done drinking the beer, I was as sick as I was again on like the first day. Again, I was like, oh my, it took me another week to recover. And I always wondered like, you know, could one beer really screw up your immune system if you're like recovering? And my anecdotal evidence is like, absolutely. But I didn't know that it was like really that strong an effect. So that shocked me. Yeah, yeah. It's something.
People don't say a lot. And actually, I made deeper research some time ago because I had to give an interview about this topic. And actually, there is no safe recommendation for alcohol. Really? So zero is the recommendation? Zero. Yeah. There is no one single document, at least at the point when I searched for it, that had a safe recommendation for alcohol. We discuss a lot about the wine and drinking moderate amounts of alcohol.
Still, no one made or could make a safe assumption that there is like a safe minimum amount until these days for alcohol. Right. Well, unless you find some biased publication, but that doesn't count, right? Well, I hope not. Yeah. But, well, you know how some folks are. Not everybody. Most people are pretty knowledgeable about this stuff. But every once in a while, somebody goes, well, it was published. I mean, therefore, it's awesome, right? It's true fact, right? I was like, ah.
Maybe not, never mind. Okay, so I have just a couple more questions. The first one is when somebody does get sick and they're coming back into training, what is your recommendation to gauge if somebody's ready to actually train harder again? Or should you have a slow buildup? What if somebody's off the bike for like...
Do you find that there's a difference between one or two days or if somebody's off the bike for a week or if somebody's out for longer? Yes, we have recommendations for that. Actually, once you get rid of the below-the-neck symptoms, so muscle pain, myalgia, and chest, cough, whatever you have below the neck.
it's usually you are no fever you are allowed to go back return to play and train and the return should be gradual so start always start with easy recover rides once my one of my athletes got back from the sickness or illness so I really go short
like maybe just 30 minutes and really like fun rides just go have fun with your bike or for running running is really always a little bit more stressful than cycling for example but still and then try to really make it easy and then if you feel okay next day we progress maybe 15 minutes then more 15 and then we progress as again based on the athletes feedback
I'm feeling okay, I'm feeling good, and sometimes what may happen is exactly what happened with you after that fear. They may feel okay, go for a workout, and they get really bad again. And then again, stop, no training, even gym, just focus on hydration, your diet, get rest, and actually...
Coming back to the prevention, some teams and that's actually what some amateur athletes should do also is stress managing. Do some training on how to cope with stress because you can change the stress that will be coming up all the time. But depending on how you deal with stress, they have this interesting research some time ago that
made I think was four groups and they were comparing how people react to death and the sense they may die some point and actually they found out that the ones that were really believing that they would get sick although they had no risk factors to be sick from cardiovascular events for example they really got sick oh just because you imagine how powerful our brain is and then
That stress management, you know, everybody's submitted to similar stress Oh, because you have a systemic stress response and that actually puts your body more into the fight or flight mode and that actually reduces immune system activity Exactly, that's what, I mean, they couldn't find like a causal relationship, but they found that people that didn't know how to react
to the stressors of their life or relieving it were like, oh, I really suffer more. The problems are bigger on my side, something like that. They really had more cardiovascular events later in the study. Interesting. Even if they were like no problems with BMI, the weight or diabetes or whatever risk factor you may consider for sedentary life, for example, they were still paying a higher price just because they
believe they were at higher risk. And one last one is maybe the use of probiotics, as I said some time ago in this episode. So what would be like a probiotic? Would that be like a kombucha or a yogurt or something like that? I would say the yogurt is like the cheapest and more easier access. Then, of course, you have some really higher price, more specialized probiotics that they sell you. But if you are just trying to
Again, include that into your regular diet. Your goods are probably the best option. Okay, cool. Awesome. So I think actually one of the last things I wanted to touch on here is before the podcast, you and I had talked about a lot of the data that we have on illness is actually from Olympic athletes and not amateur athletes. And we had kind of touched on this before with...
Amateur versus elite athletes and sickness. So is there like a bias in the literature almost where there's a lot of data on the highest level athletes and there's not so much on amateurs? Yes. It's very limited amount of data that we have on how to do the prevention, how to treat and even return to play. An elite athlete will have all the
Possibilities most of the time to speed up his recover and get back to play sooner than the others. And when you think about the amateur athlete, he's sick, he has family, he has his job and also maybe not access to the well-balanced diet that elite level athletes have. And then you have to consider that when you are working with an amateur or a master athlete that it may take longer for him to recover and that don't
just try to push him as you may see on Instagram with other athletes that recover which are elite level and they may have access to faster recover techniques just because they have this access so again if you are working with amateur they may take longer because of how they have to access to other solutions compared to elite level and also because we don't have
Data for that specific for them. And that's similar to what we have these days on COVID. Most of the data regarding return to play on the COVID-19 is on public or people that are not like young athletes. So they might have different approach risk factors compared to younger athletes. And then when we have to take the decision on should
Is he allowed or not to get back to training? You don't have all the pieces of the puzzle yet because we don't really have enough data from elite level or younger athletes to judge the exams and the clinical state of the athlete if it was like asymptomatic or mild or moderate was he hospitalized or...
had some cardiovascular events. So it's a work in progress and the same applies even if you think just about cold or flu, not all the information is very broad, the public that was studied before.
Yeah. Actually, I wanted to ask you about Remco Evanpole, because he famously crashed really hard, and I think he said in an interview he had been trying to lose weight during his recovery, and that it had delayed his recovery. So that's the kind of thing where I think a lot of folks might go, oh, well, why would he do that? Or some folks would go,
Oh my God, I've tried to do that and I've delayed my own recovery. So are there any other famous examples you know of elite athletes or even amateur athletes where there's a good object lesson in recovery mistakes or successes even?
I have some cold at the beginning we were believing but his recovery is taking longer than what we would like to so I might actually send this podcast to him at the end and
That's maybe one of the challenges of remote coaching because you don't really can see the athlete and maybe make a more appropriate judgment on when to take a day off or a few days off and we have been really conservative but in my opinion it's taking longer than it should be and actually just today I discussed with him maybe we need a few days off even though
No light training. And then that all comes back. You mentioned a good point on the weight loss story is when you think about weight loss, it's better to do when the training is on the lower intensity because the toll on the immune system is lower.
and you are already on a caloric deficit, so it may increase your chances that you will not get sick because of the caloric deficit. And once you have an injury and you need this energy for the recovery of the tissues and you do some weight loss diet, that's counterintuitive. You should probably avoid that because you need that energy to fix the tissues and then after that may consider it.
weight loss. All right. So my very last question is, so what did you learn during your PhD on the differences between men and women in the brain and angiotensin system? The studies I did were really, really basic on the cellular level and also on the computer simulations. But we found out that there are some proteins that are specific to men like SRY and ones that are
shared between men and women, like the SOX family is where the SRY belongs to. So the SRY is just in men, doesn't exist in women. Because it's on the Y chromosome. Exactly. So it's on the Y chromosome. But there are other proteins that are similar that are on women and men. And we were able to find that...
at least on cellular level we need more clinical and human studies to prove our theories that there is a different regulation of the renin-angiotensin system at the promoter level of these genes which is our and as you know this system is like fundamental to
keep some aspects of the cardiovascular system, like the stroke volume, the blood volume, and because they regulate at the kidney level how much urine you do, how much you filter of your blood, and if we are seeing difference between the regulation of these genes in men and women, it may explain why there are some difference, for example, in the incidence of hypertension.
which is a disease derived from a misregulation of the brain. Well, in some cases, a misregulation of the brain energy system. Right, because somebody has so much blood volume that it's causing their cardiac hypertrophy, but their heart never gets a chance to rest and recover. Is that more or less right for hypertension? Yeah.
Well, there are many changes in hypertension. For example, increased vascular resistance, peripheral. Oh, so the heart has to work harder to pump the blood. Yeah, and then you have a higher pressure to weigh the pressure or the resistance at the vessels. So that's why, for example, the changes you have on your heart when you have hypertension is different from when you have the changes from exercising.
Usually the ones from the hypertension are not beneficial for your heart because they get thicker but the chamber inside gets smaller compared to the exercise when the muscle grows also but the chamber grows also that's how you get more stroke volume more cardiac output during the exercise and then that's why important for example especially men
If you have a higher risk factor for hypertension to check your pressure frequently and if you need medicine or do more exercise and then avoid the risk factors associated with sedentary life or lack of exercise and then get the beneficial changes that you get from exercise.
doing especially endurance exercise for your heart and also, of course, your performance. Did you get to the point of learning anything that would lead to differential recommendations for anything between men and women from what you learned in your PhD? Yes. But again, as you know, in biology,
the more you study the more you learn how complex the system is and that's just for for you to have an idea we again we don't have the technology on there that's readily available for everyone to check if you think about the gene in the promoter region how it is regulated to be expressed or not we have a
Bunch of proteins that, and I was studying just one of them. And so it's usually not just one, it's a lot of proteins that combine. Yeah, there could be like 8, 10, 12 protein complexes to transcribe a gene. And for people listening, a promoter region is another region of DNA that links up onto one of the, I think it's the transcription factor, while it's transcribing the gene and will upregulate the number of transcriptions of the gene.
Verical, correct. Exactly. And also the renin-angiotensin system, we tend to just remember about renin-angiotensin 1 and 2, but these days there are many more proteins or peptides that are active and being studied and makes the history much more complex about how we check them and how we may interfere with them to be...
healthier or live longer without his factors in this case. All right. That's our episode. Thank you, everybody, for listening. I don't think I need to put a big bow on this one. That was a great episode. So thank you, Fabiano, for coming on. And if you all want to hear me and Fabiano talk more later, well, mostly me asking Fabiano questions and dropping knowledge on us all.
you know that's going to be awesome so if you want to hear any particular topics shoot me an email empiricalcycling at gmail.com or if you want to work with Fabiano also shoot me an email and we will get you all in touch otherwise the usual stuff share the podcast iTunes and empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com and Instagram at empiricalcycling and with that I will see you all next time we are hopefully having a new Wattstock episode coming out very soon