Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm not your host today, but I am still Kolie Moore. Kyle Helson's going to be hosting for 10-Minute Tips, and we are doing an extended 10-Minute Tips from now on, so we are no longer in the 10-minute time frame, as you may have noticed from the track. That's okay. I think the episodes are going to be better for it.
So as always, thank you for listening and please subscribe to the podcast and especially share it with a friend if you like what we're doing here, if you like the kind of episodes you're hearing, and especially if you think there's some relevant information that needs to go around.
Remember that we're also an ad-free podcast, so if you want to donate to the podcast, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We have no show notes up for this episode on the website, but the website is empiricalcycling.com. We have some merch at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com. And if you have any coaching and consultation inquiries, questions, or comments, you can email me directly at empiricalcycling at gmail.com. We also have an Instagram AMAs in the weekend, so give me a follow at empiricalcycling, obviously.
if you want to participate in that. And those have been going really well. That's been a lot of fun. So looking forward to your questions. And with that, I'm going to let Kyle take it away. Welcome, everyone. I'm your host this week, Kyle Helson. Cole has the day off. So this week, I want to give everyone some tips and kind of talk about some good methods and things to keep in mind when you are reading a scientific paper and really trying to digest it.
Astute listeners will know that we talk about a lot of different papers and sometimes you talk about papers more than once and so we want to help give everyone some tips for reading papers if you want to go off and find the papers that we talk about and read them yourselves or if you want to find new papers or if you're just new and you're new to reading scientific literature and you don't have an extensive background in scientific reading.
So when you're trying to digest a scientific paper, there are generally four goals, and any of them can be applicable sort of any time. The big one is you want to explain the meaning or the interest behind the problem being studied. So this is like the big picture. Like, this paper is investigating whether high-intensity intervals are good for VO2 max, period. That's one sentence. It's a nice short.
Takeaway. That's what this paper is looking for. Number two, you want to explain the methods or the data or the analysis tools that the authors used. So for example, you might say, oh, this paper looked at whether doing five by five minute intervals were better, or this paper looked at whether doing 30-30s were better. And then to measure whether or not one of these
Methods was better, they used a ramp test, or they used an FTP test, or they used a one minute test, something like that. So you want to be able to say they used this metric to see whether the improvements or the changes they were looking for actually occurred. Number three, you want to explain the meaning of the results. So that would be saying like, according to this study, and if you use this
protocol, you should expect to see a change or you should expect to see no change in a certain quantity or quality. So say 3030s, you would expect to see little change in FTP or, you know, five by five minutes, you would expect to see a bigger change in five minute power or something like that. And then you would want to lastly be able to look
at the larger picture and see where this sort of nugget fits in. So if this is VO2 max training, if this study is looking at VO2 max training, how does this VO2 max training sort of fit in with your larger training plans as a whole? How does this fit into larger physiological systems as a whole? How does this fit into a season planning or race specific planning? You want to be able to relate the gist and the nugget of that paper back to the larger picture.
So at some point, especially if you're really, really steeped in a sub-discipline, you can pick up a paper from that sub-discipline and spend a fairly small amount of time reading it in almost a formulaic manner and get the gist. And that is because you are so well-versed in the background and the techniques generally used in your field that it doesn't take you a lot of time to...
get to the bottom and then internalize the conclusions of this paper. But I want to stress that this is not something that is easy, but this is not something people are born with. This is a learned practiced skill. And like any learned practiced skill, the more you do it, the better you become. And also, there are some things that can be scary about reading papers. Like you get into a paper and then you think, oh my goodness, like,
I don't know what this word means or I don't know what is going on. That's okay. You can stop. You can go back and you can reread sections or reread the whole paper or start from the beginning or go back to a previous section as many times as it takes for you to actually understand the logical chain that flows from one section of the paper to the next. Especially if you start to see a lot of words you don't understand or definitions you don't understand.
that's also an opportunity for you to stop and go look up other papers or other works or look at the references that the paper cites to help you understand or help you gain that baseline knowledge needed to digest this paper so very much so keep in mind that reading a scientific paper it's not a linear read from start to finish it's not like a novel it can be very much a
An iterative process as you read a section, digest it, go on to the next section. Okay, well, once you go into the next section, maybe that will tell you what are the more important takeaways from the previous section. So then you go back to the previous section and read that again. Okay, now I see. And now you sort of pick up the logical chain from there. So one of the first things you can do if you pick up a paper that you've never seen before and you're interested in because of the title or the abstract, look at the authors.
Usually you look at the authors, you see if you recognize any of the names. Sometimes that can help you set the scene for the paper because you know this author has a certain specialty. So for example, if you pick up a paper by a well-known muscle physiologist like Keith Barr, well okay, so this is probably going to be about muscle cells or muscle fiber types or things like that. It's probably not going to be about VO2 max or threshold training.
so that alone can sort of set in your mind okay now think about the things that you'll need to know to kind of get in and really dive into this paper. Typically you'll start off then by reading the abstract but also reading the first part of the introduction to make sure that the background that you have is sufficient to keep going.
you know the maybe the scary thing is if you read the abstract and you start reading introduction if all of a sudden the first three sentences in you don't understand the gist of any of the first few sentences well then maybe you know that you need to go and you need to look at some papers that came before or some of the papers that this paper references so you can build up your basal level of knowledge and then this will also help you put that
Bring background knowledge to work and allow you to set the context for this paper once you expand your background knowledge a little bit. I understand this can start being a rabbit hole and that you end up going back and back and back and back until you have to read 10,000 pages of something, but hopefully it isn't going to be that difficult and you can find a few other papers that maybe you can skim or maybe the sections that you can read from other papers to help you out. Now if there's a theory section in this paper, depending on how familiar you're with the topic, you may or may not
be able to speed, sort of speed skim the section and move on. If you're not familiar with the subfield, if you're not familiar with the discipline, then this section you're going to have to spend more time on. Whereas if this is a subfield or your discipline that you really know, well then maybe you can spend a little bit less time on this because you know the details behind this phenomenon or this measurement technique or this protocol that they're using.
and if ever there's going to be a lot of math likely in this section of the papers where you're going to find that math so whether you like math I like math whether you like math or not just as a heads up this is where it could appear in the first place at least this is one of the first places it could appear so now the sort of methods or analysis section is typically next and this is where you you find out kind of
One of the things that might make this paper special or interesting, like, oh, check out, they have this new protocol for measuring your FTP, or they have a new style of intervals that they think are going to make a big difference in your VO2 max or something like that. And this is another place where you can actually double check whether you think the authors are using a metric or a tool
to come to the conclusions that you think is appropriate. So for example, if I say, oh, in this paper, I'm going to use a one minute all out test to estimate FTP. Well, that's when you can start being a little suspicious and say, hey, maybe I don't agree with the conclusion at the end because they use this metric or this tool that I think is maybe inappropriate. And these are the reasons why.
Also, if this paper is one in a series or if this is a follow-up to something else, this is where you can sort of tell and you can compare the methods or analysis in this paper to ones in the past that you've read or ones that you've seen or ones that you've heard about. So for example, say if I'm writing a high-intensity interval training paper and I want to follow up the famous Tabata study where they looked at 20 seconds on, 10 seconds rest for four minutes, four rounds.
and I want to say I'm going to look at a study doing 40 seconds on 20 seconds off for 10 minutes well then maybe in this section is where I would cite the Tabata study and say this is a modified or a scaled up version of that. So this is also one of the first sections that you can start to see some really important
assumptions or some really important implied conditions that may or may not be expressly stated. And this is because certain methods or techniques or tools can have built-in assumptions into their use. And this may take a little bit more knowledge, but you want to make sure that the methods or the tools or the metrics being used for this analysis are
applicable or are true for this given study or this paper. So as an example, if you use a 20 minute FTP test to estimate someone's one minute power, well, you can say, well, I know that 20 minute tests aren't really testing the same physiological properties as a
As one minute power does so I would be a little suspicious like this test doesn't really match up with this stated goal. The next section is going to be the data and the results section and this is probably where you're gonna find the plots and this is probably where you're gonna spend the most time digesting the plots or the tables and the actual information presented. One of the things you can do is
you can read the paper and if it references a figure make sure you know where that figure is and you look at the figure and then when you look at the figure read the caption the caption isn't always going to be new information sometimes it will be a clarifying point to what the text was referencing but sometimes it will contain new information or explain the plot in more detail or the table in more detail so you want to make sure you read the figure captions
So you want to look at a plot and the first thing you'll see is typically you'll see two axes. I'm going to talk about two-dimensional plots where you see an x-axis or a horizontal axis and a y-axis or a vertical axis. And you first want to start off by understanding what these two things represent. So you want to check out to see what does that the variables that are represented in the plot, what are those variables? What are the units? What do they represent? What do they mean?
And then you want to look at the legend of the plot and figure out what the lines or the dots or the curves on the plot are. And maybe you ask yourself, what do I expect to see from what I've read of this paper so far? Or what should I see? And then ask yourself what conclusions you would draw from this plot. For example, if there's a bunch of data points and then there is a line of best fit or a trend line or a model or a comparison of data versus a model.
Ask yourself, do you think that those two things make sense? So if you see a bunch of lines that are put on there and the lines don't really match up with where you think the data points are, maybe that's something that you can be suspicious about. And maybe that's something they address in the text. Maybe it isn't. But it's then you know, after looking for that plot, that you need to go back and you need to look in the text and see if they explain why.
that line may or may not match up well with those data points. People can get really abusive in this way and they can just slap best fit lines on all sorts of random data points and you can massage data a little bit and you can definitely manipulate data to try to paint a conclusion that you want.
It's up to the reader to also be able to say whether or not they agree with the conclusion that the author is trying to draw. So really look at this section, look to see if the plots make sense.
and this is another thing where if you are a person who's going to write papers having really nice plots that people can read with really easy to read labels and big writing big fonts so you can actually read them when they're printed small on a paper this is also a really key aspect for the people out there who are going to be writing papers. After the data and the results section you're probably going to see the conclusion or the discussion section and so as you read this section you want to make sure that you
understand and either agree with or disagree with the conclusion the author or authors are trying to paint. So if the conclusion the authors are trying to state in this section doesn't really make a lot of sense given the plots that you saw, the first thing you do is go back, look at those plots, see why or why not you may or may not agree with that conclusion. You should be able to understand both why
Or why not? Not just that you agree because they say so. If you go back and you see that you had a different assumption and the authors are making this assumption and so that is why, great. Now you've learned what the authors were trying to highlight. You can follow that logical chain better. But if you still disagree, that can be okay too. It's not bad to disagree. It's not that...
Every scientific paper that ever published is gold and never to be questioned. In fact, that's not the point. Papers are meant to be questioned or investigated further or have follow-up studies done. Something else you can keep in mind is that there are good ways and bad ways to design studies. So a lot of times you'll see...
studies done on not very many subjects. You'll see, oh, this paper looked at six recreationally active men. Well, six is kind of a small number. So if they only had six, then maybe you think, oh, hey, this conclusion, they draw a conclusion, but because it was only six people, I don't put as much stock into that, for example. So this is another thing you can kind of temper your expectations based on the methods and the data presented.
So hopefully some of these tips help. Hopefully these help you the next time you sit down to read a paper. I really want to stress that this is not a skill that people are born with. This is not a skill that people magically have like osmosis into their brain from like sleeping on textbooks or something like that. Getting good at this takes time. Practicing reading papers is something that you can do if this is something that interests you.
And if you have friends or family that will indulge you, maybe even practice reading a paper and then explaining it to them. This is something that's done a lot in academic circles. If you go to grad school or even in college and undergrad, you'll find journal clubs where people will print off new papers or maybe some old papers or interesting papers, and they'll practice reading them and then meeting up with a group of people and having informal discussions and explaining the conclusion and the results and things like that in real time.
Hopefully, if this is the sort of thing that interests you, you can find good resources out there, good papers, you can read some of the papers that we reference, and you can really hone the skill of yours. I hope that helps, and I hope you enjoyed these tips, and everyone have a good week. Thanks for listening.