Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Cole Moore, and our usual co-host, Kyle Helson, has the day off today because we are joined by Corey Lockwood, and we're talking about time trialing. It's going to be a great episode. I'm really looking forward to it. And instead of our usual ad sponsors that you might hear in a podcast, of course, we are ad-free. So we thrive on donations only. Big shout out, of course, to our regular donators. So we really appreciate everyone who does that on a monthly or occasional basis. Really appreciate you.
you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate of course we've got show notes up on the website we probably don't have any for today but of course if you have any coaching or consultation inquiries and I have a couple roster spots that just opened up and especially if at the end of this episode you want to reach out and have Corey coach you he's definitely got a couple spots open so you can email me directly at empiricalcycling at gmail.com and if you have any
Consultation Inquiries. You can shoot me an email there too. And of course, up on the Instagram, at Empirical Cycling, that's me, Corey.Lockwood is Corey. And I'm doing Instagram AMAs up on the Instagram stories. And I'm actually going to start asking for listener questions because we're going to start incorporating listener questions into every single podcast. So this is the first one where we are doing that. Instead of doing a dedicated listener question show, we will do some of those too.
But we're going to make sure that we add listener questions to the end of every single podcast. So that's going to be coming up. So if you want to get in a question, I will be prompting a topic or a guest. And so you can ask your question. That's at Empirical Cycling on Instagram. And this is a great episode. We cover a lot of ground.
I learned quite a lot. After this conversation, I'm extra impressed with Corey as an athlete. He's super methodical, but I think that really benefits time trialing well. We talk about what it's like time trialing at a high level. We talk about beginner time trial tips. We talk about position. We talk about course selection. We talk about all sorts of stuff and the mental focus that goes into time trialing.
among many, many, many other things. So here we go, interviewing Corey Lockwood about time trialing. So for those of you listening at home, this is our third attempt to record. We have had some technical difficulties. Turns out that Kentucky is a nice place, but not everywhere in Kentucky has good internet. So, all right, let's start out with...
For the third time, Corey, how's your training going right now? Well, I should be pretty versed at this by now. So my training is going really good. I feel like at this point in time, my fitness is better than it's been in previous years. And I feel fresher and more solid than I've been ever before at this point in the season. Most of the time, I feel like I'm in a more advanced stage.
of training and I'm further along in my peak and a lot of times I've found like you deal with kind of more of a later season burnout or you have to take a mid-season break and it usually unfortunately lands around nationals time and so with this approach I feel like I have a lot more room to grow and a lot more mental capacity to deal with the rigors of training and travel and so I feel like I'm in a very solid place.
Yeah, that's really good. You know, because I think one of the things that you and I have definitely noticed in, you know, our own training, well, yours more than mine since I was never at that high level of an athlete, but, but definitely in coaching, you know, people can realistically only hold like, probably like what, four, maybe five weeks, the very outside of like super peak fitness, right? That sounds about right. Yeah.
Yeah, so the first thing that I like to start people out with is a season break, and you took, was it your very first season break, like last September? Yeah, that's the first time I've taken two or three weeks, and it was quite an experience. So how has that been helping you out right now, feeling good going into your season instead of coming in too hot?
Yeah, I feel like first learning the importance of recovery. A lot of cyclists and endurance athletes tend to think that more is more. And so taking a chance to really take consecutive days off and then see the benefits of that. Like even now, like if I take a couple of days off and come back, I usually do some of the best interval numbers right after two or three days of consecutive rest. And so really learning the importance of resting, putting systematic rest into your training and understanding.
How valuable it is in producing like positive gains in your fitness. And so right now I feel like between learning that and then using that consistently, it's put me in a better spot. I feel like physically than I've been ever in previous years.
I can hear your cat scratching at the litter. Yeah, it's driving crazy right now. Oh my God. Sorry. That's all right. It's still recording. I was trying to cover my mic up with my hand and I literally, like I was contemplating whether I was going to throw my paper tablet across the house at the cat or where those are. Oh man. Anyway, where were we? What was I asking?
I completely forgot. Oh, yeah. So, you know, because I'm, you know, I'm learning from you as I'm coaching you. And, you know, I gave you what I would normally give somebody.
for an early block because now it's the maintain fitness, keep building fitness, get ready for racing. And so I gave you a workout because I like to increase time and zone for threshold stuff. But you just coming off a rest week and you just went right for one by 45 minutes at more or less threshold. And that wasn't what I had planned, but it was like...
well within the spirit, you know, because I wanted you to get in some good work and, you know, feel good and then, you know, have something to build on. But I think, you know, this, you know, the work I did actually works with that really well, but it wasn't what I had planned. So take me through why three weeks out or sorry, three weeks, three months out from TT Nats, you did a like a 45 minute, you know, rough pacing effort.
Yeah, I feel like doing these systematic tests throughout the process approaching nationals works really good. I think the 45 minute test gave me a good gauge as far as the length of nationals usually lasts around 40 to 45 minutes and being able to practice that pacing strategy, lock into the arrow bars and really get a chance to see what that feels like gave me some good data as far as what that's going to feel like.
And, you know, anything we may need to adjust, and you have the time to do it. And so having done that three months out, we have that data, we have, you know, I have the things I need to adjust on my bike, and I literally had a notepad there as I was going through. I'd write this down, like, real quick, like, I need to fix this, or I'd type it onto my phone. I need to adjust that. And so collecting that stuff early on and seeing what that really feels like, I think.
It helps. 15 minutes or 10 minutes in an interval, you get one sensation. But when you do a true 45 minutes, you really get to see a lot of little things that start bothering you here and there. And then you can really take the time to adjust that, like how much food you're eating or your ability to switch up positions or how this fits or how this is going to work. And so you can really go through the process early and then start making addendums to those things. So how do you prioritize what you're noticing in an effort like that?
How do I prioritize? I kind of really feel like what my legs are doing based on the sensation that I feel, the power numbers that I'm putting out, the RP that I'm experiencing. So a lot of times and then like how tight of a position I can hold. So I'll look at myself like in the mirror. Obviously you have a mirror when you're doing time trial intervals on the trainer so you can see what sort of like a tight position you can hold. But at the same time.
you're seeing if it starts affecting the power you can produce that's sustained and you start keeping an eye on what your RPE is and what your legs feel like whether you're more quad heavy or more hamstring heavy or whether you have the ability to like rotate your pelvis forward and back and so I find it's really critical to be able to have several different body positions you can run but really being able to keep the front end closed at the same time so
You know, like if you're climbing, maybe you'll rotate your pelvis underneath you and you do a different pedal stroke or when you're going more aerodynamic, like you'll rotate your pelvis forward and flatten your back a little bit and drop in a little more. And so being able to stay at the same point in the saddle and rotate with your hips, but then being able to also run sustained power for a really long period of time without just what I would call running out of legs. A lot of times, you know, you'll feel good for five or six minutes.
But when you get into the 10 minute, 15, 20 minutes, you really start seeing like, okay, like I'm a mil or two too high on a seat and I feel like I'm overloading my quads or you're like, no, I'm too low. I feel like I'm stomping into the pedals too much and I have to like roll my pelvis underneath me more. And then it starts opening up your front end later on. And a lot of those things like start costing you seconds later on. And so you'll start seeing that stuff. Actually, that's interesting that you mentioned that because one of the things that I've seen
with people either dialing in their own TT positions or going to a TT fitter with aerodynamics primarily in mind. One of the things that happens, unfortunately, seemingly more often than not, is people's quads do get really overloaded. And so what does that feel like as you're going? Because I think a lot of people listening to this, because I've certainly coached quite a few people with a TT bike fit where their quads literally just give up after like,
Two weeks of just, you know, what should be pretty accomplishable threshold training. So what does that feel like in your quads? It would feel like doing leg presses to failure, basically. You start feeling like each rep you do starts putting systematically a little more load on the system that's not really sustainable, where you may be feeling like, you know, other systems are like at your, you know, sustainable.
ability to run for 45 minutes. You feel like your legs start pumping up and you start running out of the ability to hold that power for that amount of time where normally you should be able to. It feels like your legs literally pump out and start giving out. I find a lot of times for me, too quad heavy is like I'm too like, actually, I mean, that's going to get into a whole can of worms there. There's a lot of things that can cause that.
It's a very definite sensation. It feels like your legs start pumping up and giving out. Yeah. Like I said, that's something that I've definitely heard from a lot of folks, unfortunately. So my recommendation would just be obviously go back to your fitter and have another go at it. Try to alleviate some of the quad stuff. But just generally speaking, when it comes to actually racing like a national championship at the pro level,
What is that like, just generally speaking? It's really fun. It's definitely a much more intense environment. There's more to see. There's more happening. There's more distractions that can happen. If you allow it to happen, there's more pressure on you. The experience of racing a national championship was really a lot of fun, though. The courses are unique. It's cool to have all the fans there.
The energy is really high. The atmosphere is really enjoyable. And then when you're out on course, it's all that energy and all that prep work you do to get ready. They're really, you can really feel it when you're out there on the course. You have a lot of like, how I put this, like inner momentum that's pushing you to really like drive. You find some of your best performances out there. You've got, you know, you've been training all year for it. You've been thinking about it. You've been planning for it and put it all together and go out there and just have like.
A run, just put it all out there is really fun. It's very satisfying. I think that's interesting because a lot of the pros that I coach feel a lot of pressure. And you said in regards to pressure, you just said if you allow it. So how do you...
Find something like that. How do you make it more enjoyable for yourself, regardless of how much pressure you put on yourself? Because also, I think a lot of the amateurs that we coach, and I was certainly like this myself, especially early in my racing career. I put so much pressure on myself for a result every single race. The more competitive the race was, the more people were there to get a result, the more nervous I was. So how do you...
Take, you know, a national championship race and enjoy it. You know, a lot of it is making sure you're doing all the prep work days, weeks and months out. And so you basically leave no stone unturned. And so by the time you get there, you already in your mind, know what you're capable of plus or minus a percent. And then you set goals that are based.
on what you can achieve personally, not necessarily what you think you should place in the race, because it's still variables that are outside your control on a time trial. Even in that, you know, you could get the early run and it could be raining. You know, you could get a run that's earlier in the morning. It could be more humidity and the temperature is lower or somebody that goes later on, like, you know, the air is thinner and it's quicker because it's not.
you know 65 degrees and you know high humidity it's 80 degrees and low humidity or something or the wind changes so there's a lot of variables that are outside your control that can change your placing and so taking and setting the placing aside and not having that a primary goal but more of like a secondary thing that just happens to be when you execute things properly so like a goal for me would be like show up do my warm-up on time
Eat my breakfast if I should accordingly and show up to the grid on time. You have like these systematic like checkpoints you do. And a lot of times you practice this, you know, like when I did my 45 minute effort, I went through and I literally ate the breakfast I should. I did the warm up I would do for TT. You know, I practiced like sitting on the starting grid and everything. But then you take that same systematic practice you've been doing for the last three or four months and you see if you can facilitate that at time trial national championships. And that's usually like a goal I would set.
Nail all my warm-up stuff, eat the proper breakfast, do your warm-up, and then pace each lap according to how you think you should, and you break the laps down into sectors, and you have split times you want to run, you have power averages you want to run, speed averages you want to see, and so you really use all of those as your goal, and when you get to the end of the race, be it as it may, you may win, you may get first, you may get tenth, but you look at what you achieved and how you...
did it. That's a better goal, I think, in my mind other than going at results, which can be so hit and miss in a lot of ways. I think that's actually really a great mindset because that's...
What I really try to instill in people is having the process as the goal. And because especially in like a mass start race, there are so many more factors that are way out of your control. You know, like what teams want to show up, what teams want to ride, what teams want to block, like who's, you know, trying to make it come down to a sprint, et cetera, et cetera. And so there's so many more dynamics that come into play when it comes to a result. But, you know, in time trial, you know, everybody calls it the race of truth, right? But, you know, what you're saying here is there's still so many factors that are out of your control.
And so just showing up and knowing that you dotted all your I's and crossed all your T's and going, all right, this is the best I had today. So does that sound about right? Yeah, you have to be, it's a race of truth because you have to be truthful with yourself that you put in your best effort, irregardless of your positioning at the end of it. And so you do all your prep work and you're truthful with yourself that you put your best foot forward. And so in that sense, yes, it's a race of truth.
And, you know, you put this as something to touch on, too, which I never would have thought of having not competed at this level. And you said, you know, is this one of those things that you actually can do as a true solo effort? So is it the race of truth? Can you do it alone? You know, sports nowadays, there's so much technology involved.
So many things that require specialization that one person couldn't hope to master everything, nor do you have the time to. And so perhaps when I'm out there pedaling on the bike, I'm doing that per se.
By myself, but, you know, I had somebody, you know, help me set my bike up, you know, I had, you know, sponsors help me get equipment. I had, you know, swan deers help, you know, set things up here. So we put my bike on the trainer, you know, I even got like, you know, director or mechanic following you in the car. And so there's so many different areas that takes a complete team effort to be able to get you out there. So I wouldn't really say that you can do it individually anymore.
because it requires so many different people with a different specialized background playing their part whether it be you know with you out there on the road or behind the scenes to get you to the starting line so you really need a full team effort so it might be an individual effort but it's supported by a complete infrastructure and team that puts you there so you probably can't do it by yourself anymore.
That sounds like science in a lot of ways. It's very infrequent now that you see a paper with just one author. A lot of the times it's one or two authors or more or up to 10 or 20. And a lot of people are pitching in to doing the research. It's no longer just like one guy in the 1800s in his lab talking with one other guy and suddenly you've got a theory of magnetism and electricity or something like that.
And it kind of sounds like motor racing. I've been watching F1 lately, Drive to Survive. Awesome show. Definitely worth a watch. And when you watch it, it's definitely just those one or two drivers out there, but you see how many people are there for the pit stops, how many mechanics are there, how many people they have on the radios. There's 10 people just looking at monitors and talking to people. That's their whole job.
It's interesting that you say that because I think a lot of people at the amateur level think about that, but as you go up in the level, so many more people are involved. Does that change how you approach race day and preparation in a significant way compared to when you were just a lone wolf? In a way, yes.
You have to have a different mindset and then you have to trust other people with their specialities that they're doing the best that they can. And everybody has an important part to play. I mean, if you look at like a team sport, like you can't be worried about what, you know, one of your other teammates is doing, be it baseball or football or something, because you have your own specific task you have to accomplish. And so if you're the person that's, you know.
doing a specific goal out in the bike race. You have to focus on your goal, but you have to have the trust and the faith that your teammates are going to do their jobs and that the staff members are all doing their jobs and everybody is doing the best that they can to put this entire team effort together.
And so that mindset's different than if you were a lone wolf, you show up and you're the ones mixing your bottles and you write your own strategy and you pump up your own tires and you do all this stuff. But when it gets to the point where the performance is at such a high level, you no longer have the bandwidth to do all of those things. So you have to have multiple people that are supporting you so that you can spearhead an effort out there on the race course to the best of your abilities.
And how much performance do you think that gives you the day of between, you know, having to do everything yourself and then freeing up all that more bandwidth to, you know, focus on your own specific prep, like, you know, not being stressed, making sure you get in your warm up, make sure everything's on time, you know, that kind of stuff. So how much does that translate to on course performance? If you take advantage of it and you don't let the infrastructure.
to stress you out and you can actually take advantage of the extra bandwidth you can perform better. So some people will look at all this stuff that people are doing of like, oh, well, that means now that I have to do like this extra special job, like pull a rabbit out of a hat and it like builds pressure to perform on their shoulders and they end up like caving themselves in before they can use that extra bandwidth they've been given. Or other times like, or other athletes you'll see that they'll...
They'll actually take and do spectacular performances with it. So it depends on how you use it. But yes, it can help. Yeah. And so I think, you know, one other thing to touch on here before we actually talk about, you know, the race day of and, you know, stuff on course is actually kind of getting into that is how much of time trialing is power and how much is, you know.
More intangible things like skill and technique and preparation. Well, you have to have the initial buy-in of power per se, where your power has to be good enough to win or plus or minus. And then there's, you know, obviously, as you touch on intangible things like, you know, the way in which you use power, your strategy, your techniques.
And so there's a good amount of it is power. I hear you dealing with a cat over there. I tried to make that quiet. He's trying to jump into the windowsill and knock my phone down. Oh, there's nothing quiet about those cats. He's trying to sabotage me right now. Sorry. My notepad over there again, I was like trying to shoo him away. Okay, so where was I? I was talking about...
Okay, so ask the question again. How much comes down to power and how much comes down to intangible stuff like skill, technique, and preparation? Because you would mention that there's a power buy-in, but how much of a good performance is skill and technique? Because I think a lot of people figure that time trialing is less skill and less technique. So how much of the intangible stuff comes into play the day of?
So you were talking about F1 drive to survive. It's like your physical engine has to be on par with the other cars to run a fast qualifying time. But then the way in which you drive the car makes a big difference.
you know the line selection on course your ability to pick and choose when you want to sacrifice aerodynamics to put out more you know raw horsepower versus times where you think it's better to tuck and run a tighter hip angle and maybe run a more aerodynamic position your breathing technique down even like if you watch like some guys they'll change their cadence
Based on what the train's doing, whether it's moving up or moving down, to actually pump more speed out of the pavement like a rider would do on a mogul track. If you watch guys ride a pump track where they go around and pump speed out of the bumps on the ground, you'll actually pick up all the micro bumps on the ground and you'll actually speed up your cadence and pump the bike through it to actually pick up more momentum with the same power.
and so you'll actually look at like the slopes on the pavement different like coefficients of drag and you'll actually move around and pick lines to pick the most speed with the least amount of power output even down to like looking for sheltered sides of the road based on which direction the wind's coming from and so there's a lot of technique involved in it. Yeah and it sounds like the technique is it's not only just handling the bike and you know being able to go fast around corners or
As appropriate. But it sounds like the technique is also like reading the course and reading the wind and the terrain, right? Yeah, and being able to use your power effectively to get the most speed out of a given section. Because that's what it's about. It's about speed. It's about velocity. You can just put a flat X amount of wattage out. But if you aren't smart about it, you won't get the most out of it. So you have to know.
Where's the best line to pick to get the most speed out of the power that you're putting out? And sometimes that is about handling the bike, being able to corner better. You know, if you can't take per se, like, you know, the turnaround around a cone effectively, you miss your turnaround, you have to sprint out of the cone harder. And that, you know, shows up later on when you have to do, you know, 12, 12 sprints out of turns, like your last minute or two of the time trial is not going to be very good.
The ability to pick lines and do all your technical stuff does help a lot. Let's see. Where should we go next with this? We have a lot of ways we could go here. So while you're riding a course, what is your main focus? Because I think a lot of people will probably think about power first. But how much of that is like you know how to pace it. You could do this power with your eyes closed.
and you're thinking about other stuff like so like so where does your mind go while you're riding one of these things? So. It can be like a sport of passion, so you're like really you have a lot of like internal intensity and you're trying to use that to harness the most speed you can get on the course, but you also have to pace that and that you don't burn yourself out before the finish. So your primary focus is speed, how fast you can go so you can drop and have the.
Have the lowest split time. And so from there, you can break down into smaller technical things that you can work on to get more speed, be it like timing your breathing or, you know, tucking aerodynamically in different areas. But usually you can only focus on one thing at a time. So you rotate through focused pointed things.
that keeps your mind like fresh and occupied but occupied at moving yourself with intensity down the course. That's where I found like from my backgrounds of other sports bringing that forward is having that never having a lapse of concentration because every time you stop thinking about speed when you're time traveling you automatically start moving backwards like you can never shut your mind off for a second you're always looking to like
get more speed, more speed, more speed, intensity, intensity, but then you're trying to like balance that with not burning yourself out, cracking yourself. So it's like I said, it's just like F1 qualifying for 30 minutes. Like you don't settle in. Every time you settle in, you're losing time to the person in front of you or behind you or somewhere around the tracks here. You can't settle in.
If you didn't have the motorsport background you had where you had to have this mental focus, because I've tried playing racing games where you need this focus, and it's exhausting. I've got realistically about 20 minutes of pure focus, pretty much doing anything, let alone doing a 45-minute time trial. My mind always wanders, and maybe that's a me problem, but I'm sure other people start daydreaming too when something gets...
wrote. So like, how do you practice that mental focus? Or like, how would you if you hadn't been practicing it for, you know, the last, you know, 10, 15 years of your sporting life? So first, you have to be aware that your mind can only focus so much. And then there's different levels of focus.
There's different parts on the course that require 100% focus and there's parts on the course where you can force breaks and force rest and so perhaps there's an area for two or three seconds where you don't have to pay attention and then there's a section on the course for maybe a minute where you have to have 100% on time and then there's a course where if you're 50% focused you know you're not going to lose any time and so what you start learning how to do is how to break the course into like
Offensive sections, maybe flow sections, and then off sections on the course, and you break it down into split times where there's like one minute, 100% focus, and you're like laser focus, five seconds, you almost like meditate, and like you loosen your hands up, loosen your jaw up, two or three deep breaths, and you literally talk to yourself, you're like breathe, relax, and you shut your mind off for a second, and those little brief respites in mental focus allows you to have that 100% focus later, just like if you're doing
40-20s or 30-30s where you have to do those forced rests so you can lift the power again. You have to do those forced mental rests so you can lift the focus again. And so you know systematically on the course where you have to have that. That is fascinating. So we could probably do an hour on just that alone, but why don't we move into the next thing, which is...
So you go into a course with like a pacing goal. Like you go, you expect it's going to take about X amount of minutes, like 45 minutes. And you're like, okay, I could probably do 420 to 400, maybe 25, 30 watts for this effort. When you get there, if your legs are better than expected or worse than expected, how do you change your pacing goal and how long does it take you to figure that out?
So you have to be careful. Usually the first couple of minutes, you'll have such a high amount of adrenaline. It'll almost mask the amount of rate of perceived exertion you're doing. So you usually give it a couple of minutes just to double check and make sure you feel that good. So you usually stick to your strategy. And so there's like two or three, three laps at nationals. You'll stick pretty closely to your strategy and you'll kind of like test the waters. And if you're feeling really good, then you can give a little more and you stick to that.
And if it comes around to the second lap, you're like, no, this is really a thing, then you can add a little more. So you have to be smart about it. Obviously, if you start out within the first two minutes, you're like, oh, I feel great. And then you start going really hard within five minutes. You're like, oh, that was a mistake. And then the next three minutes, you pay for it. And it's miserable when you do that. I've done it before. I think everybody's done it before. Everybody. Yeah, so I think that's...
One of the things that everybody always asks me with a time trial, I think you'll probably be like the one person who doesn't ask me, what power should I aim for? So I think one of the things that typically happens is, well, actually, let me ask you this. Let me put it to you like this. When one of the people you coach asks you, what power should I do in this time trial? How do you respond given what you just said to me?
Well, to use one of your famous quotes, it depends. It depends on the course. It depends on the conditions. It depends on the athlete. So, per se, like, if it's just like a straight out and back course, no wind, easy, pan flat, one turnaround, then you're going to do a negative split.
You'd start, you know, under your threshold and build up to it and you'd go pretty hard into the turnaround where you'd almost go to the point where you feel almost you've gone a little too hard and then like that turnaround usually gives you a break just enough that then you can like do like one step higher and do another systematic lift to the finish. Now, if it's a course with laps, it would be something different. If it's a course with maybe it's uphill and there's a turnaround, it's downhill back to the finish.
Then you'd just go bananas to the turnaround until you're blown up and then you'd coast back down the hill. So there's different pacing strategies. So it depends. Yeah, like if it were a one kilometer time trial, just send it. Yeah. But there's a lot of thought that goes into the pacing and that's what makes it technical is you have to look at the course, you have to look at yourself and know your fitness, know the conditions.
And they have to go, okay, well, this is the best strategy for me because some people can, you know, do really hard, like lifts and power over the top of the threshold and then come back down and do it again and again and again. And some people are very much like an electric motor in a very steady state. And so you have to look at, you have to look at the course and go, well, this is the conditions. This is the way I have to ride it. This is going to be the best strategy for me. And then you pick out power zones coding to that. Yeah. Yeah. Cause I think one of the things that.
People typically say, can you just look at my power curve and tell me what I can do for 12 minutes? And I'll be like, I think if I told you what you could do for 12 minutes, we might leave some performance on the table. Because a couple of years ago, one of the athletes I was coaching, he had just come off a VO2 max block and I was going to give him a short 25, 30 minute test, just time trial. But he had an indoor time trial and I was like, okay, this will be pretty good.
maybe 15, 20 minutes. And he had underpaced it for the first 13 of 15 minutes because he was shocked at how good he felt. And this is one of those instances where if he had asked me, what can I do? He would have way underperformed, but he actually underperformed because he was shocked at the numbers. So that kind of thing on the day is one of those.
things where you hope that somebody way exceeds your expectations for what they can do. Like if you asked me like, what can I do for this time trial? I'd be like, I would say right now you could probably do 425 watts. But on that day, I hope you blow it out of the water and do 440. You know what I mean?
Yeah, it's almost like you come back around as you focus on RPE. There's a certain sensation you have when you start a certain strategy and it should feel a certain way where you're like, you should load your legs up to this level of sensation and it should be here. And then at this next point, you load your legs to here and then you should overload here. And then you look back down at the power and if your leg is not lining up with what your expectations are, you recalibrate your expectations and power numbers to like match up to your RPE.
Or like on a good day, you'd be doing whatever it is. We'll pick a number. If you're a good day, you're doing 300. But like you are having a bad day and you're like, well, the best I can hold is 280. I'm not going to push myself to 300 because 280 is an 8 out of 10. So right now I'm going to hold 280.
Later on you find you didn't change the battery in your power meter and was reading wrong anyways, but that's happened plenty of times. Yeah, that's one of those equipment things you got to take care of on the day, but like also if you've got a reliable piece of equipment, don't touch it.
Yeah, so if you're not touching it and it goes wrong on race day, actually I think that's one of the most important things that I'm hearing from you that I try to press upon people probably not often enough, even though I harp on it all the time, is listening to your legs during an effort.
because you don't want to be a slave to your power meter and what you expect. You want to be able to adjust on the day. So what role does equipment play? Obviously, it plays a huge role. So just generally speaking, though, in time trialing, what role does equipment play and how do you select your equipment for different race conditions? I know that's an extremely general question, but give me a very general answer that people can maybe take something away from.
Equipment plays a massive role in your ability to perform. So it depends on the course. You'll select equipment accordingly to the course, like your tires you would select. If it's a course that has more cornering and less like aerodynamics involved, like if it's more of like a prologue time trial, then you want something you can carry more corner roll speed with. So you're going to pick wider profile tires and you're going to pick.
Rims that are according to more of like doing cornering like you would do in a Criterium. If it's maybe more of like a flowy time trial, something that's more aerodynamic, you'd pick maybe if it's got like rollers and stuff, you'd pick wheels that can roll up really well in rollers and carry really good momentum and you'd pick something that's a little more aerodynamic. Maybe you'd even put a 23 on the front with like a wider rim because it'll work better.
as far as aerodynamics go. If it's a super windy course and hilly, you'd run maybe different tires. You'd run maybe wider 25s or something where they would have better contact patch to the ground and you'd run smaller rims because you'd get gusted all over the place and you'd run different PSI. Maybe you'd run maybe another stack or two into there like get you up off the front end where you're not so front end heavy where you're going to get speed wobble or something really badly.
and then if you're like maybe if it's an uphill time trial obviously you'd run climbing rims you'd run a road bike instead of a TT bike so different helmets for different conditions like if you're spending a lot of time like in and out of position you'd run like a short tail helmet if you're locked in you'd run a long tail one if it's a climbing you'd maybe run like an arrow road helmet and so there's different selections you can do there
Temperature changes, things you would do. You know, you run ice socks or you'd run, I mean, if it was miserably hot, you'd run short sleeve almost if it was uphill. So, I mean, there's a whole gamut of stuff you can pick and choose from. So, you basically have to know the course. You have to know the conditions. You have to know, like, yourself and your own pacing strategy. Then you pick equipment accordingly to, like, equip yourself with to do your best effort. Now, so I think people could easily spend...
probably tens of thousands of dollars on time trial equipment if they had infinite budget. So what is the one piece of equipment that you would tell everybody? So let's say somebody's got a time trial bike or they've got clip-on aero bars or whatever it is, and that's all they can afford. What is the next piece of equipment? So obviously, if you're on clip-ons, you want to go to a TT bike, but if you can't get that, or if you're on a TT bike and you don't have anything else, what's the number one thing that you would probably reach for?
Okay, so you've got aero bars of some sort, you're saying, whether it be on a road bike or on a TT bike. I would assume that most people in that situation would have a shallower set of wheels. And so if you're going to get a secondary set of wheels, you get a set of deep dish wheels, like a deep dish front wheel and a disc that way, like, you know, this stuff, like you can always do the old, like, get the expensive wheels and then
Tape over all the vent holes on your helmet if you need to for more aerodynamics. Put saran wrap on it or something. I've done that before, so you can't afford stuff. Shrink rash helmet, that's hilarious. It works somewhat. I mean, I never aero tested it, but I mean, if you want to get a little more aerodynamics, but wheels make a pretty good difference. A helmet makes a pretty good difference. The position is one of the biggest things. A speed suit makes a big difference. Those are all pretty close.
pretty close seconds. The frame in itself is not so much like a big aerodynamic difference. But it gives you the position, right? But it gives you the position. You can put clip-on bars in a road bike and get a pretty close position. There's usually more setback. And so you're behind the crank further. You're not up and over the bottom bracket like a TT bike, which is not a bad thing sometimes if you can set it up right because you usually have more like room to breathe as long as you're not too far back.
So I guess like a helmet would be one of them, a speed suit maybe, but like, you know, that's a tough choice. There's a couple of them that make a difference. Yeah, and it's hard to actually kind of, you know, A, B all these things because you've got to have all of them to begin with. And so, you know, I actually, you know, what would be fun is like getting like an aero swap meet together, like a bunch of cyclists get together, you meet in one testing place and you...
like pool all of your equipment and you can test out each other's stuff. Maybe not the kit unless you really wash the chamois or put on a chamois guard if such a thing exists. But yeah, that would be kind of fun. So next question I have that's very general is, where does time trialing skill carry into other areas and disciplines of cycling? Well,
Skill and time trialing. One, you have really good focus. Two, you're usually like a highly analytical rider. You can pick strategies, pick bike setup really well, and then being able to do those like sustainable outputs. So like that can go into a lot of different areas. Like you can be a good teammate, obviously, and ride the front. That's one thing that gives you a good skill. Like two, having that.
ability to do long sustained efforts like you can be good in a breakaway like your time trialing skills come into being the solo and off the front in a breakaway works really good because you understand especially like in criteriums you can get off the front solo you understand how to do that mental breakdown like I talked about earlier where you've got like attack flow recover and you break the crit down into little spots and then you can ride off the front like with a great degree of success.
So there's quite a few other areas. I agree with all that. Of course, that also requires that you have the power to actually write off the front of a criterium, which is true. Yeah, I remember as a sprinter or just, you know, while I was learning that I was a sprinter, I would always like I was I would always.
have such an easy time getting separation from a crit field. And then like 10 minutes later and no more, they would reel me back in. So, okay. So next question is, what are the simple tips and tricks that you have for beginner TTs or time trialists that would probably most easily?
and largely benefit somebody's performance on race day. Making a schedule works really well. That's a trick that most people usually overlook. You know your start time and you usually backtrack systematically from your start time back to the time you would wake up in the morning and you give yourself five minutes buffer between each checkpoint. Like you make breakfast at this time, you drive at this time.
You get your numbers at this time. You put your bike on the trainer at this time. This is how long it takes for you to do your warmup. Make sure you put your velo toes on at this time, like your helmet, have your stuff laid out. So making like a systematic step-by-step checklist of from when your start time is backwards to when you wake up. And the usual trick is it takes a lot longer than people think. I would say bare minimum two hours before your start time if you want to be there. If you're an hour and a half, you're usually already late.
Even for a local time trial, it takes, you know, it takes a lot of little, little steps of little things to be completely ready so that when you're out there on the course, you don't think about anything like it. It's always terrible. Like if you have like zip up booties and one of them unzips or something, it's flapping around the wind or you forget to zip up your speeds. You'd have done that before.
Oh, God. And then you can't zip it up and then you're stuck or you forget to put your visor on and somebody's yelling, put your visor on. And like at the start, you're like, oh, great. And then you just like throw it off and then you have no visor because like you were in a rush and you forgot or like numbers flapping in the wind, you know, and all sorts of like nonsense that happens. Like when you show up, like there's always something that you forget.
And so your list grows every time. Like put your visor on, zip up your skin suit. It's like little things that you don't expect to need to have written down. You know, it's sort of like when you're packing for a trip and you write down toothbrush. Because if I don't write down toothbrush, I don't bring my toothbrush. That's right. It's just like that. And so having a list is a big one. You know, and I think it's because I didn't expect you to give that answer. Honestly, I would have.
thought you would say like, you know, course recon or something like that. But like, you know, I think you're right, though, just in that the amount of mental stress and the impact on your warmup and your confidence in yourself and your day can really be impacted by things not going according to plan. And so, you know, for people who are basically one step above robots like you and me, I think, you know, that's great. But, you know, for folks who are able to, you know, rock and roll a little bit.
more easily with the flow of the day. That's nice if they don't have to do this, but I think generally speaking, you're right that this seems like it would be the lowest hanging fruit for somebody just getting into time trialing. Yep, having a list. It makes a big difference.
So simple that they even do it for surgeries with very smart doctors. Yeah, get that sponge out of that patient. Just make sure, put it on the list. Just generally, in terms of coaching, how critical do you think that your personal experience is to your ability for coaching athletes who are getting into racing or even are experienced cyclists themselves?
Having gone through a lot of the ups and downs, mainly a lot of the downs when you do a lot of the, you know, days that don't go as well, then when somebody else has a day that perhaps doesn't live up to their expectations, you can put yourself in their shoes and you kind of remember what that's like and you have the ability to then, you know, communicate to them, connect with them in a way to be able to lead them through that situation.
and in whatever difficult time that may be or you know there's other situations that you know perhaps like how to go about something like from a certain perspective you can look at and be like well I've gone through a race similar to this or I've been in a training day similar to this and this is kind of how I went about it so you can offer bits of advice that may parallel in a way what they're doing and so it allows you to connect with them and give better better feedback.
in a way. Yeah, I appreciate that. All right, so one more question and then we'll get to some listener questions. So who and what have been the biggest contributors to your own growth as an athlete? I mean, obviously, family's been a big contributor to growth in my cycling, being able to help me, friends, people that I've met.
People like yourself, you know, learning all these really cool things about coaching and about, you know, human body. Like those are all great contributors to getting better as an athlete and as a person. Failure has been a really big contributor to growth. There's been a lot of those for sure. And so a lot of really bad ones. And so each one of those you learn from, be it like a crash or.
something that didn't go as planned or riding a time trial with your skin suit unzipped or whatever it is. There's been a bazillion of them. And so those are all contributing factors to getting better. And so as much as I dislike all the failures and some of them you really cringe at when you think back and you're like, oh man, that really happened, didn't it? Can't believe I did that. But you learn from it and you get better.
Hopefully you don't do it a second time. Hopefully. It's funny because how many mistakes have I made where it's taken me like eight, nine, ten times before I realized maybe it's me.
All right. So we have some listener questions. So I asked on Instagram, if you want to follow me on Instagram, I'm going to be doing a lot more listener question type stuff in the future. So that's at Empirical Cycling on Instagram. So Corey, how do you fuel a day of FTP intervals? So I think this is actually coming from somebody who's very fast himself. And I think actually this is something that a lot of people may not appreciate or may wonder.
You go do 45 minutes at 400-something watts, and you've burned over 1,000 kilojoules. So how do you fuel a day like that where you might be riding an extra four or five hours with FTP intervals, and so now you've burned like 6,000 kilojoules. So how do you fuel a day like that? Yeah, the amount of carbohydrates you need for a day like that's insane. Most people don't eat enough. It's really easy to get behind, and then it's hard to get back ahead.
One, two, three breakfasts. Like you get up, like I'll get up at five o'clock in the morning and you have just like a simple carbohydrate breakfast using complex carbs, something that's simple. And then like you'll have a main breakfast later on. That's pretty substantial. And mind you, like I would do the same breakfast on a day of FTP intervals as the same sort of breakfast I would do for like time trial national championships or trying to do like.
Penultimate climbing stage at Tour Gila or anything else. Like you eat a lot of carbohydrates and you want to eat carbs the night before too. So if you just go out and have like, you know, a couple of rice cakes and a bottle of water, like you're going to have a really hard time. So you eat a lot of food and predominantly like I find complex carbs work pretty good for me. I mean, the amount of food you're going to eat is different depending on your body size.
For me, I mean, obviously, well over 100 grams of carbs for breakfast, like several, so hundreds, hundreds of grams of carbs, hundreds of grams of carbs. Yeah, you're on the Hobbit's, you know, eating schedule from Lord of the Rings. Yeah, first breakfast, second breakfast, you know, lunch, tea, levensies, whatever it is. It's just like that. And you go through two or three of those and then you do your ride and then you make sure you're eating like every 15 or 20 minutes on the bike too.
That's the only way you get to stay ahead of it. Yeah. Okay. Somebody asked about training requirements for an Ironman bike leg, if any, anaerobic what and when. I think we kind of touched on that with, you know, talking about how, you know, pacing is not quite always steady. Do you stick to power targets erased by feeling TTs? We addressed that.
Advice for a newbie TT rider? Okay, cool. Yeah, so a lot of these questions that we got, actually, we've already touched on in the podcast, so we're going to kind of skip over them. Oh, here's a good one. What strategies do you use if you are a very lightweight rider on a flat TT, something like 60 kilograms? Hmm. So I'm assuming when they say lightweight rider, there's a couple of things that come to mind that maybe they're assuming that they don't put out as much wattage because they're lighter.
That's my assumption as well. And the other thing would be that if they're lighter, they could deal with variables of wind and getting blown around on the road more with aerodynamic equipment. So I would say choose your equipment being your wheels wisely. If you can handle something that's like a deeper section set of wheels based on your weight, then go for it. But be mindful of the wind.
And the other thing is that it's about velocity. So like if you're smaller and you can't put out as much power, but you've got a smaller CDA, you could still, in theory, achieve the same amount of velocity if you're putting out X amount of power, but you have a smaller coefficient drag. And so I would say focus on your position and make your position as
as effective as possible for the amount of power you put out. And you might be surprised how fast you can go. Maybe you're only putting out 300 watts, but if you've got a really small position and you've done a really good job of picking out your aero equipment and you know how to pace the time trial based on your fitness style, you can go just as fast as somebody that's out there, you know, watt-monstering, smashing out 400 to something watts because they look like, you know, Donkey Kong.
That is a terrible stereotype that all riders who look like Donkey Kong put out big watts. It's true. I can only do it for sprinting. I can't do 400 watts for longer than a couple minutes. I would also say that you want to pick your courses. If you're unable to really get a nice drop in your frontal area and reduce your drag a good amount,
then you would want to probably target hillier time trials when possible. That's true. So if they can pick and choose the time trial course, for sure uphill ones. If it's a stage race and it's got some, you know, penultimate climbing stages, you've done really good and you're trying to like keep the yellow jersey or stay within like contact of it, then yeah, do the strategy I was talking about earlier.
Try to lose as little time as possible. You'll find you might stay pretty close. And then when it comes back around to the mountain dig and you do pretty good. So yeah. Yeah. Race the Joe Martin TT. That's a good climb. Yeah. What target cadence? Cause I never think about target cadence in terms of what somebody should do. I look at what they usually do.
and say stick with that when possible. So this kind of also gets into gearing a little bit. So why don't you talk about how you pick gears and maybe drivetrain efficiency as well versus also like what cadence are you at? So cadence is something that I view a little differently. Cadence is a tool that I use to generate speed and manage.
And so I'll use high cadence, high power to usually generate speed on the bike. And then I'll drop the cadence and drop the power and drop my position to be able to turn a gear over and manage that speed. It's like you build up the speed quick, pump it up the speed, and then you carry the speed like rolling a bowling ball with momentum. And so cadence is something I use to generate speed and manage. Oh, so I think what you're saying is like...
Like when I tell people in a criterium, I usually say you want to try to accelerate from like over 90 to 95 RPM. So you're talking about like acceleration and then maintaining. So I think that actually makes a lot of sense because when you...
Try to Accelerate a Large Gear. It is really energetically intensive, like more than the kilojoules that you would read on your power meter would say. So actually, I think that's probably really good advice. So I would say, yeah, like try to accelerate at a higher cadence and then drop to your like normal cadence for power. Yeah, and your normal cadence for power is where you'll feel most comfortable. You'll feel like the best balance of like leg pressure, you know.
Like your breathing rhythm will feel good and whether it be 80, 85, 90 RPMs, whatever feels best to you. And then you usually spin up from there, like up above it to like accelerate. And then you'll come back down to that to usually like manage. As far as gearing goes. Yeah, somebody asked what size chain ring on a TT bike and somebody else also asked about, you know, choosing gearing.
You know, that depends on the course. You want something that's effective for the course you're doing. You want to have a good spread of gears where you're not having to mash at 60 RPMs, obviously. So if it's like a pan flat TT, like out and back, not dealing with any wind, then...
I have a 60 on my bike right now actually I have a 1x60 on there I've heard of like and I've seen people like Tony Martin putting on a massive chainring but it's also because they don't have to get to their 11 on the back so you can have a straighter chainline and lose a lot less in your drivetrain efficiency
And also what happens too is when the other guys are geared out, you can pedal at 34, 35 miles an hour and still be at like 80 RPMs and you're not spun out at 120. And then you can turn a lope along doing like 300 watts and start making like time on the guys while the rest of them are spinning up and super tucking. You're just like cranking down the hill, down a pulse flat, just like a big diesel engine. You make like 20 seconds on somebody. So the gearing can work there.
Oh, that's actually a good thought. Yeah. And so if it were like a Hillier course, though, you would probably take the 60 off and go for something more traditional, like a 53, 39, or even like a compact if it's super, super steep. Yeah. I mean, if you're doing something like, if it's like the San Dimas uphill time trial, that was like the notorious uphill time trial in SoCal. It's like a 15 minute effort, but the majority was uphill. Yeah. You'd run a mid compact on that.
And you'd run a road bike, obviously. You wouldn't put a 60 on there. It'd be miserable on a 60. All right. Last question is, is fabric always faster than skin? And I also want to make a disclaimer that I do not know Corey to be an expert in aerodynamics like Dan Bigum is. But you've been around your time trials long enough. I feel like you would probably know the answer to this question.
So I've watched enough GCN videos and I've done enough like looking at, you know, reading like forums on arrow weenies and all these other little like forums that have like stuff that I would say most of the time, depending on the fabric you're using, fabric can be faster than skin, but it depends on the speed suit you're using and who's making the fabric.
And so I know that there's some, not all speed suits are created equal. There's some out there that are pretty fast. And then there's some out there that are pretty slow. And it takes a trained eye and probably a large pocketbook to get the really fast one, unless you know the people. So in that case, if it's a really slow one, you might be faster to just shave and have, you know, bare skin.
Actually, I was going to jokingly ask you, but you just said shave. So do you shave everything that is exposed to the wind? Like if you've got like a shorter sleeve jersey because it's super hot out and it's a little uphill, you know, something like that, would you shave your arms? You know, I don't know how much of a difference that would actually make if we wind tunneled that difference between having hair and no hair because
Like if you look at a golf ball, for instance, like we're going to go with the old golf ball thing, like the golf ball isn't smooth. It has dimples on it. And they find that a dimpled golf ball actually goes further than a smooth one because the aerodynamics are different. Like, so there's some, there's obviously I'm not an aerodynamicist here and then you can go, I can get myself in trouble talking about this. So smoother surfaces are not always faster.
Yeah, I think actually that shows something really good about you that I think that generally speaking, we try to do a good job of, which is knowing the limits of our knowledge. So I appreciate you saying that you don't know entirely. But according to the same internet research, I would agree. I've spent my time around some really smart aerodynamicists to know that like
I have limits to my knowledge and I'm not going to go into that area. There's some pretty smart people out there. And for everybody I coach who's gone to a particular aero fitter whose name I don't want to give away on the podcast because I don't want him to get blown up because I got a EU in there also. But according to him, everything needs to be tested. So you never really know what's faster until you test it.
That is very true because I've done testing like at a velodrome before where you're like, that had to have been faster. And they're like, nope, you were slower. That was the worst position. You're like, really? So then, yep, you do have to test it. That's very true. Awesome. All right. Any closing thoughts besides, you know, whatever your cats have been trying to say on mic this whole time? Yeah. Well, they're all quiet now.
closing out here of course they are you know if anybody has any more questions on time trialing or you know my personal experiences on riding or anything pertaining to that like they can find me on Instagram you know don't be afraid to ask me questions they can follow me on Strava though like my last like five or six months on Strava has just been like majority of it's been on the trainer because of cold months and stuff so a lot of those mileage
Readings on that are not entirely accurate, so I apologize about that. I'm doing the best that I can there, but yeah, comment on stuff and reach out and I'm more than willing to talk it up and talk bikes.
That would be my comment there. All right. I want to thank Corey again, of course, for coming on to the podcast because, you know, wow, what a wealth of knowledge. I hope everybody learned a lot as much as I did. And, of course, if you want to work with Corey as a coach, he is taking on athletes with Empirical Cycling. So email me empiricalcycling at gmail.com and we can set that up. And, of course, if you want to ask a question yourself for future podcast episodes or you just want to check out the Instagram AMAs on the web.
You can check me out on Instagram at Empirical Cycling and sharing the occasional meme content. If you're into memes, mine are okay. I wouldn't say they're groundbreaking, but, you know, they're fine.
and of course if you want to help out the podcast share it and five star iTunes rating would be great and of course donations go really a long way because now we are you know we have a couple extra expenses than we previously had with a new recording platform for the podcast so that's going really well audio quality has been really good has not dropped any any files yet so you can donate at empiricalcycling.com slash donate and with that thanks everybody for listening and we'll see you next time