Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I am not your host, but I am Cole Moore. Kyle Helson is going to be hosting today for this show. So thank you all for listening as always. And I want to ask that you subscribe to the show and also share it with a friend or somebody who's got questions on physiology or whatever we're talking about. Remember to give us a nice rating wherever you listen to podcasts, including iTunes and or a review. And also we are an ad-free podcast. So if you'd like to donate to the show, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate.
We have shown us up on the website. We have merch at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com. And if you have any coaching and consultation, inquiries, questions, or comments, you can please email empiricalcycling at gmail.com. And also, don't forget that on Instagram, at empiricalcycling, in the stories, I am doing AMAs every weekend. So they will be up for 24 hours. I usually put it up somewhere around mid-Saturday. So be sure to check that out. So without further ado, here is Kyle.
Hey everyone, this is Kyle this week, Cole's got the night off. It's getting to be the end of September here, maybe it's October when this episode comes out. So people are probably, especially if you live in the northern hemisphere, starting to think about the off-season. And off-season for a lot of people means that they're going to start to reintroduce gym training or resistance training and more off-the-bike stuff. So we want to go through a series of tips here to kind of help you out with your off-season strength training.
is breathing. And that maybe sounds kind of weird. You think breathing, well, lifting weights or doing strength training, it's not really an aerobic exercise. Why do I have to think about breathing? Well, it turns out breathing and especially the way that you're breathing helps stabilize your core muscles is really important for keeping your back and your abs stable during heavy and like maximal attempts and lifts. So for example,
in a squat or a deadlift if you watch say strongman or if you watch Olympic weightlifting or if you watch CrossFit or any of these strength sports you will oftentimes see people approach a lift and just before they start the lift the first thing they'll do is they'll inhale a big breath and then they'll kind of tense up and make a funny face and that is because what they're doing is they are inhaling a
Big belly breath, so breathing with your abdomen, not your shoulders, your abdomen, and thinking about expanding your abs and pushing your abs out and then contracting them really hard once you've got that breath pulled deep inside. So you kind of want to think about this like tensing up your abs, like you're going to be punched in the stomach, only you don't want to just think about your abs in the front, you want to think about your obliques in the sides and the low back muscles in the back, and so you want to think about creating this kind of
cylinder of tension around your core. This helps stabilize your trunk and spine during lifts. This breathing pattern is often called the Valsalva maneuver. Some of you who have done scuba diving or snorkeling may have heard of this name before. And fun fact, many people will actually subconsciously do this.
Inhale and then tense up their abs when they're initiating a bowel movement. So you can think about that next time you're in the restroom. And now some of you may be sitting there thinking like, wait a minute, I've read things on the internet or I've heard from friends that you shouldn't hold your breath when you lift weights. And this can be, like many things on the internet, kind of true. So you should definitely not hold your breath.
continuously for multiple reps in a row. So that would be like, I've got a bunch of leg presses, so I'm going to inhale and then try to bang out eight reps with my breath health. So that gets really tiring and you're actually going to be probably losing that tension, that really tight core tension that you're looking for as time goes on. So you really don't want to hold your breath for multiple reps.
What you want to do is you want to inhale, hold your breath, do the rep, exhale. And lifting weights, you can definitely pause. You don't have to just crank out reps like bang, bang, bang, bang, bang for a lot of these exercises. You can pause for a third of a second, a half a second or whatever to readjust your breath and go again. Other critics of the Valsalva maneuver will also say that holding your breath and tensing your abs up like this can lead to increases in blood pressure. And now this is true.
So if you are at risk for hypertension or have a history of hypertension, you should definitely consult a medical professional before you start any sort of strength training or resistance training regimen. So we are not doctors. I'm not a doctor of medicine. So please do not use us for medical advice. Now, if you look up what your body actually does when you perform this Valsalva maneuver, when you inhale and then tense up,
initially you are going to actually see your blood pressure and your heart rate drop a little bit because when you inhale and then tense your abs you are actually increasing your intra-abdominal pressure so you're increasing the pressure inside of your core and that is one of the things that helps stabilize your core or from bending or twisting or loading your spine poorly while you do the lift and
you'll find that if you do this and hold your breath like this for many seconds your blood pressure will start to rise because your sympathetic nervous system will kick in and compensate for that increased intra-abdominal pressure and it will increase your blood pressure and your heart rate and if you are doing this while you're lifting you may think well a few seconds that's actually
that's not very much time so I'm always going to be increasing my blood pressure and my heart rate and that actually may not be true because if you look at someone doing deadlifts or squats or leg presses or pushing a sled or flipping a tire most of the time heavy reps even pretty maximal reps do not take multiple seconds you know you can think of that one really grindy kind of gross looking maximal deadlift or squat that may take a second or two to like
Really, really finish the lift because you're giving it all you got and you're right on the limit. But for most of the training, 99.99999% of your training, and I would even argue that most cyclists never actually have to attempt heavy, heavy one rep maxes in squats or deadlifts or leg press as much as your ego may like it. You're not going to see reps that force you to grind and hold your breath tensed up really tight like that for many seconds. So you actually are not going to necessarily...
Put your body in a position where you're going to have to dramatically increase that blood pressure and heart rate to compensate for that increased intra-abdominal pressure. Also keep in mind, we are not recommending that you increase your intra-abdominal pressure for no benefit at all or just because it's fun or just because it's what you see other strong people doing. It is actually because it helps stabilize the abdomen and spine. So you're actually going to...
help prevent maybe back injuries, a really common back injury. People think, oh, squats and deadlifts, oh, they're bad for your back or whatever because you can potentially put your spine into flexion while it's loaded and actually performing the Valsalva maneuver will help prevent that because it will stabilize your spine and keep your trunk more rigid. Also, if you are going to...
perform this technique and do the Valsalva maneuver. You're going to have to remember that in between each rep, you can exhale. You can even breathe a little bit a couple of times and then inhale and do the next rep. That's totally fine. You don't have to, like I said before, you don't have to like crank out reps, bang, bang, bang, bang, bang. But also keep in mind, you also don't want to drive yourself to hyperventilize. You don't like exhale because that's also not going to be good for you.
So another common piece of advice you may hear about holding your breath while lifting weights is that you should inhale on the descent or the eccentric part of the lift and then exhale on the concentric part of the lift. This again is not going to provide necessarily the most stable core and abdomen and on submaximal attempts this is probably okay but it is not going to allow your body to produce as much force as
Fully Bracing Your Core. So if it's a warmup, if it's really light weights, if you're just trying to work on some range of motion, kind of get yourself going and kind of feel out, feel how your legs feel, feel how your back feels, this is probably fine. But for the heaviest sets, the heaviest weights, your hardest weights, you're going to want to fully brace that core throughout the rep. I hope that helps. I hope people got some good advice.
and I hope people will practice this at home a little bit even you know it kind of might be weird if you're sitting on the couch and you your your friend or your significant other whatever looks over and you're sitting there like inhaling and tighten your core and then for a half a second and then you're exhaling but if you haven't ever done it before it is a skill that takes practice and so just like anything else you can practice outside of the gym when you're not lifting weights and that will help you get better at it when you are in the gym and you are lifting weights.
everyone liked that tip and we'll see you next time.