Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Cole Moore. Thank you, everybody, for listening. If you are new here, please consider subscribing to the podcast. And if you are a returning listener, thank you so much for coming back. We really appreciate it. And if you like what you're hearing and you want to support the podcast, you can definitely share the podcast and give us a review and a five-star rating wherever you listen to podcasts. But sharing it is really great. It doesn't cost you a buck. And I've been getting a lot of threads sent to me, a lot of posts, a lot of tags and stuff.
And I really, really appreciate all of that. And so thanks, everybody, for just spreading the word. It does help us out a lot. And if you want to donate with a couple bucks, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate because we are ad-free. We have no ads whatsoever, other than obviously that we are a coaching company. But if you can't afford us or you don't want to work with us, that's totally fine. We are here to help out anyway with the podcast. So thanks, everybody, for all the support.
And if you want to become a coaching or consultation client, that is pretty much our ultimate Patreon for the podcast. You can reach out to me, empiricalcycling at gmail.com, and we can get a conversation started. Because right now is mid-September. It's pretty busy for transfer season. We get a lot of new inquiries this time of year. But even if you're thinking about it for later in the year and you just want to get a conversation started, please reach out. Don't hesitate. I'm really happy to hear from everybody.
Thanks everybody for reaching out for those of you who already have. Really appreciate it. And if you would like to consult with us, we do a lot of consultations and...
Our time is your time. We're going to answer your questions, especially if you're self-coached and you like what you're doing. You just want a little bit of guidance or sometimes you need a lot of guidance. That's okay. We can do that too. It's a good time to reach out, ask your questions. We can look at your files. We can review your season. We can help you plan for next year based on you and your goals and get the individualized kind of coaching stuff that all of our actual regular clients get. And we're just going to get it for you in just an hour or a little bit more oftentimes.
So reach out to me for that if you are curious about it. And follow me on Instagram, at empiricalcycling, in case you couldn't guess. We've got weekend AMAs up in the stories about training. Ask your questions there or just give it a follow.
Yeah, also this is where we ask questions for the podcast. And most podcasts lately, we have done that. I actually completely forgot this time. So that was my bad. But at the end of this podcast, I bring up some of the hot takes that everybody had, the controversial training opinions that I solicited on Instagram a couple weeks ago. That podcast I did with Kyle. My computer ate it, unfortunately, and we cannot get it back. So I brought a couple of those. We may or may not rerecord it with Kyle. But regardless.
I think this is a fun podcast, because this is...
This is our newest coach here at Empirical Cycling, Megan Easler. She's a pro road cyclist here in the U.S. She's got multiple podiums, top fives and tens in UCI races and at Pro Road Nats. She was selected for the national team and went to Europe to race with the national team. She's got 60 UCI points to her name. She's a great time trialist. She's a great road racer. She's a really good sprinter. She's a multi-talented rider, and she's absolutely fantastic.
So not why I picked her to coach with us. You know, she's been a personal client of mine for a while, and she's also, she's got a really scientific mind.
And I really, really appreciate that. And you're going to hear more about that in this podcast. We kind of poke a little fun at it because it leads her to doing some silly stuff, but also she knows that she shouldn't do that kind of stuff with her clients. We talk about that too. She's not somebody who lets her own talent blind her judgment with other people. And that's something that kind of...
Average Speed folks like myself, I don't think we typically have an issue with that kind of thing. You know, folks like me, we are more...
prone to think that we know everything when we don't, and that's a lesson that, you know, we always learn over and over and over again in coaching. I forget if that comes up in this podcast, but regardless, Megan is great because we talk more about her season and her training ups and downs and kind of how the whole season went and the rigors of being a pro cyclist here in the U.S. with a very full training schedule. You can go.
to her road results or pro cycling stats, and you can see how her season has went, and you can even compare it to previous seasons. It's been a really good season for her, and we are, of course, hoping more from next year. But, you know, we talk about her time in Europe, and we talk about what European racing is like in the women's peloton versus here in the US. We also kind of, we also get into some of our, you know, other personal things, like we kind of talk about our
Healthy and Unhealthy Relationships with Food. And we also kind of talk about high-volume riding and her experience with that versus previously. And we also talk a lot about, you know, coaching and individualization and stuff like that. For me and Megan, it's actually a pretty regular conversation, although you'll hear me attempt to guide it like I'm doing a podcast interview, but for the most part, we're just chatting and having a good time like usual.
So thanks everybody for listening in and without further ado, here is my conversation with Coach Megan Easler. One of the things I look for in coaches is like having had a variety of experiences themselves with like with coaching, with racing and with like their own personal training history and you've had a lot of everything. So, so why don't we start with not to
Not to make this all about me, but like what, what was different when you started working with me as a coach, like last, and that was like what, last June, I think, right, to start? Yeah, basically came into this season kind of wrecking myself with like two or three, like 30-30, 40-20 workouts a week, and I'm just like, why am I so tired? And then... Was that in between racing?
It was like primarily like leading into racing. So it'd be like three, four weeks before a big event, you're just like pounding these down. So you come into the event totally tired AF and then race, have a little bit of rest. And then if you had some time to do some more, do some more and then go into the next race. And I think a big thing that got cut out was like the longer endurance rides. It was just like, what kind of intensity could you get in?
Between Races was, like, the goal, it seemed, and I don't know, you think, like, ride hard, get faster is, like, how it works, and it's not always how it works, and I kind of found that out the hard way. So, yeah, stepping up the endurance, I think that's, like, all I did, and I got, like, so much better, like.
for the second half of the season. Yeah. And you know what's funny is like, you know, with all the intensity, I've learned that you recover super, super quick. Like your legs are back after a hard race in like four or five days, even if you're still sleepy. Yeah. And feeling a little tired with that. So I think, you know, I think normally I would...
Guess that you could recover very quickly from a bunch of hard, high intensity, but it's like, it seems like when it's on the menu for like a couple months, you know, even somebody who's as gifted as you aerobically and with recovery, you know, it seems like that still takes its toll. Yeah. I mean, like, just kind of, you can overdo a good thing is kind of how it seems. Yeah. I mean, so.
I mean, maybe because we don't normally talk about like my exact coaching process on the podcast. So, you know, you're, you know, you're like a, you've received it firsthand. So like, so what's the difference with the intensity work between, you know, working with your previous coach and working with me? Does it depend? Like, it's like, I mean, I was giving like prescribed VO2 zones, which is like one very distinct thing. Like, I don't know if you can.
Properly prescribed someone a VO2, like, power target. That's one thing that was different. I also feel like overall, like, I mean, I was doing, like, some weeks I feel like three 30-30 sessions. Like, I would never do that now, really. Like, in one week, that's, that would tip me overboard, honestly. It's like one in one week is good enough. Yeah.
Oh, no, totally. I mean, and that's kind of like for something like that, especially like getting into racing, you know, one of those hard workouts a week for most people is plenty. And then you've got to recover and do aerobic stuff, you know, especially if you're like heading into road season, you know, you don't want to be overcooked for that kind of stuff. And I think actually, I think you having had that experience while it sucked was like actually valuable for you as a coach.
And so, like, how has that kind of informed how you coach people now? I definitely know how much would put me overboard, so I'm not going to prescribe that. But also just, like, I kind of know how I felt after, like, you do a couple and you're like, wow, I feel really good. And then you do a few more and you're like, okay. And then there's a few more after that. And you're just like, man, I'm exhausted. And you're just like.
Am I getting unfit? Like, what's going on? So it's like, that kind of taught me to, like, read the signs for people. So, like, if I notice that, like, you know, they did too much intensity, it's like, okay, we can, like, bring it back now and recover from that. And then usually they feel better, like, after taking some rest. But, yeah, I feel like that made me know how to not overdo it by just, like, listening to what kind of people are cueing you in on. Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, and, you know, it's not like I let our coaches work any other way other than, like, actually talking to people. But, you know, because I actually was just reflecting on this the other day. I remember the first client I had where he was like, I don't think you listen to me enough, and I probably didn't. But he was like, you know, for X amount a month, which was honestly not much, he was like, you should be talking to me every day. And I was like, okay, for this amount.
No, but also I was like, I should charge more and be much more engaged because I think it's going to really help with the coaching process. And it was like night and day in terms of being able to read people. Because actually with that guy, one of the things about him is that even if we had talked every day, it wouldn't have helped anything.
because he was always asking, I need more training, I need more training, I'm getting unfit, and I'm like, no, you are tired, you've been at this for months, and I see all the signs of fatigue, and he's like, nope, please give me more training, and I'm like, no, and that was where we didn't see eye to eye, it was on the rest, and that was the end of him on my roster, by his choice, but I wanted to keep trying to get him to rest. Yeah, some people don't understand how critical that part is, the resting part. Yeah.
Actually, I think you're actually in a good position to talk about one of the other things that I think a lot of people – I've been harping on for a long time that a lot of people have a misconception with women and volume and recovery and training load because you do some ridiculous volume or what people would consider ridiculous and I think is normal for a pro cyclist.
Talk to me about volume and kind of the difference between what you were doing before and what now and how it's like made an impact on your fitness and everything. Well, I just want to point out that I do still have my lady bits, so they're in good condition. But yeah, that's like one thing that I've changed from last year to this year is actually doing more volume. Like last year, I guess I was averaging like 12, 13 hours a week.
This year, I try to hit like 20 a week. Sometimes I get into like 30. Not like very often, but every once in a while, throw in a big week. That's made, I think, a huge difference on my endurance and just overall. I feel like my FTP has probably got a little boost from that as well. But yeah, I'd say it's pretty critical to this entire like how the season has went.
I mean, I don't, I don't feel like I'm overtrained. I feel like I would have known by now, like my year probably would have been like trash or like at some point I would have like fallen off. But I feel like I stayed pretty consistent through this year, which last year I came out thinking like, yeah, I'm super fit. And then just like didn't have any good results at the bigger races that mattered. So I would say that just doing low volume, high intensity is not always the key.
And, because I'm going to actually, I've got your WKO5 up right now, and you nailed it. 2022, you averaged 16 hours a week. But the first half of your season, you did, for most of your weeks, you did between like 12 and 15. So your average was about 13 and a half. And it was just pretty consistent throughout. It was just like very, very steady. Not a lot of really big push, not a lot of really big rest.
Yeah, and a lot of high intensity. So, you know, I think for some people, they do okay with low volume and high intensity, but I think it comes at a cost. And, you know, what's your, so like, actually, maybe people are curious, like, what are your longest rides? Like, how much, what's your average long ride these days? Not that I don't know, but. Seven or eight hours is a pretty good day. I try to shoot for seven. If I get to seven, it's like.
That's good. I don't know. Six doesn't feel long enough to me anymore. And eight's like...
That's like a 9 to 5, that's a little much, but 7 is like my sweet spot right now. 8 makes it feel like a job. Yeah, I don't want it to feel like a job. You're like, oh man, 3 hours in, do I get coffee break yet? I do take a coffee break about 3 hours in. As you should. And actually this year you nailed that your average is 21, and your biggest week was 32 and a half. And that was leading into nationals actually.
So that was like, that was after Joe Martin, it looks like, and leading into NADS. So, yeah, so tell me about, tell me about the big races between last year and this year. And actually, one of the things that you and I have talked about in our other conversations is actually kind of why
Why you were doing all the high-intensity stuff for those races last year? Like, the reasoning your previous coach had given you. And I always think that's really, like, fascinating to consider. It is very fascinating. To quote, like, preparing you for the surging of the racing, which that, like, if you think about it, leading into Redlands is kind of silly because there's a lot of, like, longer sustained climbing, whether it's, like, five minutes or...
you know, 20 some minutes going up Oak Glen and the laps of Oak Glen that are also like 15 or so minutes long gradual climb but I mean the women's racing I don't know if it's different than the men's but like it's not that surgy at Redlands it's just like can you grind it out I mean like Highlands is a very intense circuit race which maybe the 30, 40, 20s would have been great for that but
For the rest of the stage race, I was dying. And I don't think I was at all prepared for whatever was going on. Yeah. And the thing that you said that stuck with me is that he was like, I think he said, well, you're not going to be fighting for the win, so you've got to, you know, and I was like, why not? Oh, yeah. Yeah. I mean, like, everyone, I feel like, should train, like, you know, they want to win. Like, maybe you're not going to win, but I...
I don't think you should be limiting your training based off of, like, well, you're not going to win, so let's, like, not do some proper FTP intervals. Like, I didn't do a single FTP interval, I don't think, at all, until I started working with you last year. Yeah, let's, I don't think, let's plan on you being pack fill is a very good strategy. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, like, why even go to the race, like, if you're just gonna...
You're like, I want my fight for 45th. Congratulations to me. And I wouldn't even sprint for 45th. Like, I don't want to prepare for that. Oh, I mean, and I also think that one of the consequences of low volume, unless you have a super, super, super deep training history on the bike or...
Or like you are one of those genetic freaks who just builds mitochondrial density like nobody's business, you know, either in response to like moderate or high volume or even high intensity, whatever it is. I think for the most part, like when you're not riding very much, like when you're doing like 15 hour weeks on average, like some people can go from that to a stage race, but like you've got to figure out another way to work your endurance.
Um, and if you don't have a constriction on your time, I think the best way to build that endurance and build that depth is to just ride more. That's the thing is I like wanted to ride more. I said, Hey, I am taking quite a bit of time off this summer to race and I have tons of time to ride. And I even like, um, had to text one day this coach and was like, Hey, I don't have a workout in for this day. Like, um,
Like, what should I do? And he's like, do you have time for like three hours endurance? And I just, in my head, I'm like, I told you I have literally all day, all day on the weekends. Like I have all the time in the world to like get in a ride. I wanted to ride more and I just felt like kind of restricted. But, you know, like it's one of those things where you don't want to like stray from the plan just in case you like do something wrong and get overtrained or whatnot. Yeah. Well, I mean, that's one of the.
Things about the whole trust the process thing. It's like if you don't have perfect compliance with whatever somebody's vision of the thing is, then if you don't have the fitness you want or something isn't going right, then they can point at that and go, well, you didn't follow the plan. I see this all the time. And sometimes, absolutely, that's the case.
Like if somebody wanted you on the bike five days a week and you rode the bike three days a week, I think there's an easy way to go, okay, yeah, maybe, yeah, you need a little more compliance. But if the person's like, I was super stressed at work or I was sick or the kids, then it's like, oh, well, then I don't want you on the bike that much and we need to just shift our focus about like, you know, enjoyment or maintenance or something like that. Yeah, completely. Yeah. I forgot where I was going to go next. Oh.
I was going to say, so tell me about your favorite part of the races this year, because you had some great TT results. You were on the podium at several of these big TTs. Valley of the Sun, third. Redlands, you were fifth. Gila, second. How is the Gila TT? That is a hard one to pace, too.
I liked it. I don't know why. I think it was the variation in the elevation. You go up for a while, and then you descend, and then you go up and down and up and down, and then you turn around. I don't know. It just kind of changed it up. It was, I think, not even 40 minutes, close to 40 minutes, but it felt like a typical 20-minute time travel. It went so fast. Because you were only pedaling hard for like 20 minutes total. Yeah, yeah. A lot of it was like downhill.
I don't know. That one was super fun. I think that would be probably my most favorite. Yeah. Tell me about what you liked between Redlands, Hila, and Joe Martin. What was your favorite parts of it? And what also did you not like and want to do better at next time? Am I commenting on each one individually? Take your pick. We got a whole smorgasbord and just grab it from the buffet.
I feel like I liked Gila the most. I don't know why I came into that one not expecting much out of myself, and that was one where I did pretty decently. I think I was fourth GC. Yep, fourth points, yep. And I got a...
another podium there for Stage 2 that ended in a sprint, which was wild, because I, like, I don't really consider myself a sprinter. I know that I can kind of sprint, but it's like, oh, okay, like, I can actually do this. So that was, like, that was really nice. But just, like, that whole, like, race itself, like, even on the last day, like, the Hilo Monster, I'm like...
Man, we'll see how it goes, but you know, I'm not like a pure climber, so I was kind of like a little down on myself, but still finished, I think like six on that day, yeah, so I was just like, I don't know, lots of pleasant surprises, but I think that's maybe in part because I came in like not expecting much out of myself, so it was like really low stress, but yeah.
Yeah, I mean, and that's something that I actually have learned about you gradually, because you don't really talk to me about the pressure you put on yourself for this kind of stuff, but it's not insignificant. Yeah. I usually try to, like, take the pressure off myself. Like, if I can downplay something, I totally will. Like, going into it, be like, well, I mean, like, you know, if this doesn't work out, then it's like, whatever. Like, nationals, I had, like, no idea what to expect from myself, so I was like,
How about I just don't expect anything at all? I was like, I don't know. I was just like, I wouldn't even care if I had to just like drive home, like just go hang out with my dog. Like it's just a bike race. I mean, because one of the reasons I think that it's interesting to bring that up is because I think a lot of cyclists put a lot of pressure on themselves for results or for fitness or for like more is more.
kind of stuff. I mean, and I actually, one of the reasons that I think that, another reason I think you make a great coach is that you are, you know, you are willing to, like, put all that down to rest and recover. And because it would be easy to say, like, you know,
More is more. I've got to do more. I've got to ride more. I've got to ride harder. I've got to be lighter or something like that. The list of things goes on that people put pressure on themselves for. I think you've got a great perspective on that, but I also know that you've had struggles with that in the past, too, with your previous sports and running and et cetera. You want to talk about that history for a minute?
Yeah, I mean, are we talking in particular on weight stuff, or just in general? We can, because I think that that might be something where you've got a really good perspective that people might need to hear. Yeah, so I guess like way back in high school, and just like your classic scrawny little runner, and I'm just like, I want to be smaller, I'll be faster, and like, you know, you look like the pro athletes. And so I just started.
Dieting, use quotations around that, because I had no idea what I was doing. I was just like, okay, just like, you know, 1,200 calories or whatnot, that should have me losing some weight, right? And I'm, like, still exercising and, like, kind of, like, totally lost my period. I'm like, well, that's, like, fine, right? Like, pro athletes don't get their period. Like, it's totally normal. And then I ended up, like, seeing my doctor, and she was like, no, you need to eat more.
So I was like, oh, okay, and I got it back for a short little bit, but I mean, this was like a long trend of events where it's like, you gain a little bit of weight and you're just like, God, like, I just look fat and I need to like lose a little bit more and like, I know I made a post about this on Instagram, but like, it gets like way worse, like there were points where it's just like, oh, I ate a little bit too much, like, I better go for a jog, like two miles, three miles, like.
Counteract the Calories, or just like when I finally thought like okay I'm gonna eat more and it just turned into binging like I couldn't actually get myself to like eat a normal amount and just be okay with it like my body was just like oh my god we haven't had food in so long or like I've been restricting too much so you eat too much and then it's just like now you're just like pukey and you can't hold it in like I just feel like um
Like in these sports, I mean, not cycling is not a binge eating sport, but it's just like the pressure you put on yourself. It's like everything matters. It's like if you eat too much, you might be too heavy and then your performance might decrease. This is just like what people think. And then, you know, like you want to eat enough, but you don't want to eat too much. Just, yeah, like it's a hard thing to balance and it takes so much time to like actually like.
I mean, your body knows what it's doing. Like when you like give it, when you listen to it, like it knows like, okay, we can eat the proper amounts as long as you're not like trying to intervene with that process. But it took quite a ways, quite a long time to like figure that out. Yeah. And especially if you're like, if you're a stress snacker like I am, yeah, that could be a problem too.
to like keep the weight off for somebody like me. Cause I, especially if I'm strength training at the same time, like bodybuilders call it dirty bulking, where you eat literally everything in sight and you get really strong, but you also get really fat. And like, that's another type of like, you know, very unhealthy relationship with food. And a lot of it comes from like, you know, stress or like pressure to like get stronger or whatever it is. And like, you know, at bodybuilding actually, I just talk about this all the time.
I'm in the gym all the time as a sprinter myself. So like, so it's like, I'm always thinking about like, oh, wow, these guys have an unhealthy relationship with food as well, because they just want to get bigger. And, you know, and a lot of the time, you know, you watch interviews with strong men, they're like, they're like, yeah, I thought the number on the scale going up meant I was going to get better. And like, I was really just completely unhealthy, just eating Snickers bars all the time.
you know no matter what the sport is like there's there's problems with that but like um that was my mentality when I did CrossFit like uh what junior year of high school and that's where I got into the binge eating problem is like I went from under eating and restriction to like
Oh, I have my cheat day. I'm just going to eat whatever. And since you restrict like six days of the week on your cheat day, you're just like, I'm going to eat everything. 10,000 calories. Yeah, and you're just like, it's for the gains, bro. I mean, maybe a little bit of muscle, but a lot of it's probably just unhealthy like fat and not so good stuff. Yeah, when you overwhelm your body with calories like that, it's like it's wanted to put stuff in the right place, but it can only...
Do a good amount of repair at a certain rate. And if you give it all the calories it needs, then it's like, oh, great, this is great. Oh, my God, it's so much. And it's like, yeah, it gets kind of crushed under the weight of that binge. And it also sets up unhealthy mentality, I think. Yeah, I mean, my binging was like, oh, you don't ever eat, you know, pancakes and cookies and cupcakes, like when you're like restricting during the other six days of the week. So like that became like.
Okay, every meal is gonna be something I can't have, or like can't, you know, like you just like label all these things in your mind is like, oh, that's gonna make me fat or like, yeah, make me gain weight. Yeah. And actually, I think one of the things that I remember most about your Instagram post is your relationship with peanut butter. Yeah, that was an interesting one. Because like, what was this?
To, I mean, before the start of last year's season, I had a different coach telling me, like, hey, like, maybe you should come into the esports world, like, at, like, 125 pounds, like, cut out the peanut butter, and I was, like, I think 127, 128-ish, maybe a little more, but I was, like, I don't know if I can just drop three or four pounds and, like,
I think it was a month or two. And I'm, I'm already like pretty light, I feel like, or lean, like I feel, I'm usually hungry all the time. So I'm just like, how can I cut out more food is the real problem. But I was like, yeah, I guess I could see like what happens if I cut out peanut butter. And like, my period was like two weeks late, like it didn't come back until I like.
actually started eating peanut butter again. I think it's because I wasn't getting enough fat in my diet. Exactly, yeah. I don't really cook with oils and I wasn't eating any kind of fatty stuff other than peanut butter. I don't eat a lot of just nuts because I'm usually just chowing down peanut butter. And you're allergic to a lot of stuff too, so why risk it? Yeah, why risk it? Peanut butter gets the job done. But yeah, that was an interesting...
Self-Experiment. Yeah, and actually, I've heard a lot of people still villainize fats to some degree. I think in the last 10 or 15 years, the conversation on fats has come around, but I remember in high school in the late 90s, we had a bio teacher who was like, oh yeah, you're eating a lot of fats, you're getting fat. It's like, well, it's not necessarily true.
Can be, but like, how many fats are we talking about? It's like, and then the concept of healthy fats came in and like, oh, you actually need this for like bodily function. You know, because it's like, you know, it's, it's like, it's almost like Lamarckism, where it's like, eating fat makes you fat, like, it seems like it should work. It's like, you know, Lamarckism is like, you know, if you want your kids to have like big biceps, you get big biceps on your own. It's like, you know, it's like a false inheritance kind of thing.
False Relationship. Yeah, that makes sense. Yeah. Actually, do you remember Lamarckism from bio? Because you're a biochemist by degree in trade. I don't know if I learned that, to be honest. They probably thought it was silly. It is. But I actually really enjoy those kind of weird things like phlogiston, which is...
I think eventually became oxygen. It was like the stuff of fire or something like that. I forget exactly. But I love stuff like that because it's like people trying to piece together how stuff works, but they don't have all the information. And so they make up really crazy stuff. And it's like some of my favorite stuff in all of science is like the weird stuff that turned out to be wrong.
Yeah, I feel like we always learn those at the beginning of every chapter in a biology book, and you're just like, wait a minute. But you never get tested on it, so you forget it. Well, yeah, you're like, I only need to know the current theory, because all the previous ones, you're reading this, and you're like, this isn't right, and then they're like, that's before they found out, you know, X, Y, Z. Yeah, Darwin actually thought inheritance was from the gemmules in the blood. The what? Gemmules. G-E-M-M-U-L-E-S.
Is that like the DNA steps before the DNA steps? Yeah, he had to come up with a mechanism. And he was like, well, there's a thing that gets passed down. We don't know what it is. So I'm just going to, I don't know. A GM mule. Nice. Yeah. Wait till you hear about the homunculus. I'm going to have to like touch up my evolutionary. Don't worry about it. I just love all this stuff. But anyway, I actually love that you have a biochem degree.
Um, and, cause I, I think, cause the other day, um, you, you had like gone out and tried something and, and it was, it turned out to be a bad idea or like, oh no, it was like the, the muffins thing, right? The muffins. And I was like, this is, this is peak Megan right here. Oh yeah. We're still waiting on the results. That is hilarious. So anyway, so like for people listening, um,
And Megan's scientist brain is like so, it's like such a scientist brain. She's always like, I wonder what happens if, and then goes out and tries it. And like, it's one of my favorite things about you. Yeah. Do I have to elaborate on the muffins? No, you don't have to elaborate on the muffins. Right. But I, but I like, I know this is you in training.
Yeah, yeah. Where you're like, I wonder how I'm feeling. I wonder if this is feeling okay. And you'll go out and do a one-minute effort and be like, wow, that sucked. I guess I'm not feeling okay. And then you'll try five minutes to FTP and be like, wow, that sucked even worse. I'm just going to go home. Yeah. I was going to try it once, maybe twice, and then get my solid answer and then go home with that one. Yeah.
In a coaching relationship, to have somebody who's willing to go experiment and go try. And this is kind of how we learned that four or five days after a super hard event, your legs are recovered. After a hard VO2 block recently, you set a massive one-minute PB, stuff that would make other people's eyes water.
It made my eyes water. So much so that I did the Megan test and did it again. Yes, that was my favorite thing. You were like, and it was like within like 15 watts or something like that. I was like, holy shit. Oh, it was within like three. God. It was within three. That's why I was like, I don't know. I could have gone harder, but maybe not because the second one was just as good. But then you're also like, oh, what's the error of my power meter? It was basically, which is also like the craziest thing. And then you're like.
and then it's like because it's post via two block and you're like, all right, that was good. So five minute test, five minute test is like, uh, no, no. Um, but I, I, I love that fuck around and find out attitude. Yeah. Um, but you don't do it to like the, to the, to the degree that it's like detrimental to training. It's like, it's like, you know, when you're in that like recovery kind of like medium, like where are we at block with fatigue and, uh, not where are we at block, like where are we at period?
Am I recovered yet? Have the watts come back? Is my motivation come back? Am I done being sleepy? You're out there trying stuff. And it's great because otherwise, like you coach people, you've got to program it in. Otherwise, and you're like, boy, I hope this is right. And then you find out based on people's feedback. Yeah, I mean, you shouldn't have to do a whole FTP workout to find out today is not the day to do a whole FTP workout.
I feel like that I've become a little bit more in tune with. Yeah. I mean, and this is like, and this is also, I think, kind of goes to something else I want to touch on is like you and I have also joked about trust the process. I believe Kyle and I have joked about it on the podcast too, but it's like, it's one of those things where it's like trust but verify, you know, if something's supposed to make you faster, like, like you've been like mid training block and you're asking, you're like texting me like, does this.
Is this actually working? Are you sure? This doesn't feel like it's working. And I'm like, oh no, here's why it's working. Like, look at this, this, this. And then you look at it and you're like, I'm not seeing what you're seeing. And it keeps me so on my toes. It's so engaging and fun. So I really appreciate that about you to be so inquisitive. And that was even before you were coaching people. You were like, how does this work? How do you know it's working?
and yeah I feel like part of that's just like maybe a little bit of PTSD trust issues because like you ask some coach why are you giving me this and then they're just like uh and they'll like give you some like blanket answer or like can't explain how it does you know how it like improves your performance or FTP or whatever it is you're working on so it's just
I don't know, it's nice to actually, like, have the answer, and then, like, you can have the confidence to do the workout, like, you know, that's actually trusting the process, and then you see, like, the end goal, but if you just keep doing these things over and over again, and don't see any progress, it's like, well, maybe it's time to, like, rethink that. Yeah, I had a consult, God, I can't remember how long ago now, where he was, like, he was basically asking, like, is...
I've been doing these workouts with my coach, and I'm hoping for some kind of breakthrough. And his coach was also hoping for a breakthrough. And that happens sometimes, for sure, where you do the same thing, and it's really hard, and then one day, suddenly, you've got a lot more watts. But it had been a year and a half or something like that, or a year, and the guy, it was just steady. And I was like, you would have seen it by now if this were going to happen.
and I hate it to break the news to him about that but I mean sometimes you need a second set of eyes and it's like I well and the reason I kind of bring all that up is because I think one of the things that I've always tried to do is I've always tried to make like the the nerd shit kind of line up with real life experience like like if we act upon these known principles this should improve and if it does great if it doesn't well
Now we need to ask, why not? And I think, I think you've, you know, you've seen that firsthand. It's like, it's like, I give you an explanation. And then you're like, no, I don't know about this, but it sounds right. All right, I'll try it. And then like, I mean, how many watts of FTP have we, have we gotten you like just this year? 30? I think it's at least 30. I think. Well, after this last block, we may be looking at like, depending on how the recovery goes, a lot more than that.
Yeah. It's just a slow process. It is a slow process. But you also know that having done two VO2Max blocks now, that you've seen the refractory time on it, too. Yeah. And I also think that it's great that you didn't just get the bump like Corey does or like Katie does.
where it's like, you know, you've got that like that fatigue and I've had this exact fatigue where it's like, oh God, am I going to, am I recovering from this yet? Oh geez, how does, am I going to be done yet? Oh my God, can we stop recovering? And it's like a couple of weeks and then as the fatigue goes away, like the watts start to come up and you're like, oh, there's the gains I had. Yeah, like it was super slow last winter. I remembered like I was kind of.
A little frustrated. I didn't feel like I was getting unfit by any means. I was just like, well, that was pointless. And then I'm just kind of doing like sweet spot on the trainer and like gradually it went up and up. And I was like, that's weird. Like, I mean, I like these numbers, but maybe I'm doing them too hard. And then it just kind of became obvious the more I did outdoors.
But yeah, I just, now I know it takes a little bit longer for me. Like, I remember one of your podcasts, I think you said it could take anywhere from like two weeks to two months. And I'm just like, two months? It's me.
That's definitely me. Yeah, it is kind of you. Yeah, I remember last block in the spring, we started to see flashes of the recovery after a month, but we also had a confounding variable, which is that you were on a trainer that you were in between gears for your preferred cadence at FTP. Oh my god, I hate that.
And you were like, can it please be nice outside? But you're like, you're in Iowa, so it's not going to be nice outside in January. No, I don't think it was nice until like... March? April? Like late March? Northeast U.S. also, like up in Boston, it's about the same. So, yeah. So, I mean, that was also like...
I mean, that was frustrating to you, and frustrating to me, to kind of work through that with you. And then, actually, I remember when you were visiting here, and we were doing all the aero testing and stuff like that, you had set up the feedback. And then you were like, oh my god, I can actually do this on the feedback. This is great. Because the feedback kind of adjusts instead of keeping you stuck between gears.
Yeah, it's a little bit better. I still prefer outdoors. I don't know if it's just like the actual speed of like the bike itself, like the faster you're going. No, well, not sure. Well, you and me are like that.
Where, if it's faster, we like it better. Like, we feel like we can push harder. I mean, and this is one of the reasons that you're a good sprinter and a good TT-er as well. Because, like, there's a lot of people who can put out a ton of power up a climb and you get them on a TT bike going 30 miles an hour and they're like, I can't push. And you're actually a little bit more the opposite, where it's like, if you're going uphill, it's like, you know, also could be because you...
Live in Iowa, and it's all flat out there. Yeah, it's really hard to say. There's a few variables here. Yeah, so I mean, because that's one of the things that we've got for you for training for next year, where it's like, that's an obvious weakness, so we're going to do some of that very deliberately. Yeah, sadly, the mountains will not just grow in Iowa. No, but I keep telling you to move to somewhere with mountains.
I know. Waiting on Cooper. He's got to finish school. Yeah, that's right. Then hopefully. But Iowa's cheap. The housing is so cheap here. That's true. And you also get, you're near the Iowa Fair. And I actually can't imagine having a poor relationship with food and like going to the Iowa State Fair and then like seeing all the food there and you're like, I can't have any of this. It looks so good. Yeah.
Not good. I feel like those years I just avoided it. So they have some healthy options. I think I remember one year going and looking specifically for the healthy options like peanut butter and jelly on a stick. Or I would get maybe a cup of corn. And there's obviously those other years where I was like, I'm going for the deep fried Snickers, maybe two of them, and that's it.
Oh, God. I've actually never had a deep-fried Snickers. That sounds amazing. Dude, it's really good. They just, like, have a Snickers on a stick. They dip it in fried batter, and then they put a little powdered sugar on it. I'm in. Let's go. And the whole thing, like, you bite into it, and it's just, like, gopping, melty, like, chocolatey goodness. It's so good. I'm in. Sign me up. I actually thought you were going to say, for healthy options, it was, like, fried okra, or, like...
Fried Corn, or everything is fried, like a fried vegetable. No. Okay, well that's good. I feel like there's like three vendors that have like anything moderately healthy and it's not a vegetable. Oh, actually, one of the other things I wanted to talk to you about, it's not related to fried vegetables, but it's about Europe. Tell me about your time.
with the national team in Europe for the latest Argenta Tour and the latest Tour of Balois. I'm sure I butchered the titles of those. I'm sorry. I think that was good. I honestly don't know if I know how to say them. But yeah, it was a super eye-opening experience. I'm almost sad that I didn't start the season with those two races just because... How so? It was...
The hardest racing that I've ever done. Like, um, Aaliyah was actually joking about this, and she did really well at this, like, the last NCL race, but she was like, the U.S. crits are gonna seem so easy now, and then she just goes off and, like, rides off the front, so, you know, like, if that says anything to, like, how good these races are, I feel like, for preparing you, um, as, like, a bike racer, like, they were,
Very technical, so like lots of corners, turns, like slamming brake, maneuvering, quite a bit of crashing, and very high intensity as well. It's basically like doing three-hour crits is what it felt like. Yeah, I think when we were texting while you were there, you said it was like a gravel crit. It was like as hard as a gravel race, but the actual surging demands of a crit.
Yeah, yeah, it was basically like all out from the gun, all out in the middle, all at the end, just all out, all out. Three-hour criterium, hell yeah. And you're just like getting out of the saddle, like every corner to like sprint, fight for a position that you're probably not going to gain, and then like sit back down, go hard, get up, sprint, sit down, go hard. Like it's just like there was no rest, which was really fun, and I feel like, you know, there becomes this like huge mental component because it's like.
You can't be off. You always have to be on, looking for, like, dangerous riders or, like, sketchy stuff or, like, you know, I have to move up. I'm getting too far back in the peloton. Or, like, there's some riders off the front I didn't even realize. Like, you're, like, too focused on what's around you. Like, it's just, like, it was a whole new aspect to racing that I didn't really get in the U.S. that I really appreciated having.
Yeah. I mean, and also, and you were actually doing great on the GC until you got caught behind a crash. Like, you were 24th in the first time trial, and then you, you know, then you were like top 20 in the first stage, which wasn't that later that day? Yeah. Yeah, crazy double days. But then like, yeah, then day three, you were like, you were like 12th in GC, and then, yeah.
Day 2, yeah, Day 3, then you got caught behind a crash and you were like, God damn it, I fell asleep for half a second or I let myself get too far back. Yeah, with that, it was a really windy day and there ended up being some crash for some reason. I don't even know what happened. And I slammed on my brakes, didn't crash, crash. Some girl fell on me. And so I tipped over into the grass and I was like,
Alright, whatever, I'll get my bike up and go. And I get up on my bike and I start sprinting. And, like, I'm sprinting to try to catch up to the group that was ahead of the crash for so long. I think, like, almost an entire lap. And I was, like, drafting off some of the team cars, getting back to the main peloton. And when I finally got back, it was, like, not long after that, I think it was...
DSM started in Echelon, a very productive one that shelled a ton of people. So I just like going all out for, I don't even know, 10, 15 minutes, maybe more. And then all of a sudden I have nothing left to like maneuver around all these people that are getting shelled. I don't even know if I was in the right position. It was just all like a blur. Like after that crash, it just got so hard. But yeah, it's...
It kind of felt like one of those races where it was like, just be ahead of the crash. Like, I think maybe 10, 15 of those girls had like avoided most of the damage of the crashes that happened that entire tour. Like, everyone else is like out of the GC position because they're behind a crash. Yeah. I mean, and it's like, it's really interesting because the people who did really well there, like, they're like Belgians.
You know? Yeah. Or, you know, or they're Dutch, like Lucinda Brand won, like Emma Norsgaard, Anna Henderson, like that's, that's the top three in the GC. I mean, a lot of that came down to like the time trial too, but like you had to also not lose, you know, a minute or two or three getting caught behind a crash. And like, you know, some of, you know, when I was watching it on TV, because this one was broadcast on like a lot of the
U.S. two-point-something races. Yeah. I was just like, it looked like proper Belgian racing. And one of those days, you said, we got the whole experience. Like, we got lightning, we got hail, we got rain. Oh, yeah. Which day was that? That was Argenta? Argenta? That was different than Balois, just a single-day race. But, yeah, it straight-up poured really bad and hailed.
and then we saw lightning and I was this was about halfway through the race we're going to the second finishing circuit and I was like okay they're gonna pull us like I mean this is my first Belgian race I'm like so fried I've been going so hard for probably an hour and a half at this point I'm like I'm ready to mentally check out I start drifting towards the back I was like lightning they're gonna stop the race they don't stop the race they keep going so I gave myself like five minutes I was like
Okay, I have to get back into it. And so I start, like, slowly making my way towards the front again. But, yeah, that was wild. I'm so glad that you actually got that opportunity because I think that's one of the things that really sets, you know, at least women's racing in the U.S., it sets it into a different perspective.
So how, like, before, like, would you, do you think you would characterize, like, like, women's domestic racing in the U.S. any differently now, having gone there and, you know, done a bunch of Belgian race days? Yeah, um, I definitely think that if
People Aren't Taking U.S. Racers Seriously. It's because the lack of skill required to race our races. I know that sounds like really bad, but when our stage races are just set up on like huge open highways and then just like a result is based on like, can you climb this climb? Like, but over there, there's a lot of races where it's just like.
Are you the most technical rider and punchiest rider and, like, smart rider? Like, can you be always in the right position at the right time, like, ahead of the crashes? Like, can you maneuver around a pack that's, like, smushed, literally, like, from one edge of the road to the other side of the road? A tiny road. Yeah, and a tiny road. Like, the width of maybe one and a half lanes wide. And it's cobbled.
at most, and it's cobbled, and there's medians in the middle and on the edges. Yeah, did you get the guy with the flag over his head, like, doing the dance? Oh, yeah. We got the guys with the flag. It took me so long to figure out what those signs meant, like, what they were trying to signal. Oh, yeah. Yeah. I mean, and actually, you know, it's interesting because, like, I think, and I don't want to sound...
I don't want to sound down on the racing in the U.S. at all, because there's a lot of really talented bike racers here that should get – they're really fast, they're really badass, and they should get more opportunities in Europe and everything. But some of the other races like –
compared to some of the races that you've done coming up, because I hear a lot of women complain about this, where nobody wants to sit on the front and do anything. Anybody who does gets brought back. In a lot of ways, it's very negative racing, or it sounds like it. I haven't done it. I've seen it. But it seems like there's not a lot of...
Bigger teams, like, willing to get on the front and, like, do proper work. And so, like, you go to UCI races here and, like, that's some, like, you know, proper racing as you might normally recognize it. Yeah. I was going to say, too, like, I feel like it's not like I'm super down on, like, our U.S. racing. It's like we're, we don't get this opportunity to have.
These types of fields of women, like racing at that high intensity, like, it's just totally different, like, I mean, they grow up racing those races, and they get really good at, like, what those races demand, and we just have a totally different, like, way of racing over here in the U.S. But yeah, it's just, it's different, is what I would categorize it as. Yeah.
What moments do you remember from this season where you're like, I think I can do better next year? Because I think, you know, we talk a lot about, you know, positive things, but we also, you know, as we coach people, but, you know, that process of like, well, let's be honest with ourselves, like what needs to be done better? So like, so where were you, like, was it a race moment? Was it training? You know, was it like something off the bike where you're like, this is going to have a big impact next year if I, you know.
Change This or Fix This? I feel like it's climbing for me. I think being in Iowa is a struggle. The first thing that popped into my mind was like Oak Glen of Redlands. It wasn't a particularly bad day for me, but it definitely was not the best that I could have had. And I think part of it was due to like a bit of dehydration.
Half a bottle for the entire race because I really had to pee. Found out that I cannot get myself to pee on the bike, which may be useful for next year, but I wish I didn't have to have that skill. But yeah, I just feel like it's got to be like the cadence thing of climbing at a high power. That's kind of like my biggest limiter and just like not being ever.
in the mountains, or any hill, really. Our biggest hills are like a minute long. Yeah, and I've, I've, I think I've mentioned on the podcast once or twice, like, oh, if somebody's got a specific limiter, that's when we do low cadence training. Like, yeah, you've got exactly that specific limiter, and like, that's why, exactly why we're going to do low cadence training. Yeah, I remember you being like, oh, low cadence is dumb, blah, blah, blah. And I'm just thinking like, wait a minute, could this be the solution to my problem? I mean, I don't.
I'm not a huge fan of 30, 40 RPM at X Newton meter torque. Do people do that? They do. I was thinking 70 RPM. That's where I'm going to go with this. 70, 80. I've seen a lot of 25, 30, 40 RPM. You assign it based on Newton meters, not in terms of
Power, anything like that, because at that point, it's really, you're not, the metabolic limitation is a little different, like you're really spreading it out through all the big motor units as you do these, you know, giant gear pedaling, but I'm like, I'm probably 50% certain at this point that a lot of the benefits are either like neurological, like you get a lot of neural drive from doing that kind of stuff, and you get used to pushing those big gears, so when you're doing it at like 80 RPM, it's, hey, this is pretty chill.
I think the other part of it is that people may not recruit those large motor units that often. And so when you do that kind of thing, you actually stock them up with some glycogen. And I don't necessarily think that it's the best to aerobically train them in terms of their repeatability or anything like that, but it seems to have some kind of mechanism between neurological and just like, you know.
having some extra capacity to push. But it doesn't seem to me like it's any better than normal TTE training or race efforts. Yeah, it's not the key that you're missing to boosting your FTP by 50%. No, in fact, it would not be that at all based on how the mechanism of FTP works. It would not do that in the least.
Despite the fact that I've seen a lot of – at this point, they're pretty old. I've seen a lot of papers looking at strength training and endurance training and the positive effects they have. Like, Fiat Max usually doesn't go up. Like, somebody's 20-minute test will go up, but, you know, it's not from having more aerobic capacity, that's for sure. Yeah. I mean, that just doesn't make sense.
Alright, so Megan, because I had this podcast episode eaten, and I hope Kyle and I get to re-record it at some point, we talked about controversial training takes, and people submitted theirs, and at the end of it, Kyle actually was like, oh, I've got one, and I completely forgot to, like, come up with some for myself, and so, like, Kyle and I spent a couple minutes figuring out our own controversial training takes, so, like, you know, so what are your
Training Takes, or even Racing Takes, that you think might be controversial? That you can do endurance rides too hard. Most people ride endurance too hard. Like, trying to hit that very specific 70% of your FTP or whatnot. Which is, that would wreck me. I don't really do that. Did you ever actually?
I was prescribed it, yes, or close to it. How did that go? And what were the volumes like? And this was, I assume, while you were doing all that very high-intensity stuff. It's like two or three hours. I remember doing it at one point, and I think I got really overtrained. It could have been a multiple-factor deal. But I didn't feel like I was recovering, and I would have endurance ride.
70% of my FTP for like two or three hours, and then a workout, and like I'd have maybe like one rest day a week or two, but these endurance rides were screwing me. It was like basically a second workout. I'd have like so many workout days like a week, like five workout days a week because endurance was so hard. So I just ended up overdoing it week after week, telling this coach, hey.
I'm roasted, and they're just like, oh, it's just general training fatigue, like, we'll just, like, reduce an interval tomorrow by, like, one rep, and, you know, try that. One rep, oh my god. Yeah, so it's like, oh, instead of, like, two by 20, whatever, it's just do, like, two by 15, or, like, if you're gonna do five reps, do just four. That sounds like a lot harder than a rest day.
When you're tired. Yeah, yeah, exactly. So, like, actually, here's one for you. How do you pace endurance rides? Like, what's your descriptor to people that you coach? Or for yourself, like, what's your guiding light for, like, this is not too hard? I like going off of vibes, but sometimes people are in way too optimistic of a vibe.
If you, like, can kind of, like, feel, you start to, like, breathe harder, like, you couldn't hold a conversation, or, like, you have to really think about this certain power number that you're putting down, like, I just, like, go out and I'm riding and I don't have to think about it, I don't have to, like, feel like I need to pace myself so that I hit this very perfect number for the entirety of the ride, like, if you're, like, thinking about it, I feel like you're doing it wrong, like, you should just be kind of, like,
Riding your bike and eating snacks and like looking at all the corn that you get to like see on your ride. For those in the Midwest. Yeah. I'm going to grab some of the controversial takes from the episode for you. Are these racing? No, these are just like training takes from everybody. I just screenshotted the submissions. All right. So here's a couple.
Controversial takes from people's, that people submitted to my Instagram for the previous episode that got eaten. So here's one. Good training is actually pretty basic and boring. I would say it doesn't have to be. But yes, I mean. I don't know. I mean, it can be, but also.
I feel like I'm not ever, like, doing something too long. You have, like, you're off-season and you're building a little bit, and then you start getting into some, like, sweet spot, tempo, whatever, and then it's like, okay, let's start, like, VO2s, or, like, let's get race ready, or we're racing and we're resting and we're racing and we're resting and just, I don't know, I don't feel like I spend too much time doing, like...
the same thing every single week. I think that's interesting because that's like that's where you personally would like find the monotony and so like you know having the phases go up and down because I think a lot of the time when people think of a workout as boring they're just like oh my god like I've got to do three by 30 sweet spot today it's like steady like that's a boring workout to them or like
They're like, man, I did 3x25 last time. Like, why do I got to do 3x30 today? This is so boring. Like, it's not changing and fun. I think there's a place for that. Yeah, I mean, I would find that fun if I could do my interval a little bit longer the next time. I don't know, maybe we're two different people. Yeah, I mean, well, you've got the brain and the motivation, like, for the process. Like, you...
You know, you really enjoy it. Yeah, I like the workouts. The racing is a nice plus, but I really like the workouts and like pushing myself. All right, here's another controversial take. You don't ever need full rest weeks unless you really fucked up your training. Oh, that is just false. I agree. Well, okay, all right, I can elaborate on why you think it's false. I mean, that's where all the, like, the gains happen. That's where the gains are, bro.
I just, yeah, I don't know. I feel like previous coaches were kind of like that, or they would give a rest week randomly when you don't feel like you need a rest week. But, I mean, if you're properly, like, loading for a few weeks, like, you can't just keep doing that. You have to dial back, recover, and then go again. It's like, if you don't need a rest week, then you're not really pushing that hard. You're not, like, really trying to build that fitness.
Yeah, exactly. Or you don't have a lot of time. I could see somebody where they're on six, eight hours a week, and they're like, man, I don't need a week off the bike or anything like that. Because actually, one of the things I've learned recently, or recently, like in the last year or two, is that everybody's idea of a rest week is very different. Some people don't even look at a bike on a rest week. So let me ask you this.
What's the structure? What's your favorite rest week? How does it go? You finish a hard training block or a stage race or something like that, and now it's Monday, the day after the race, between Monday and Sunday. What's your favorite way to rest up and get back to it? Since I did this a few times, probably Monday off, Tuesday,
probably off, Wednesday recovery ride, Thursday recovery ride, Friday smash effort. The fuck around and find out efforts. Yeah, 5, 10, 20 minutes, I'll see what you got. Usually I feel pretty good by that point. And then just like the weekend is like some endurance, just long ride and get back into it. Let me ask you this. Would you give those like fuck around and find out smash efforts to any of your clients?
Hmm. I mean, if they were actually keen on properly doing the recovery, like, Monday, Tuesday off, like, Wednesday, Thursday, like, pure recovery. Like, I ride, like, my recovery at, like, 30% FTP. Yeah, you do. It's awesome. It is pure recovery. But, yeah, like, if somebody can actually do that, like, yeah, sure, like, let them rip an effort while they're fresh. But I...
I hesitate to give someone the freedom if I can see that they're not being diligent with their recovery process. Actually, I would say that's something that I would individualize with people. For you, I know after a couple of super easy days, you're ready to rip your pedals off, even if you're still a little sleepy. Then we gain good information because sometimes you're just ready to go.
and sometimes you're like I am still tired and I'm just gonna ride easy and that's that and like you're gonna ride those long easy rides on the weekend like anyway but like if you're really wrecked I'm gonna be like keep it to like three or four hours Megan come on like don't yeah don't do your normal like seven almost a day job hours
Yeah, and I've been at that point before where it's like I'm halfway through this ride and I'm like, holy crap, I am tired. Like if I need like a second coffee, like I know I'm done. The two coffee stop ride is a bad one. Yeah, like it's, I don't know, some people have that perspective like I don't know why, like I just couldn't do it today and it's like maybe you're just too tired and you should go home and have a nap and some food. Here's a hot take for you.
Most people don't have the mental fortitude to do real FTP work. I kind of get the sense that most people are like a little optimistic with their FTP if they can't do their FTP. So like, actually, let me ask you this. So for typically, like when you get an FTP lump, and you know, you're like, you can hold your FTP for like maybe 30-ish, 35 minutes.
Even at that point, how long does it take for an FTP effort to feel hard? But also, does that change for you personally when you are fatigued? I feel like it kind of varies. When you're working on a new FTP, you're obviously not going to be able to go out and do it at 2x20 or 2x30, like what you maybe could have done at your previous FTP.
You have to work into it. That's where I was. But at what point does it require mental fortitude? Is it like 20 minutes in? You get two 10-minute efforts and then your third kind of sucks? Or is it kind of hard at first? Where's the mental fortitude? Where would it come from? Where is it for you, actually?
Probably when I'm nearing the last of the intervals. Like the last five minutes. If I'm two minutes in and I'm having this mental struggle, it's just not a day for FTP. But on a typical day, it's just like you've done enough FTP when it's those last two minutes. They're just like, okay, that's enough of that. All right. Here's somebody else's hot take. This is not a hot take if you've listened to the podcast already.
What hour that we've done. The take is, ultimately, there's no substitute for hours. I agree with that. Oh, here's a good one. Because this is something that I find is highly personalized. And this person's take is, it's good to be a bit tired before the race. Definitely personalized. How so? I discovered that this year.
Yeah, the fresher I am, the better. If I can't be fresh, then it's just like, you gotta get a heckin' hard workout, not workout, warm up in, before the race, but typically better to be fresh, personally. So, because this comes down to tapering, because I think actually one of the earliest conversations you and I had about this,
As you were like, I really need some work going into a race. And I feel like that really changed through the year for you. Yeah, pretty much by the second half of the season. Yeah, I don't know. It was pretty early. Yeah, I was like, you know what? I need like three, four easy days.
Prior to the racing, like I don't need a little tune-up, I don't need an all-out effort. You don't need openers. Yeah, like I don't really like openers, unless I want to see how my legs feel, but I won't do it to like open up for the race. Yeah. But yeah, I do like, I don't like missing a long ride, like a week before.
And then I just feel weird. Actually, that's pretty common because one of my other clients, going into his big races this year, we actually did very little of reducing the volume. We actually kept it up pretty well until basically the week before, before getting in a couple easy days. And a little bit after that, he was absolutely flying.
Then we did some maintenance volume, but going into that first race for a good peak, which he held for a couple weeks, it was like hell for leather volume, but we modulated the intensity a lot and the recovery days. Yeah, I feel like my lead into nationals, I think it was two weeks prior to nationals, I did one of the bigger weeks of this year, and I feel like I was just getting my legs.
back from all the racing. Like, I wasn't doing those, like, longer rides or, like, that much hour on the bike. I was on the bike, and so I kind of got them back under me, and then I was like, okay, now I can rest a bit and then go, like, hard at nationals. Yeah, no, that was, I mean, that was, you know, I think we handled that really well, but, like, I think the amount of back and forth you and I had about, like, about, you know, training and rest and, like, tapering and recovery and openers, all that stuff, like,
I mean, that was a long process. Yeah. I mean, it's not something you could take and give to, like, anyone else either. Like, it just wouldn't work that way. And I think that, you know, because every once in a while, like, I get a text from you, and it's like some hard question about something. Like, you're like, why did you give me three hours before X? And I'm like, uh, you didn't have to do it. And you're like, oh, I didn't know that. It's like, I was like, well, because I think I gave you that before, like,
Joe Martin one of the days. Yeah, I think before the first day of Joe Martin, I gave you like three easy hours with a couple of short efforts and you were like, you were like, I don't, I don't, I don't, I didn't need this. And I was like, I was still under the impression you needed some, some work in your legs for these races. And like, we hadn't really come to like, oh no, we need to be really fresh. Yeah. And I mean, that's my fault too. Cause I, I wasn't quite in tune with it either. Cause I'm like, yeah, we'll see. And then it's like, I don't need to like.
Have a take two on that one. It's confirmed. Agreed. All right. Here's a controversial take from a good listener. I know this dude. I like him. Coaching is 20% prescribing intervals and 80% emotional IQ and getting to know athletes.
Wait, can you repeat that? Sure. Coaching is 20% prescribing intervals, so like workouts and stuff, but 80% it's emotional IQ and getting to know athletes, like the interpersonal stuff and learning how to individualize stuff. Yeah, I don't know about the specific percentages, but I feel like those both have big factors into the coach-athlete relationship.
Know nothing about their personal life, or like, kind of how they function day to day, especially how it relates to their intervals. Like, it's just kind of hard to like, give them workouts. Yeah. And it's not like we also need like a daily, you know, personal journal entry about like, you know, I woke up feeling a little stressed, but then I made, you know, pancakes and I put smiley faces with syrup on them. And now, then I felt better. It's like, you know, it's really sufficient to be like,
I'm really, really stressed at work. Or I spent a ton of time on my feet today. Should I ride? What should I do? That kind of stuff. Because I think that a very large part of coaching, this is probably the clientele I attract personally, for my personal roster. But most of the time, I've got to hold people back. Because most people want to work really, really hard. And I'm like, no, no, no, no, no. This is not the time to work hard.
And I'm always also for these folks, I'm always looking for an opportunity to like let them off the leash. You know, it's like if you've got a month and you just finished a race blog and you still got good legs, I'm like, go do whatever you want. Go smash some efforts. Go do some stupid group rides. Go on your 300-mile ride, Odyssey. You know, do the, you know, whatever like eight gaps ride that you all have here. It's like I'm looking for those opportunities for people to have fun, especially when they've got good legs because, you know, you can't be a training monk.
like 365 days a year. Yeah, definitely not. Like I had one of my athletes, he was like, I didn't get enough sleep and my intervals sucked, but it was like opening night of the game or some football game. I'm just like, dude, like you don't have to like nail every single workout because, you know, there's like other fun things in life. Yeah. And we've got to, we've got to strike a good balance.
But yeah, I think, yeah, and the rest thing, I actually think knowing when and how much to rest is actually one of the things in coaching and exercise physiology in general that I don't think we're ever going to know anything about. Yeah, I could agree with that. I feel like
Even sometimes I don't know. Like clearly with like my, like the VO2 block and I'm like, I shouldn't be rusted, but you know. And you kind of are, but you kind of aren't. It's not a simple formula. Yeah, I kind of am, kind of not. And then I sent you the nature paper from Wastock 41 or something and you were like, oh my God, I can't even. And you're a biochemist.
I know. It was just such a struggle. I was like, bottom line, it seems like I'm missing some proteins, and that may take some time. Pretty much, yeah. A non-stoichiometric change in mitochondria protein density. Yeah. Who knows how long it'll take? One to two months. Yep. I know, it's a pain in the ass to wait that amount of time, too, but also, like, you know, it's worth it in the end. Oh, here's a...
Here's a fun take. Riding a lot below quote unquote zone two is okay. I think the last podcast episode, which as of recording came out like last night, but I brought in Marinus to pinch hit for Kyle because Kyle's in NASA Gulag in the desert right now making balloons. I cannot confirm or deny if they're supposed to like be mistaken for UFOs.
They are balloons. They do have some sort of scientific function. I'm not aware of what that is. I know. But anyway, so Marinus was like talking about the volume he does and like what a game changer it's been. And he was like, yeah, I think I must spend most of my ride time around like 50% FTP. And this is a dude with like a 400, you know, over 400 wide FTP. And like his, you know, his first threshold is like in the, you know, low to mid 300s. And he's like,
You know, 200, 250 watts most of the time. He's just spinning away. Nice and easy. Yeah, I feel like that's useful. I get the zones kind of mixed up because I just... Because we don't really use them. Yeah, I'm like, okay, zone two or one endurance, I don't know. But yeah, I definitely agree most of the time should be spent riding pretty chill. I think a lot of my endurance rides are pretty close to 50% FTP.
I don't really go too much above that, because I'd rather just go easier and a little bit longer, because why not? Yeah, and also, it saves you energy for the days you have to go hard. Yeah. Like, if I rode my endurance ride the day before an FTP would work out, I'm not going to be, like, wrecked from it. Right, yeah. Even if it was seven hours. Which is, yeah. Alright, here's...
Here's another training take. I think we probably got two left that I think are going to be fun. If you really enjoy zone one days, you should change sport. Like recovery days. If you enjoy them? Who's not doing recovery? Because I can't tell if this means like you should just take a day off or what. I mean, last weekend's AMA up in my Instagram stories, somebody was like,
Is it okay to get on the bike and just go really, really easy? Because you want to get on the bike, but you're too tired to ride, ride, or something like that. And I was like, yeah, just keep it easy. Get back feeling strong. And by the way, this is called a recovery ride. Yeah. The best ride. Well, one of the best rides. Yeah, and this is one of the times where you and Cooper, you go ride with the dogs. A lot of the time, I'm like,
Oh, shoot, we're low on whatever. Let's ride to Gateway Market and get a bag of coffee or a snack. It's like a cute little spin downtown. Yeah, you get to hang out together. It's a good couple's time, too. It's a really good couple's time. It far beats riding with a significant other that's like...
You have to do my endurance. It's not useful for my training. I have to stay in this specific zone. I'm just going to drop you. You know, none of that. You just go out and spin. Yeah, and that's not fun for anybody either. I actually had someone tell me, I'm not even in a zone. And I was like, what? Zone zero, zone NA, zone not applicable.
Literally zero watts? Is that what this means? Just being alive is like 50 watts. Come on. That's, yeah. Whatever. Okay. Let's see. Last one is, a lot of people take their threshold and below workouts to literally making rides lame. I actually kind of just touched on this one.
workouts under threshold? Like FTP workouts, endurance workouts, probably a lot of endurance workouts, or like, because I could actually interpret this in a couple ways, where like people, I could see this as people just take their FTP too seriously. And it's like, if you like miss an FTP workout, oh no, I ruined my season.
I made a meme about that a long time ago, where it was like the dominoes thing, where like the guy is like, like ruined season is the big domino up top, and like the bottom domino was like, you missed a workout, you got a cold, like you get beaten by a junior, like any number of these things that we've all had happen to us. I was thinking more of like when someone's like, I have to be like,
Really stuck on this one specific number for this entire ride. Otherwise, it's just like ruined. Oh, here's one. Somebody was dating a guy who, he would be like, I've got to go do my endurance rides. They have to be exactly 200 watts and I cannot stop pedaling. I cannot stop for you to put on a jacket. If you stop.
It's like doing two different rides. It's not like doing one long ride. The stimulus is very different. And it's like, I think that is another way to take one of these workouts way too seriously. Definitely a ride ruiner for sure. Like if you can't stop for a coffee or to take off your jacket, come on, like two seconds of stopping, your body's not like, wait a minute, this isn't endurance riding.
We're going to start over. And she was like, I was hanging on his wheels so hard. It sounded like race days where you're too focused on keeping up and you forget to eat and drink. That's what it sounded like. Yeah. Yeah, horrible. All right. Well, that's a bunch of controversial training takes. My controversial training take, if whatever you...
If whatever like fancy stuff you think is going on under the hood, if you think training that will make you better, you had better see that you got better. Like if you don't see real world improvements, then you didn't do anything. I don't care if your lactate clearance got better. Yeah, I had people like kind of like controversial. I think I re-shared that meme that you had posted. Which one was that? There's been so many. There's a meme about like
Sorry, that one meme. There's like 80 of them, 80,000 maybe. But it was the one on like women can't train, what it's like talking, telling people that women can't train like 20 hours a week or more or something like that, or high volume weeks. And it was like that person like talking to a brick wall. But I had like gotten people like message me like, well, actually.
Women Can't Train As Much As Men Like It's Just The Way That It Is Blah Blah Blah And I'm Just Like I Started Like Doing More Hours This Year And I Had Like The Best Year That I've Had So I Just I Don't Know It Just Seems Like It Worked Out Okay Yeah I Think So Too And Actually Personally I Think Regardless Of Gender I Think A Lot Of People Who Find That They Are Unable To Train More Than Like
15 hours a week, they're doing all their rides too hard, or their endurance rides too hard. Because I consulted with a guy many years ago, and then he became a client for a little bit, where he had done a bunch of lactate testing. And he was like, all right, well, my LT1 is at like two millimole lactate, which is not how it's done. That's a statistical convenience to assess something like in a ramp test or whatever.
Okay, one millimole, right, we got a rise in lactate. That's like, that's all it's there for. It's not physiologically significant, really. And for him, it was way too hard. So for him, it was like, like 270 watts or something like that on his like 380 watt FTP. And he would like go do his endurance rides at this pace. And he was like, yeah, I overtrained when I ride more than 17 hours a week. And the first thing I did, I was like, take your power meter and put it in your pocket and ride easy.
I don't care how easy, just go ride easy. And like, this is your training for the first week. And he got used to it. And then he was like doing like 20 hour weeks for a bit. And he was like, this is actually okay. And I was like, yeah, see, you were just riding too hard. He goes, well, what about my lactate? And I'm like, what about it? Yeah. Yeah, I think that's kind of the biggest problem is people are like, oh, well, I can't do like 20 hour weeks on top of like.
Five hard interval sessions? Like, how is this possible? Like, you know, if you cut out some of the unnecessary intensity, then maybe, or just like the hard endurance rides. Like, I know some people are like, well, I don't do over five hours. And it's like, can you at that pace that you're trying to do? All right. Thanks, everybody, for listening. And thank you, of course, to Megan for coming on to the podcast. And if you are wanting to work with Megan after hearing her here,
Please reach out, empiricalcyclingatgmail.com, and we will set you up with Megan for coaching. She's got some open roster slots. It's been filling up pretty quick, and she has a very quick study with coaching. She's doing a great job, as I know she would.
If you want to reach out, please, yeah, don't hesitate. And if you're just curious, please don't hesitate. And if you'd like to work with any of our other coaches, we are always taking on clients. We're always trying to find the right fit for people, even if somebody like me or somebody like Megan or Rory or, you know, Corey or, well, just go down the whole list. Even if we are not the right fit, we almost always have somebody who's, like, perfect for a client. And, yeah, just reach out. Let us know a bit about yourself.
We'll be happy to kind of set you up with the right person for a conversation before you get started. So if you want to consult with us too, please reach out again and we can look at your season, we can answer all of your questions, we can give personalized training recommendations on everything. We can talk about strength training, we can talk about off-season or periodization. The world is your oyster, so please don't hesitate. Thanks everybody for all of the inquiries so far.
Yeah, over on Instagram at Empirical Cycling if you'd like to ask a question on the Weekend AMAs or for our podcast guests or whatever podcast we're doing for topics in the future. So yeah, with all that, thanks everybody for all the support over the years and we really appreciate it and we look forward to hopefully hearing from you soon. And so just reach out even if you just want to say hi and say thanks or if you want to tell us what we said with some bullshit. So that's totally fine too. All right, thanks everybody again. Bye.