Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Coley Moore, joined as always by my co-host, Kyle Helson. Thank you, everybody, for listening as always, of course. And I'm asking you to please subscribe to the podcast, but you know all that. But of course, really share the podcast. It really is the best thing that you can do if you want to support the podcast. Also, a five-star iTunes rating and a nice review, although some of the bad ones are...
They're kind of funny. And also remember that we're ad-free, so if you want to donate to the show, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We're going to have these show notes up on the website. Not that there's going to be a lot.
I'll probably put up what we're talking about here in the description. You'll see that in your podcast app. So if you have any coaching or consultation inquiries, you can shoot an email to empiricalcycling at gmail.com. And by the way, those of you who have sent in something on the website for the contact sheet in the website, a bunch of those, almost all of them in the last month have gone to my spam box and I apologize for that. I have dug them out and I have responded to the ones that I've gotten. So I'm sorry about that.
MedicalCycling at gmail.com. Consultes, we're always doing those, and we are taking on athletes as well. So we have nice rates for professional athletes and students and people in extenuating circumstances, of course. We want to give everybody good training, regardless of what you can afford. So that's my pitch there. So also up on Instagram, that's where I got all of our myths today.
at Empirical Cycling and, of course, doing the weekend AMAs up in the Instagram stories. That was a lot of fun this weekend. Thanks, everybody, for that. So give me a follow there. And, of course, we have our water bottle collab. Is a discount code a collab, Kyle? I'm curious. I don't know how these things work. I don't know. All right. Well, it depends. 10% off your order. You know, good dudes over there. They do cool designs. I have a couple other things. I like them a lot. All right.
Mythbusters. Not actual Mythbusters because that show is way too cool for me to be on. But we are going to be talking about fitness myths. And I'm kind of excited about this one because I've asked up on the Instagram twice for fitness myths for people to send in. And we got some really good ones. So two of these that I've put up for this episode are going to be the most requested ones that we've gotten. Seriously, we got like 10, 20 people.
on the first one of big gear work and strength training. Does that surprise you, Kyle, or do you think that this is one of the more common ones? I think it's pretty common. I think especially because it's in the popular zeitgeist or something almost at this point, right? Like, oh, big gear work. I think a lot of people, if you get into cycling, you maybe don't want to...
also get a gym membership or something like that and so you look for a way around it and it's unfortunate though because even I think even in Friel's book he mentions that like it's not a substitute it's a thing but it's not a substitute like you just do do some quick math and you can see that that's the case but no I think it still persists like people talk about oh you know I can even remember like an old GCN video where they talk about
doing standing starts type thing on your road bike at stoplights and stuff like that as a good version of strength training on the bike or what have you. Yeah. I remember reading an article on it a long, long, long time ago, right when I was starting to digest training stuff, and it was Brad Wiggins who was either winning the tour or he had just gotten the podium at the Vuelta. It was something like that.
And somebody was like, yeah, the people interviewing him were like, yeah, today he was up on the mountains in Tenerife and he was doing, he was climbing at like 50 RPM, which is strength training for cyclists. And I didn't know anything at the time. I was like, oh, that's cool. And you know, you want to ride your bike, but you don't want to learn to squat because it's hard and it takes a little bit of time, at least not a ton, not like a clean or something like that, but some time and you can hurt yourself.
Okay, cool. 50 RPM on the bike. That sounds awesome. So is it really a substitute for strength training? This is something that we've actually never talked about on the podcast before, which is how does strength training work? And one of these days I do want to do a short series on it because otherwise these series are taking over a year now. But I think it's...
It's going to be interesting to discuss because there are a bunch of things with actual strength training that we know affects the, we don't know everything about strength adaptations, but we know a lot. Like we know about as much about strength training adaptations as we do about endurance training adaptations. And of course, there's a lot of gray area there. There's a lot of fog of war. If we want to consider ourselves at war with our molecular biology.
Yeah, but I think one of the first things to do is like, why don't we start with what makes us strong? And we don't have any notes for this. So this may be a little meandery, so I apologize. We just have our myths up in front of us. So I think one of the biggest things to think about, people think about with strength is muscle tension, like time under tension, right? Like, Kyle, what do we know about tension?
and Muscles that causes strength adaptations. It seems like more tension is good generally. I mean, I think that some of the overlap gets a little confusing because when you look into a lot of the strength training research, some of it is very clearly for hypertrophy and others yet are for, you know, maximal force production. And so the studies kind of exist in those two different things.
You can kind of think of those like the bodybuilding versus powerlifting camps or whatever you want. But generally, more tension is good. That's why you see like, you know, I don't know, those old fun videos of Ronnie Coleman trying to squat 800 solid-ass pounds for like a set of five or whatever. Yes. And so...
For there, people think like, oh, muscle tension, or maybe they've heard like time under tension. That's why maybe they think bodybuilders do higher reps, you know, sets of 10, 20, stuff like that. And so that they just think, oh, we're getting in all this integrated tension. Yeah. Well, there's two things that we can think about directly as a consequence of that. Okay. So if we want to get stronger, all we need to do is create tension on the muscles, right? So here's the most basic version is an isometric, like just sit there, like flex your bicep.
Just go ahead, flex your biceps. Everybody listening, I know you're cyclists and they're not really there, but flex your biceps and look at them. All right, now flex them as hard as you can and now you've got a lot of tension on the muscles, as much as you can possibly muster, right? And so if you just sit there and if you want to get bigger quads, why don't you sit there and just isometrically, without moving your leg, just flex your quads as hard as you can and now you're going to grow muscle, right?
Right? Yeah, why don't bodybuilders, why do they actually touch barbells at all? Why don't they just like pose out all the time and get bigger that way? Right, yeah. Yeah, I think, I mean, you could imagine a very, very untrained person. I'm sure there's a study somewhere on isometrics and hypertrophy. Well, hypertrophy is a funny one because it's basically anything that increases the muscle size.
And they do that by either looking at the muscle fibers under a microscope or they just put a measuring tape around your leg or your arm or whatever they're measuring. That's it. Or they'll do a cross-section. Like maybe they'll do like an ultrasound cross-section or something like that. But they're not going to be...
It's not going to be exact on what was the mechanism because a lot of the time it can just be like fluid retention because you're building glycogen stores because with hypertrophy, metabolic load is as big of a factor it seems in muscle growth, just directly muscle growth like bodybuilder stuff, as mechanical tension. Okay, so here's another thing. Now I know that I need actual weight. I need to actually move the muscle.
to generate tension to make it strong, right? So now what am I going to do? I'm going to, of course, take a weight. And now if I want to increase time under tension, I'm going to, like, let's say I'm squatting. I'm going to squat very slowly. Let's say it takes me 10 seconds. All right, let's make something reasonable. Let's say it takes me five seconds to get to the bottom of a squat and then another five seconds to get up. Even though I could do it in about one, why don't I do 10?
Is this a good mechanism for gaining strength? I would say generally no and this is probably because of other reasons like if you are descending so slowly you're probably going to systemically fatigue or it's going to be more cardiovascularly taxing and so then you're
Letting other systems limit your ability to actually make force. And if you want to get stronger, just like if you want to get a higher FTP, you spend more time working at or near your FTP. If you want to produce more force, you want to spend more time actually producing high amounts of force relative to the maximum amount of force you can make. Yeah. And there's one extra component here.
that I think matters. Because with time under tension, I think that's sort of like measuring kilojoules on the bike. It doesn't tell you a lot. It gives you a picture of something, but it doesn't tell you a lot. If I tell you, Kyle, I burned 1,000 kilojoules on the bike today, you're going to be like, was that an FTP effort? Was that a sweet spot? Were you doing an endurance ride? Was that sprints? You have no context whatsoever. It's almost like TSS. Time under tension is the same.
Because I can spend 20 seconds under tension and you don't know if I did one rep or if I did 20 reps. And so time under tension is an interesting one, but it's not really what matters here. What matters with actually gaining strength, and by strength, we need to define this too, the ability to produce force.
And if we're going to measure real strength, of course, we have to measure maximal force production. And so if we want to build our force production, of course, once we've gotten the neural stuff out of the way, like you learn to do the movement, you can get stronger that way. But with strength training, you need large mechanical load, under tension, and under stretch.
that is one of the most underappreciated things in strength training because of course, if you like, if you look at doing a quarter squat, I think we talked about this once in one of the strength training, uh, 10 minute tips we did a couple months ago. Uh, like if you do a quarter squat with like, you know, you and I could probably do it with like five, 600 pounds or something like that. Um, that's not very effective.
It's a lot of mechanical tension on your muscles, believe me. It's a lot. But when you look at how the muscles sense actual tension, it's related to things called costomers. And the costomers, they have to have mechanical tension, and then you have to stretch them. And the costomers go, whoa, we cannot take this. We need to fix this. We need to be able to better adapt to this load and make it more submaximal. And so that's kind of what's happening in the muscles.
So that's why I think we previously recommended doing deep squats with less weight rather than less deep squats with more weight, right? Right, yeah. And so now, let's look at what's happening on a bike. So on the bike, in a pedal stroke, let's just start with the stretch of the muscles first. When we start to apply force at the top of the pedal stroke, our quads are long.
Right? They're long, but they're not under tension. And so if we think about the hip, hip is flexed up, knee is flexed inward, and now we have nice long quads. And now we start producing tension. This is the opposite of what happens in a squat, where we start with shorter muscles, and then we elongate them under load. So already, it doesn't look good for strength training on the bike. Right? Right. Yeah, I think it, you know, it's maybe comparable. People think, oh, well,
I guess there's no eccentric component to pedaling, but isn't the concentric portion the time that you're actually pushing and doing the work? Kind of, but a lot of research does actually show that the eccentric portion of lifts is actually quite important and shouldn't necessarily just be ignored only because pedaling is only a concentric.
Yeah, and I've done that concentric only experiment too, and it works for a little bit. It really does. Like I did just deadlifts for a while, and I got up to deadlifting some serious weight, but I plateaued at some point because I needed to either start, I needed to go deeper, I needed to do something else in addition to just deadlifting. Although I'm sure somebody's going to say, if you just deadlift, you can get stronger, I've done it. Okay, maybe.
Didn't happen for me, but that's not the point besides my crappy anecdote. The point is that, yeah, the mechanical stretch is we don't get in cycling as well. Like we don't apply tension and then lengthen the muscles. We apply tension and we shorten the muscles because they are concentric contractions. That's it. That's all we're doing. And so not only that, but let's look at the kinetic chain, for instance.
Here's a kinetic chain thing. It's like a regular back squat versus, let's say, a belt squat. What's the difference mechanically in what you're doing between the two, Kyle? Well, just so people, in case they're not familiar, a belt squat machine is a machine where you wear a...
that looks like a dip belt or almost like a lifting belt, but it sits on your hips, kind of like if you were backpacking or something, and then the load gets placed on the inside between your legs and it pulls down. So you're mostly, hopefully, loading the weight on your hips and not in some vital organ in your abdomen or something like that. Yeah, it's like a fanny pack or a hip pack, except it's like a couple hundred pounds. Right. And then you can squat down. And for that...
For some people, they are able to sit up more upright than they are if they're doing like a back squat with a barbell. And that's because of limb proportions and flexibility and things like that. But there you're not loading through your spine, which for some people is going to be a much needed relief.
that whole concentric, eccentric phase and it's not just like a trap bar deadlift. Yeah. And the point is that you're removing everything from pretty much your lumbar spine up because it also removes the balance component too. And so it's shortening the kinetic chain. So the weight is like just above your hips.
And that's it. It's between your hips and your feet. On a squat, you've got a bunch more muscles and a bunch more joints in your spine between your shoulders and your feet.
And so those two things mean that you can really, really go ham on the weight on belt squats. Like I've done this with leg press. It's the same idea. And I have gone way too deep on the leg press because suddenly your quads are just free to run amok and they're not used to that level of work intention. And I have screwed myself up for like a couple of weeks overdoing it on the, just by like going leg press, like, ah, we sets of sets of 10, 15, 20.
and then I'm like all twitchy for a couple of days afterwards. Not good. Don't do that. And so when we get onto the bike, we have even more components in the kinetic chain between our hands and our feet, whether we're standing or sitting. And there's a balance component and, you know, it's, you know, all concentric and all that kind of stuff.
The difference between proper strength training and just riding on a big gear on the bike is that when we like, let's say you're doing a standing start, right? Because this should be the closest we can get, the most tension we can make on the quads, right? So when we do a standing start on the bike, if we stand up, we need to keep every joint between our hands and our feet as tight as possible.
Otherwise, it's going to flex a little bit and you lose power. But all the other stuff that we mentioned about strength training, like your quads are starting long and they're getting shorter and all that kind of stuff, this means that we're not going to achieve the mechanical tension on the muscles that we need in order to actually create enough tension to actually get strong. So, of course, there is something to this myth, isn't there?
Yeah, yeah, yeah I think some of that is that like the example you just gave in a standing start you need if you're a track sprinter like the people who mostly are concerned about say doing standing starts well they are doing lifting in the gym a lot of it and then they are also trying to turn that strength into strength on the bike with sport specific movements like a standing start and so
it's not like you should never do them it's not like there's no there's no use for that and then likewise it's not like if you're a mountain biker or a cyclocross rider right there's a lot of times where you are in like a bigger gear lower cadence like or you know maybe not optimal gear and you do have to produce high torque so it's not as if bigger gear efforts are completely useless it's just that they they don't necessarily replace or they don't replace at all strength training from the gym and so
It's not bad, it's just not great. Yeah, and it's like if you took a powerlifter and you just put them on a bike and you said go do standing starts, they're going to look horrible. I've coached people's first standing starts on the track and most people don't have it good when they start and I didn't either.
and it's okay. But it requires practice because it's a motor learning thing that you need to practice. But this gets to something that I glossed over before, which is that when you actually do strength training, the motor pattern is a very large part of the strength. You need to be familiar with all the little balance stuff that's going on. You need to be familiar with all the muscles you need to tension and when. And if you spend mental energy on that stuff, you don't have that same mental energy, literally.
You rob yourself of neural drive that turns on those muscles. And whether that's purposeful, because your brain subconsciously is like, whoa, whoa, whoa, we can't really push that hard yet. Is it because half your brain horsepower is going to the other stuff? Or is it just like a limiter? Your brain's like, we could do this, but we won't. And so you have to practice it. It's sort of like getting good at a squat.
Three weeks, I really start getting to the groove. All right, I've got my squat. I can really feel this. I'm good at this now. But I think it's worth also thinking about when we don't do standing starts. So like if you're just going to ride at like sweet spot at like 50 RPM, right? It's also not strength training because it's a different limiter with strength training.
When you are doing heavy squats, the thing that keeps you from doing that next squat, if you're going to like max out or something like that or get close, the mechanisms of fatigue are also different. They're actually much more similar to, my understanding anyway, is that they're much more similar to what you're doing with like an anaerobic effort, like a 30 second or one minute all out kind of thing. Right. Yeah. And I think that's a good point.
The example, okay, even if you are doing a big gear effort, how many pedal revs do you take? Probably more than 10, unless you're Robert Farsman pulling that truck in that one video where he's trying to track your pole, like a semi on his bike or whatever. But you're certainly doing more than 10, and 10 is a lot in a strength training set rep scheme. And so if you're doing more than 10,
then you're probably pretty far away from that regime where you're producing sufficiently high force. Yeah, although it's funny because bodybuilders usually do sets of 10 as their smallest sets, but they'll do it with squats and heavy bench press and things like that, like the heavier movements, then they go higher and higher reps. So there's definitely mechanical tension. Kyle, I think you told me a long time ago, when you were doing strength training in...
College, I think you were mostly doing like sets of 10 to get stronger and it was working, right? Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that was always like a college swimmer and it was working and that was, but I think for a lot of people, even like college swimmers, a lot of them had never done any, you know, formal intense strength training before. And so as a, you know, as a coach who has to try to figure out a
program for 30 people at once. You maybe don't trust them to do, I don't know, heavy triples and stuff like that. Especially because your lifting is not going to be the primary goal, right? It's still going to be the swimming. And a lot of times you're doing doubles and things like that. So yeah, we do lots of sets of eight to 10 where it is more of a traditional bodybuilding like hypertrophy.
style set rep scheme. Yeah. All right. So, yeah. So that's why big gear work is not a good substitute for strength training. Like we don't have the proper mechanical tension and stretch. And also, you know, despite how sports specific it is, it just mechanically does not bring you to that level of
Tension where like your body's like, oh, yeah, we have to fix this. We need to adapt. It doesn't do that. Okay, so. Right. Yeah. Oh, sorry. Go ahead. Oh, no. I was just going to say like this past weekend, I did a standing 500.
at the track. And even that was on a- On the world's largest gear. On a gear that's pretty big, at least relative to a lot of the gears that you'd ride on a road bike. All right. How big? All right. Hold on. People are going to love this, especially the people who are still on 5311 as their biggest gear. So what was the gear size? I was on 6215, which is-
which for old people who know like the gear interest it's like 112 which is whatever that's like 53 what is that like 53 13 12 ish I think 12 is 121 so it's like 53 like 53 13 and you start from a dead stop and you get up to anyway but you know if you think about it that's a pretty big year and that's probably closest to the biggest gear that you've got on a regular road bike like
I did way more than 10 pedal revs. I had to do 10 pedal revs the first half a lap or whatever. You're way far away from that regime. Although the gears in track sprinting have gotten bigger and bigger and bigger and you do see people still do even big over-geared efforts. But they're still not.
I'll substitute for strength training even though now they sell like nine tooth cogs they have special hubs with like a nine tooth cog like machined into it so you can put like a 64 to 70 tooth chain ring in the front like a nine in the back or something ridiculous where you know like even in like over 400 meters right the number of pedal strokes you would you'd be doing is like countable on like like visibly as you watch because they're going so slowly but
it's still not quite the same yeah yeah I remember 2019 Ed Dawkins did a flying 200 on like 135 when people were shouting at him you know we're not gear limited yeah he would he was coming to T-Town and doing like I remember talking he did a fly I think he did the flying 500 or flying lap record at T-Town on a 63 13 oh my god it's like yeah I got yeah big years anyway um all right so
our second myth by the way we got so many myths we're gonna have to like make this a series so check me out on Instagram empirical cycling I will be periodically asking for myths we have we have a list of like Kyle how many is this like 30 it's a lot yeah we got a lot so this is this is going to be I think people are gonna like this the series I hope anyway if you do let me know if you don't also let me know and
Yeah, so we're going to be able to do this for quite a while. So the next most requested thing here, or the next biggest myth that people have mentioned so far, is burning more fat helps you adapt to burning more fat. And this would be like fasted rides, keto, etc, etc, etc.
I think we kind of covered this in a previous podcast. It was Fat Max Fallacies, I think. Is that Wattstock 35 or 6? That one, we really, well, we kind of went into the adaptation mechanisms, stuff like that. But basically what we did was we showed that, we kind of showed how the fuel selection happens.
Basically what there is is something called CPT1 and CPT complex, carnitine palmitoyltransferase. And this lives on the mitochondrial membrane, and it's responsible for taking long-chain fatty acids from the cell, main cell compartment, the cytosol, and moving it into the mitochondria for a breakdown in the beta-oxidation.
to create acetyl-CoA. Acetyl-CoA goes into the Krebs cycle, and the whole time we're generating reducing equivalents, NADH and FADH2, which of course feed electrons into the electron transport chain, and that creates a proton gradient, which generates ATP. Everybody knows all this. Okay, so what... You're like your own little speed-up edit machine, yeah. I know. And of course, what this means is,
How it gets limited is there is such a high throughput, there's such a high flux that at some point the transport of fatty acids into the mitochondria is not sufficient to keep up. And so we have this other pathway, the aerobic breakdown of carbohydrates. Well, technically it's anaerobic for both fat and carbohydrates.
until well after it's broken down. That's not the point. The point is that the high throughput from the other pathway, because of either high demand in the cell, like if you do an anaerobic effort and you create a lot of lactate, the cell's like, oh, we got to start getting through some of this lactate. And so the lactate coming into the mitochondria, actually what happens is the carnitine will buffer the
the acetyl groups. And this means it takes them up, so it frees up the CoA, so CoA can actually go back and do its job, you know, oxidizing lactate and putting it into the electron transport chain. Not electron transport chain, my bad. The Krebs cycle, sorry, or the tricarbate-acid cycle, there's a million names. And so what basically happens is
The mechanism of deciding what to bring into the mitochondria is mostly related to demand rate and transport rate. That's why transport is such a big thing in burning fatty acids, right? Because I think I've mentioned this on the podcast before, if you have a lot more mitochondrial mass, that means you have a lot more transport mechanism for both lactate and fat.
They're really the same thing to the mitochondria, except one is presented to it a little faster and one gets imported a little slower. That's really the big difference. And so if we can import, if we can bring more fats into the mitochondria, we can burn them more, which is why sometimes we can see people at threshold burning very high percentages of fatty acids. And if we actually look at what is going on in the cell, it's actually a little higher than even that because the...
And short-chain fatty acids like octanoate, they can actually just diffuse right in. They don't need to be transported. And so when we start to think about being able to burn more fat, okay, so what happens if we start to...
Eat a lot of fat or what happens if we don't eat before a ride? What happens if we don't have any carbohydrates? Yeah. Okay. So what happens if we skip the donuts or if we skip the flour part of the donuts and we go right to the butter? What happens if we do that? Basically, like your body is going to go, oh, we have now gotten a lot of this certain type of fuel. Cool. So we are going to upregulate.
the transport mechanisms for this type of fuel. But the downside is that you downregulate everything that you need to have a lot of carbohydrate use. And so in bike racing, this seems like it might, your logical conclusion would be, okay, why don't we just do some fasted rides or go keto for a couple of weeks and then carb load, and then we're going to have the best of both worlds. But in our keto episode,
We looked at the Louise Burke studies on race walkers who use a lot of carbohydrates and they found absolutely no difference in performance. So, yeah, so I think this is, this is like for like just in terms of like a really well done set of experiments, you know, this is the best like practical real world example that we have, right?
Yeah, I think one of the things, and this isn't exactly true, but the idea that burning more fat helps you adapt to burn more fat, like if you fasted or on keto or whatever, you're burning more fat because that's all you got. Your body's going to use what you have, and so it's like the thing that assumes the question, like, oh, well, if you aren't eating carbs, well, then your body has three things it can burn for.
for fuel. And if you're lacking one of them, it's going to go to the next one. Yeah. Yeah. It's sort of like, you know, in order to get good at the thing, you have to do the thing. Like on its face, this would seem to be a good axiom to live and train by, right? If you want to get good at lifting heavy weights, like if you want to get good at squatting heavy weights, you squat heavy weights. It's pretty simple. It's like it's a caveman could do it. And they probably did. Who knows?
But when it comes to what actually drives the adaptation, this is where things start to break down. Sometimes it works, for sure. Sometimes this kind of stuff works. But as soon as we start trying to work our way around something that we know works, and we start to try to shortcut it or hack it,
you know then we start to sometimes we find something that's true we really do but we haven't found anything here because I think one of the things to think about that's super super important with this is that the things that drive actual aerobic adaptation like because we're looking for performance right we're looking for being able to do a road race better we're looking
for being able to do a criterion better. We're looking to have better fatigue resistance. The number one thing that improves all of this stuff is just writing. And when we do diet manipulation stuff, I've talked about this on other podcasts briefly. When we do diet manipulation stuff, we are still aiming at...
is stressing the same thing that just a lot of riding will do, which is why I've said that if you want to do any of these kinds of manipulations, it's really going to be for a small group of people who can do it somewhat intermittently and who don't have a lot of time to ride. If you have 20, 30 hours a week to ride, do that. You're not going to shortcut anything. And if you are going to do...
attempt one of these shortcuts, which we will talk about on the podcast eventually. I don't want to do it yet. But you're going to find that it's not going to unlock a huge amount of potential for you. You're going to find that it helped a little bit, kind of like riding Moore would, but then it's going to stop and that's it. And it's super stressful to do. Yeah. I think one thing to keep in mind, you can't actually hack your...
It's not a computer program. A lot of these things get sold as hacks. And a hack in a program is taking advantage of some vulnerability that is built in where it was an oversight or it's a mistake or it's just some sort of loophole that people find. And there aren't that. These aren't those. Yeah. Well, let's talk about what the actual hack mechanism is that we actually know can kind of work.
is low glycogen stores. It's not the fact that you've got a lot of fat. Okay, here's the thing actually. I did a lab when I was in school. It was one of the early, early, early labs and it was you transfect a plasmid into bacteria and you grow the bacteria up and anything that has successfully gotten it, like we use the sugar called arabinose. And so what happens is the arabinose goes in and there are
Lots of different blah, blah, blahs. And it basically increases the expression of like arabinose transporter. It increases, I think that was it. But regardless, it increased the expression of green fluorescent protein, right? And so- Nice. Yeah. And so this is one of the things that happens when we have a lot of fats or we have a lot of sugars or something like that. Your body goes, oh, wow, we have a lot of this. We need to increase the ability to transport this because this is what's around right now. It does not-
does not improve the number of mitochondria you have from training. It does not improve your ability to use fats when you have a normal, whole, balanced diet. What does is training. And so the mechanism that we know of so far, because I'm sure there's a couple others that we don't know about, the fog of war with our molecular biology, is when we have low glycogen stores, this is going to
Increased activation of things like AMPK and I think P38 and Sertutins, if I remember Sert1. I could be misquoting some of these molecular things, but basically it all points to increased expression of the, or increased, you know, pointing at the master regulator switch, you know, PGC1 alpha. And so this is how it works. Like in theory, and you can, when people start to
add and subtract. It's like, no, it just, you, the low glycogen and contraction, like that would be the stimulus. And it's the same as just riding more. It really is in terms of the expression, the genes, like what's going on molecularly. And so it doesn't say if you have more fat and you burn more fat, you get good at burning.
If you have more fat, yeah, you get good at burning more fat. It doesn't change the performance. It doesn't increase your VO2 max. It doesn't increase your threshold. It doesn't increase your efficiency. It really doesn't help just burning more fats by manipulating your diet or riding fasted. Don't do that ever. Like an hour, easy spin. Okay, sure. But after that, please eat something. That's one of the reasons I don't want to talk about that on this podcast because
I don't want people to go out and do this wrong. So I got to think about the right approach for that. Um, and so, and also I want everybody to know that it's probably not going to be a big saving grace. It's not going to like significantly change your performance. It's going, you're still going to be the same rider. You might have a little longer like TTE and that would be about it most likely. So, um, yeah. Um, yeah, Kyle, I've, I'm sorry. I've been steamrolling over you for a couple of minutes.
Oh, no, I think that's right. I mean, like, put it another way, if you were looking at it the other way, it'd be like, oh, why doesn't sitting on the couch on a bunch of stimulants with a really high heart rate get me aerobically fitter? Like, oh, you're missing all these other things. Like, just manipulating your diet is only playing with one small fraction of all the things that go into making you more aerobically fit. Yeah.
Yeah, I guess you could say like, oh, what if I manipulate my diet and do a bunch of... You know what? You are going to have a very, very, very bad time. And we did not tell you to do that. But this kind of goes into what I think is going to be our last myth for this episode, which is that you should always...
Ride in your little ring for bass or you should always do long slow distance basically like there's a couple things that you know that people put into this one but basically it's like you should always really ride easy on your bass training um like and this I think we know like what there's a lot of ways to come at this because in a way yes but also in a way no um because I think that there's a lot more context like
you know, cause it depends. So like, you know, so here's the myth. This is why it's wrong, but why does it depend? Everything is, it depends. So what does this one depend on for you, Kyle? Well, one of it is obviously if you are sufficiently fit and that like quote unquote staying in your little ring, like if that doesn't actually, isn't hard enough for you to do even for your endurance based rides, well then that's a dumb rule, right? Like if you, if you have a, uh,
and 350 watt FTP depending on where you live like staying in your little ring may never get you like out of nose breathing mode you know so like that's that's just like silly and the other thing is it also it it's on that list of things from I don't know the stupid like rules or whatever and a lot of that just assumes that because that's what pros did and pros had 20-30 hours a week to train that that's what you should do too that's another myth I guess rolled into there but yeah
It also makes a lot of assumptions about the time you have to train, your training history, right? Like if you're a professional cyclist, you've got 20 years of training history in you, you know? And if you're a weekend warrior, you've got less than that, presumably. So it maybe does work for some people, the you should only ride in the little ring thing, but it also...
presumably does not work for an equal number of people. Yeah, like if you're living in, I don't know, because it's Eddie Merck, so let's say Belgium, right? So if you're living in Belgium, are you living on the plains? Are you living in the Ardennes? Like where is this place that you're like in the little ring all year? So I think it just really stresses that you need to go super easy. And here's the thing is like, do you really need to go super, super easy? Do you really need to like...
be doing like an eight-hour recovery ride or its equivalent. I would say no. And I think, you know, one of the other things when you look at people who are time crunched is that they, you know, you max out. I think we did this, we talked about this in the time crunch training episode, the 300,000 listens episode, where if you, God, what am I trying? I forgot where I was going with this. Kyle, you remember it. Help me out.
if you don't have all the time you need to get in the volume of work somehow and unless you've got a time turner or something you have to increase the intensity a little bit and like we said it works to a certain extent it's not a perfect replacement but increasing the intensity a little bit so you at least get that extra metabolic stress in a little bit of the extra metabolic stress in that you miss by not being able to do a 5 hour long ride or something like that
Yeah, like if you've got 12 hours and you're like, all right, I'm going to just do endurance riding for every hour I have this week and maybe like one day off. So now you've got like, let's say you've got an hour and a half, a couple days a week, and you've got two, three hours on the weekends. Suddenly you're at like 10 or 12 hours, right? And so is riding at 12 hours a week at endurance pace for like longer than probably two or three weeks going to do much?
Probably not. And so, yeah, that's when you would go, oh, great, I got to start doing something now because otherwise, like, I'm just going to be spinning my gears forever. And, you know, I think we joked about this way, way in an early episode, like, what is base? You know, where I was, I think I joked, I think it definitely rubbed some people the wrong way because I don't, I haven't listened to that episode since pretty much since we recorded it.
But it's come back to me in many ways. Oh my God, Kyle, so much stuff comes back to me from these podcasts that is like, I didn't say that, and I know I didn't. This may have, I may have said this, that riding easy for a couple months is good to recover from the season that you just had, right? So if you're a professional cyclist and your season ends in like late September, early October, something like that, and you've got a classic starting in February or March,
and what if we're doing cyclocross, right? And so suddenly you've got like two or three months to recover and like kind of get your legs back under you. Yeah, I could see, you know, just doing easy ring spinning at like 100 watts on your 400 watt FTP. I could see that being very enjoyable for like a month or two or three until your legs come back to you from the fatigue of the season, you know?
Yeah, I remember someone made a comment how like, oh, like bass training isn't just because it's easy and you're like, you didn't say you did easy bass or like low intensity bass training just because it's easy. You said one benefit of it is this. And I think that, yeah, I think within that people forget that you have to progressively overload, you have to overreach somehow and if you're just...
Maxed out 12 hours at 190 watts in your little ring. What are you going to do? Honestly, if you can comfortably do 25 or 30 hours like that, now you've got some bass training. That's serious stuff. That's going to be very helpful. Actually, what's funny is this reminds me of this connection that I wanted to make between the last myth and this one is that
When you do all of these low-intensity rides, you are going to be expected to be burning mostly fat. It's not 100% fat. It's mostly there, especially if you're riding this much. This is one of those other things that might feed into the thing of if you burn more fat, you can get better at burning fat. The body wants to burn fat.
at low intensities because it's abundant and the rate of energy demand is very slow, right? Like it's, you know, you're only, let's say it's Eddie Merckx and he's only riding at 250 watts, which is super chill for him. Like he can, he can like, yeah, sure. He can definitely burn mostly fats because he's...
done a lot of training. And so now he's going to be better at burning fats. Is that because he's burning fats? No, it's because he's riding. And we, in the, in the Fatmax Fallacies episode, I, I think off the top of my head, I briefly list some things that lead to adaptation. I can list a couple of them again, like presence of calcium. We talked about this in the why high intensity interval training may not make you faster episode. We, you know, we talked about, uh, not customers, um, leak of, uh, ranodyne receptors.
Yeah, elevated calcium levels. We talked about demand on NADH for the electronic transport chain, demand on ATP stores, presence of AMP, activation of AMPK. That would be a little higher intensity kind of thing, or could be a low glycogen kind of thing. Anyway, we could think about reactive oxygen species. Oxygen throughput leak from complex three, I think is the big culprit in that. We can think about...
Oh God, there's more, which are escaping me. But anyway, so these are the things that drive adaptation. And it's not the fact that you're burning more fat, it's that you are telling your body, we have this low intensity, long energetic demand. And these signals are what causes your body to go, we need to get better at burning fat. And it's not just the burning fat. So, you know, it's kind of like your body's doing like a bait and switch.
Any more thoughts on that one, I think? No, I think this one is a common one, but we've definitely covered a lot of aspects of it in other episodes. Sorry to assign people more reading or listening or whatever. Not reading.
Yeah, it's a common one. I'm hoping that as these things get more, talked about more, people realize that, oh, just because someone said this was some rule on some dumb website or whatever, it's a famous quote from someone, doesn't mean that it's a good idea or the only way or the one absolute truth. Yeah, yeah. Like, you're just like, oh, come on, just because, yeah, I mean.
Yeah, you want to say, like, pros give lots of, like, fun, inspirational quotes, they're entertaining or whatever, but to take them to heart as being a, you know Yeah, I mean, not everything is as simple as to lift heavy weights, you need to lift heavy weights, you know, it's, when things get more complex, I mean, I think we're lucky that that one's that simple
Yeah, for sure. You're like, it doesn't get a lot simpler than that. Yeah. And it's like when you really try to put these things together, and also if you look at molecular studies too, like if we do this thing, then we increase expression of this gene or this whatever, or increase activation of this, like that does not always translate to performance. And so we really need to think about the whole picture instead of these half
Puzzle Pieces. We really need to try to find the whole map of the territory before we really think about whether something's going to work or not, like any of these hacks. Because good training is simple. Managing the training is complex, but I find that good training is always really simple and straight to the point, and you are just stressing a thing that you know is going to XYZ. And yeah.
So, alright, so you want to do another Fitness Myths in another month or month and a half or so? Yeah, sounds good to me. Yeah, and if anybody has any more Fitness Myths, I mean, my Instagram is currently still up right now. I only put it up around noon or something like that. So it's going to be up until noon tomorrow. That would be the 14th of June. So, yeah, I'm going to be...
writing them down. I will be asking for clarifications if need be. And so you can go check that out at Empirical Cycling on the Instagram. And let's see, what else have we got? Yeah, if you are interested in becoming an Empirical Cycling athlete, it should be an email, empiricalcycling at gmail.com. We do consultations as well. And like I said, we have discount rates for, of course, professionals because we know that most professionals don't have that much money. Students, also extenuating circumstances, you let us know. We'll try to work it out.
consultations too. We will look at your training. We will answer your questions. You can consult with me and Fabiano and we will try to, you know, if you just want to talk philosophy of training, like this is my thought on training. Am I doing this right? We can do that too. So yeah, let's see. What else do we have?
Ad free, oh yeah, donations, empiricalcycling.com slash donate, and of course, we have merch, empiricalcyclingpodcast.throwis.com So, I think that's it for now, we'll see you next time. Thanks everyone.