Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore. Thank you, everybody, for listening. And if you are new here, of course, consider subscribing. And if you are a returning listener, I assume most of you are, thank you so much for coming back. We love having you. And if you want to support the podcast because you're liking it, there's a lot of ways to do that. And the easiest and best one, of course, is to share the podcast. We really appreciate the word of mouth, sharing our forums, et cetera, et cetera. That's all fantastic. Really, really appreciate that.
Ad-Free, you can always shoot us a donation, a small one, even a couple bucks goes a long way. Thank you so much. That's at empiricalcycling.com slash donate.
And if you would like to become one of our clients, we are coaches, we are always taking on athletes. And if you are self-coached and you are happy being self-coached and you just want to get some coaches' feedback, that's fine too. We can do a consultation and shoot me an email at empiricalcyclingatgmail.com for any of that. Even though it's kind of mid-race season, you know, I think a lot of people might think it's a little too late to start with a coach and that is absolutely not the case, especially if you want kind of a second set of opinions or, you know, another set of eyes.
And if you have eyes on how you're doing your training and racing and balancing all of the fatigue and all of that stuff, not never a bad time to start.
If you would like to follow me on Instagram, there's a couple things that are good over there. Number one is that you can ask a question at the weekend AMAs. I do those every single weekend. Nice, concise answers as opposed to the podcast. And if you would like to ask a question of our guests, you can do so there too. And we put those up pretty much within...
You know, one to 12 hours of recording a podcast. So keep an eye out there in the Instagram stories. That's where all of that happens. And yeah, thanks, everybody. So to get to our main thing today, I was having a chat with my buddy, Adam, who is a coach who's been on the podcast several times. He is a CTS coach, and he has coached, well, he coached
Perry Rubaiwin last year. We had him on to talk about that. And he's coached a lot of really good people. And I've got a lot of good mutual friends with him. And I just love talking to the guy. And he's one of the few coaches I know who has kind of, let's call it true humility. He's a really, really good dude. I love talking with him. And I said to him, hey, man, it's been a while since you've been on the podcast. Why don't we talk coaching mistakes?
because I think between me and him, I knew that we would kind of have a really frank and honest conversation and that's exactly what we did. So I had a great time with this and we also kind of start with like what makes a good coach. And so if you've ever wondered what a coach's conversation sounds like about what makes a good coach and coach's mistakes and how we learn from them, this is a great podcast for you. So yeah, so let's get right into it and I'll catch you on the other side.
A good coach, in my opinion, I was just having this conversation, I probably have this conversation at least once a week, yeah, but it's like, when people are trying to determine how to do training, I always tell them, I have an unbiased opinion, I can't feel the emotion that you feel, so I can detach from it, look at data, look at your goals, and decide what we need to do. Then you go do it, you get a result, we look at it, was it close to what we planned?
Was it therefore good? Did it add to where we're going in the long run? And therefore, that's a good process. That's a good high-quality coaching process. And where I think athletes just get a little tripped up. It's not wrong, but they look at the intervals and they feel it. A self-coached athlete would be like, oh, should I do VO2? No, I'll do threshold, right? Or I'll do sweet spot. Yeah, that sounds good.
Yeah, well, and I find that with self-coached people who train to vibes like that, and training to vibes is fine because it means if you're having a bad day, you can take it easy, that's fine. But at the same time, it's like if you decide what your workout is as you are rolling out, a lot of the time you completely miss.
the elements of progressive overload or kind of like just having any intention to your plan. And early on, that's fine. But later, when you start stalling out and you think, oh, I got to go back to what I did at first. It's like, well, it's not going to work anymore. Yeah. No, it's the same. I mean, like I train very rarely, like train, train. And so I'm falling victim to this. Like I'm training via vibes, right? But I'm consistent and I jump in a group ride when I want to go hard.
I hit the hills when I want to go medium, and then I chill and ride with Kristen or, you know, do a mountain bike ride with the dog when I don't. And that's as complicated as it gets for me. But my weaknesses are still my weaknesses. My sprint is shit, right? I can climb decent, but I'm a medium build. And I'm like, you know, the fast of the slow. So for a self-coached, but it's not worth it to me, right? So then you go back to...
When you're actually coaching somebody, you need to detach from that, see what's going to develop performance, and unemotionally tell the athlete, this is what we need to do, and kick them in the butt when they need it, dial them back when they need it as well, because it goes both ways. And then, as you're detaching from emotion, you then have to put...
the human being hat back on and be like, okay, now this person actually has emotion, so how do I navigate what she needs or what he needs along with, like, you're having a bad day? Yeah. That's tricky. Yeah, for sure. And actually, because I asked you to come here with, you know, a couple of coaching mistakes that we've made and how we fix them, but also, I thought- And my reply to you was like, we can do 10 plus episodes, buddy. I know.
I was like, man, I'm going to have to really narrow this one down. I spent all of 30 seconds and I had a list of like eight. And I was like, okay, yeah, this is good enough. But I thought it might be interesting to start with, what do you think makes a good coach? Because objectivity is high on my list. It's actually the first thing I put down because, you know, it's, but it's also.
Like you said, you can't always remove the emotions, but like being objective is, it has to be at least part of it, because when you do make training decisions, like I had to say to somebody just this week, who was going, who wanted to do well at the Nationals Road Race, and I was like, look, we've got X performance, we've got this, and we need you to do this, and so I think it's going to be better for us to put all our eggs in the basket of the crit instead of the road race.
and I got a, okay, cool, let's do that. And I was terrified to say that because I was like, this is on this person's list for it to like go well. And I had to say as nicely as I could, I don't think you're going to go well. And it went okay. And I was pleasantly surprised about that. Yeah. Well, as much as we're talking about like the unbiased decision-making, all this kind of stuff, I think it actually swings the other way to answer your question, what makes a good coach?
I think it actually first starts by showing the athlete that you actually care. Yes. You like give a fuck about them. Because if they, here's like the quote, no one cares how much you know until they know how much you care. I like that. Okay. And so they won't have buy-in. They won't follow you, even if you're trying to lead them, unless they know that you have good intentions in mind. Good intentions with
the ability to deliver on what you're trying to accomplish, right? And that's where I'd say the second thing is focus on performance. Once you have like this empathy, right, showing that you care, then focus on developing performance. And that can mean a number of different things, but in the world of cycling, I look at it as power durations, so how much power you're producing for how long, and the podium. Yeah. Okay.
So can we take that power development, translate it to speed, use some smarts and tactics, and win? Because it's both. And then finally, a good coach is a good communicator. So if you're doing one and two, but you're shitty at communicating the plan, it's really confusing, and therefore you're a bad coach. So clearly communicate. When I get a new athlete, one of the questions I ask is, how best do you communicate?
Do you like emails, rapid-fire text messages? Do you like phone calls? Do you like Zoom? Like, in person, getting coffee? That kind of thing. I then say, here's how I best communicate. And then we find the Venn diagram in the middle. And as long as what they sign up for falls in line with, you know, those things, then cool, let's go coaching. Right? Yeah.
And then finally it's accountability, right? Like you then have to deliver on all those three things and now you're coaching. I agree. And actually, because I get asked this all the time, what are you looking for in a coach? Because I get a lot of people like at this point monthly asking me if they can join Empirical Cycling as a coach or if I've got like volunteer opportunities, they just want to join and learn. And a lot of the time I have to tell most people no, partly because I don't know them personally.
And a lot of people will start with academic stuff, because I'm a huge nerd, obviously. And so they're like, I've got this degree. Thank you. I've got this degree. I've got this lab experience. I know this, that, and the other thing. And my first thing is like, I don't know you as a person. I want to know that you are empathetic and altruistic. And the number of examples I've seen with...
Coaches not having good empathy is staggering. Like, here's a good example. Is, you know, somebody saying like, hey, you've been really inconsistent with your training. And a bad coach would say, well, I can't be associated with you because your performance is going to be bad. I don't want your bad performances blamed on my coaching that you're not doing. That's a bad coach. A good coach would say, you're really inconsistent with your workouts. Are you okay? What's wrong? How can we help?
That's the empathetic side of things. And like you said, once you've got the objective stuff, bring that emotion, bring the human part back in. Yeah, exactly. Because if you look at data, if you look at habits, if you look at whatever, as opposed to telling something, like ask something, you observe and say, oh, do you feel like you've been consistent? Because sometimes they don't even know they're inconsistent. Yeah. So do you feel like you've been consistent? Yes, I have.
What defines consistent to you? Well, I train once a week. Okay. I love seeing you go like talk on two sides of the microphone like you're people. Yeah. Well, welcome to my life. Yeah. So, you know, I think like even, even describing what coaching is, I think to some people, because even athletes themselves, they don't really know what it is. Like they've never, like an internet coach, it's a weird thing. Try to describe that to your parents. Yes.
I've tried to describe it to people who need to understand my business at some level, and it takes like five or ten minutes to explain to them fully, because they keep having other questions. Oh, so you're a coach. Do you ride with these people? Almost never. How do you communicate? Well, a lot of it's text-based, a lot of calls, a lot of video chats, and it takes a while for them to go.
Oh, this is like a totally different thing because they think of it like a basketball coach where you're sitting courtside or you're like a swimming coach where you're sitting with a stopwatch at the side of the pool. Yeah. Yeah. So, I mean, like, again, back to empathy is just like you have to meet people where they're at. And a lot of that just comes down to general education, communication, showing them that you care. And then once they get an understanding of what coaching actually is, now let's deliver the goods. Like, let's work on actual performance because now you have an understanding of
How This Works. Final thing I say, too, is like, I tell my, this is another coachy AP-ism, is like, this is a partnership, not a dictatorship. So, what you put in is what you get out. Two-way street. Yeah, and how many coaches do we know that are dictators? Not to name too many names. 90%. Quite a few. Yeah, I'd say it's, charitably, I'd say it's definitely not the majority.
But it seems like we hear about the bad ones quite frequently. And not that we're amazing, because we're obviously going to talk about our mistakes. But I think also the last thing I think makes a good coach is knowing it's not about you. And it seems like there's a lot of folks out there who think that they're people going well as a reflection on them. And in some ways it is.
It's almost like you're a CEO of a company. And when things go badly, you have to take all the blame. And when things go right, you should give away all the credit. And coaching is very much like that, where it's like somebody does well, they did all the hard work. Something's not going well, let me do something better. Very rarely is it their fault. Yeah. Yeah, no, I completely agree with that. And I think it's...
I think it's the best posture out there because, you know, the athletes, they're the one in the trenches. They're the one that's actually doing the hard work. We're sitting back here behind the computer most of the time doing it. Now, we'll talk about maybe some, like, in-person, like, actual coaching too, but for the most part, yeah, but I would prefer that. I would prefer to be in the background sort of thing and, you know, take the shit when it's flung and, you know.
you know give the accolades to the athlete when it is because that's just how I think best operate but the tricky one too is like you building your business recognizing that it is about your athletes but still having a little bit of limelight for yourself from like marketing from letting people know that you actually work with that athlete in that type of stuff and for me like that's a really that's a tricky one too is we're like building those businesses because I don't want to come across as like
Yeah, I coach elite athletes, all of them, because I don't. Like, I coach amateur athletes, I coach elite athletes, I coach everywhere, I coach juniors, and that balance is super healthy for me, because I've been down the elite athlete road, and all that pressure and all the stuff, I go, and you know, it's unhealthy to me, I've identified that, so I like the balance of it.
As you make mistakes, you realize that. So, you know, I've chose to take on all different types of clients and that's kind of what I find super healthy and fun about what I do. Yeah. So, why don't we get started with kind of what we are here to talk about today and should we roll the dice? Like, do you want to rock, paper, scissor to see who goes first or what? Let's do it. All right. Okay. One, two, three.
Shoot. What do you got? Scissors. Ah, paper. Okay. All right. You're going to either don't edit that out because that you're doing or you're going to have to really edit that one. We'll see what happens when I listen back. Yeah. All right. So what does this mean? You get to choose or I lost and therefore I have to go? You lost your first. Okay. So what's the biggest mistakes of our coaching careers or whatever? I narrowed mine down to like five. Okay. Well, I did three.
So, and we can probably add more. So, I would say, like, as a young coach, I would say the first one that I did was too many days of intensity. Too many days. And I think the reason why I did that was, one, I didn't know. I thought I knew everything. I didn't know anything. But it was also hot. Like, it was hot in the...
in the world at the high-intensity training. What year was this? 2005-ish. Okay, yeah. Genre, right? Yeah. You know, and I work for CTS. I was an intern at the time, and then a coach. We just came out with a book, maybe Time Crunch Cyclist, like around that time. But anyway, it was like really focused on high-intensity and not a ton of volume, okay?
If you look at the mechanism of what we actually wrote in the book, it was not high intensity every single day. But I think as a young coach, I was like, more intensity is better? Let's do it. So it was like, if you're riding five days a week, intensity every day. Maybe four days a week, and then we'll just have one day easy. But I was just drilling people with too much intensity. How did you... Because I definitely did this.
And part of it for me, I think, was that I thought I would look more useful as a coach, because anybody can tell somebody to not ride hard. But as we do this more, in a lot of ways, that's the hardest part, to get people to ride easy. So how did you recognize that it was too much, and how did you kind of turn the corner on it? Yeah. So I recognized it was too much when, thankfully, at
CTS, when I was in kind of the program that I was in, we had, these have become like mythological stories now, where we would have to create a training program and then present it to other coaches and get peer reviewed as they, you know, you're up there, just you, and they're, you know, loading their ammunition of comments and they're about to fire at you. But these were also, the peer group that I was working with was,
Multi-Time, you know, the coaches had worked with Multi-Time World Champs, Olympic Champs, they wrote the book on every, so it was good coaches doing this. So, raked over the coals about that, so I got feedback early on. Okay, cool. But then, as a coach, you want to apply it. Okay, am I right? Am I wrong? Okay, let's do that, and then you dial it back. So, basically, people were just getting fatigued. They were getting tired. I wasn't listening.
Then you have another peer review, right? And it's like, okay, maybe I should start listening to this, right? But what's interesting, right, is because some people, some people can handle a lot more. So I had some people that were actually succeeding and then other people that were crumbling. And that, I think, is a slippery slope because some coaches do that and they just keep going. And then the people, the strongest rise to the top. And if you can't succeed in my system.
You must be weak, you must not be trying hard enough. Selection bias. I see that. Selection bias. There you go.
See, you got the technical terms, because you're the nerd. Thank you. And then over time, I found the recipe, because I was listening to my mentors, I was listening to my coaches, and I was tuning in. Yeah, that's good. I mean, and where you went with that, as in you started listening, that's actually something that, that's my first mistake that I made, is I wasn't listening to people. Because I was coaching people, like I kind of fell into it.
Somebody said, write me a plan. My friend said, no, well, you got to write me a plan too. And that's how it started. And I was getting coached in such a way where my coach was really kind of an absentee landlord. It's like, hey, the faucet broke and you get a call back like two months later. Oh, hey, sorry, we'll fix that. And for 40 bucks a month, what do you expect? But I didn't know what to expect.
And so I just had a spreadsheet of like today, 3x10 Z4. And that's how I started coaching people because I didn't know any better. And so after a while, I was like, okay, this is getting better, this is getting better, this is getting better. But I was still missing that piece where I was really plugged into the human. And at one point, somebody said like, you know, for X amount, you should be looking at myself every day.
And at this point, looking back, I'm like, for that amount, not a reasonable expectation, maybe $100 a month or something like that. But at the same time, I was like, I would have spotted this guy being upset earlier, for sure. And that was, God, that was at 2016 or 17 or something like that. That was really early on. And after that, I started.
Like, I was in Training Peaks every single day. Get home from work, sit down at Training Peaks, how's everybody doing? That was the first thing I thought, and then everything started to get so much better at that point. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, that's the partnership, not the dictatorship, right? If you're not listening, you're just providing information and you're a dictator. You're telling, you're not listening. And so, I'd say...
And therefore, like for every athlete, I just take the individualized approach, I listen, kind of dose response, let's, here we go. But I would observe that most people, like if anybody's listening here and it's like, oh, how many days of intensity is good? Two to three, mostly. And you say, well, I did four hard days last week. And I'd say, okay, cool. How are you feeling this week? Because even if you go four or five days, or what about stage racing?
Cool. But then, like, the next week is then easy. So then you average it out by two, and then now you got, like, six days hard. Yeah. I mean, it's kind of, like, the universal sort of thing. And you can do it, you just need to, you know, pat it on the backside with easy. Yeah, for sure. I mean, back when I was at my aerobically fittest, I was doing four to five hard days a week. And I am the world's slowest responder.
Or, well, one of them. And it was benefiting me as long as I could actually do the workouts. And a lot of the time, like, and I recovered fast, thankfully. But, you know, I was also like in my, what, late 20s. So you're going to recover fast at that point anyway. And I was like, at that point, I was like, okay, I think this is good. I think I figured this out. I started giving it to people. And they were like, they would get to day three in a row. And they were like, fuck you.
Yeah, yeah, because I mean, I would imagine those people weren't, they were, they had day jobs, right? And so with the elite athlete, sure, you know, I'll give them four days. It's structured differently, and I won't do that all the time. But for an amateur athlete, somebody with a day job, I mean, this is also some like predictable patterning and what to expect out of training in order to get the response that you want. I would much rather, if four is your 100% maxed out training of intensity, four sessions in a week.
I'd rather do three and stay a little less that you have time to recover, and then we do that over time, we get more, as opposed to just Leroy Jenkins' full send on week one. I tell people that when they do that, and they can do that many hard sessions in a week, I tell them they're not succeeding at it, they're getting away with it.
This is not going well because you add one more feather on that scale and suddenly it tips into overtraining. You have a bad night of sleep, you miss lunch because of work, you get stressed one day, you have a fight with somebody, you get rear-ended in traffic. All these things can tip the balance very easily. You are riding that edge when you're doing that. Yeah, and I would say that the most slippery slope is
Athletes can get away with multiple days of that if they're motivated enough and their willpower is high. And that's what leads to overtraining or underperformance, whatever you want to call it. Because what we do is not so precise that if I say three days and you do four, you can do that a few times before problems happen. And then the athlete says, no, see, I can do four.
And you say, yeah, but long term. And then you're almost like parenting because when my dad was telling me something as a kid and I was like, no, I'm going to do this. And then eventually the bad thing happened. And I was like, right. All right. So what's your second? I'm going to stick with the intensity realm of things because I would say that I also overestimated intensity. Okay.
So what intensity are we talking about? So again, we were working, we know more now. We have better tools, we have better methods, and even at CTS, like we used to use a two by eight minute time trial. Oh, I have roasted that many times, yeah. Yeah, I bet you have. And for proper reason. And for amateur athletes, it's a decent way of getting there because eight minutes is more digestible for someone's brain rather than 20 minutes.
However, the problem that you get with that is if you're a more anaerobic athlete, you can really go deep on that eight, right? There you go. Him. Not me. Definitely me. My eight-minute power is like the same as my 45-minute power. But so then it overestimates. So when you're a remote-based coach, you've got a ton of athletes and you're just like rifling through, you're going to use the highest average power. You're going to go for it. Maybe you do.
Verification Test Workout, where you dial stuff in, but maybe you don't, and you just like go for it, then they handle it for so long, then bad things happen, away we go. Now, I'm not saying that like every coach that was working with me overestimated intensity zones, but I certainly did with a lot of my athletes. I'm not saying that it was always that field test marker, because other coaches were using that same field test, and then they would come at it in different ways, but there was art that went along with that, okay? Because if you keep in mind, it was like two by eight.
Okay? And if you saw differences in the two, meaning the first one was super high and the second one, they just like cratered, but the heart rate was still jacked. It's like, oh, maybe I should like, for the average, maybe take somewhere halfway in the middle. So I started doing that, right? And then I started to refine the process. And then eventually now, I use a totally different kind of method, if you will, but much longer if I'm going to test the glycolytic energy system.
or FTP. Yeah. And that actually goes to one of mine, which is I had an over-reliance on zones early on. Like, I think a lot of people do, actually. And I think in a lot of ways, it's not even the worst way to keep going. But I think...
It was kind of around when I started doing my long FTP tests, which I think I started giving people around like 2016-ish. I think MIT, I was coaching the MIT road team and they were the first people to do them because, you know, college kids are the typical game pig for exercise science anyway. So I was like, all right, let's do this. And we got some people doing some pretty good numbers. They liked the test. They were like, hey, did you sneak that in on me? I was like, yeah. And after that.
I realized that we could just find it by feeling it out, which How long were you? Oh, like 45 minutes. Yeah. And it was like a progression, like, give me 2x20, now give me 1x45, but ramp it up a little bit and, you know, make it an exhaustive effort kind of thing. And so I snuck it in on them, and obviously, it's MIT, like, they're going to be like, they're going to see through it. They're fucking smart, like, well, like most people, actually.
I went with, I started doing more RPE stuff at that point. And going, okay, I bet you could feel out your RPE. And so I developed kind of a method to just coach people into feeling out their FTP. And after, I don't know, maybe another year or so, I started doing more RPE things for everything. And at this point, when I'm working with folks, one of the things I tell them is, at some point, when you are
Well-trained enough, and you are the training Jedi Master, I'm not even going to give you a power target. I will for some things, but for the most part, you're not going to see them give me like, you know, 2x20 FTP. That's going to be your workout. And you know exactly how that feels, you know exactly what your number is. And when you go do it, you're going to know, okay, maybe my FTP has gone up 5 watts. Cool. Great. Maybe it's the same as before, which is normal. You can do it longer, but...
And then we've got even more kind of cues to keep all the training on the tracks without kind of getting all wonky with it. But yeah, I used to think that it was time and zone was king or queen or monarch. And as long as you did, like if you had like, you know, four by five minutes, like zone five or something, like so four by five VO2s, I was like, man, as long as you get them in in that day.
Do one in the morning commute, do one in the evening commute, wait an hour, do another one. I thought that was the same stimulus. And in a way, it's really not. And same with like threshold training. Definitely not. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, there's for sure. Like I'm right there with you. There are some people, man, I, here's a funny case. One, one guy, strong, strong masters, mountain biker.
came to us, he did Trans-Andes, and he was fast enough, but he was, he couldn't get, I tell him to do some intervals, okay, and I tell him, okay, here's some ranges and zones, but make it feel like this, and he's like, oh, but you told me to do these numbers, I'm like, yeah, but like, it's also a perceived effort, and don't forget your heart rate stop, okay, and we'll get to that in a second, but it was, it was so fucking with his head, that was like, for a couple times, I'm like, just forget your device, just go out and do it,
Remember the workout, 4x10, whatever, make it feel like an 8. Okay, cool. Seven years now, the dude has not bought a power meter. He's gone like full rogue. Sometimes I get GPS files if I'm lucky, but he wins like everything when it comes to like masters mountain bike stuff like in the southeast. Like he's having fun, he's super fit, and he's going fast. So for me, I'm like, sounds good.
Check in when you need. Here's a program. And that makes me sound like a terrible coach. But at the same time, the method is working, and it unfucked his head, so I'm not going to mess with it. Because he's way happier, he's way healthier, and that's a good thing. Now, what I would strive to do is measure everything.
and make sure to have RPE first, power, heart rate. And that's kind of like the Holy Trinity. But then all the other stuff that we're measuring with a device, let's capture it so we actually know what's working, but let's get back to RPE. I think that's a very healthy thing to do in a coach-athlete balance. Well, I would like to – actually, this is way far down on my list, but it was – because way far down on my list was like setting a performance baseline.
I think, in a way, what I would want to do with him is I would want him to record power and never look at it ever. So that way, I've still got my objective metrics of improvement or not, but I mean, even regardless of that, like, he's got X goals, he's meeting the goals, you're meeting all the expectations, things are going well, I don't see any reason to mess with the process at all. Yeah, and that's what I'm saying, because even if I didn't do anything with the data, other than
Objectively look at it. It would be super fun to see how the changes were made, right, to understand that a little bit more. In the end, like, what he did was, you know, a lot more longer, hard stuff worked on, like, some of the anaerobic, which wasn't a limiter in total, but, like, longer, hard stuff to the point where you could...
You know, tolerate three, three and a half hours of like high threshold heart rate effort and go for it, which is a lot of the marathon stuff that he was doing. So in the end, like all good. But I think for anybody listening, and I still coach like zoney, I still coach with power, but I also am telling RPE along with it. And I still have a lot of workouts where I'm like, you know what, go out there, go hard for two hours today.
Normalized power should be roughly that, check on it every once in a while, perceived efforts like a gritty 8. Let's go. Especially for mountain bikers, I love to work like that, where I'll say, give me, you know, early season, give me a 2x20 at XCO pace. Nice, there you go. Or it'll be like, you know, give me 3x5 at short track pace. And that's a good way to go, because when you're racing those races, you know exactly what that pace is. Short track, 20 minutes, okay, I know exactly how hard this is.
And it's a fun way to get in that kind of work without really making it too structured because the races themselves are way less structured than we could ever try to emulate. And in a lot of ways, I think that we're actually, the coaching world is coming back around to using races as training sometimes.
in that regard, because there's only so many things that we can actually replicate in training before you gotta go hop in a race and, you know, get in the draft of the smelly guy and try to outspurt him at the end. Or a smelly girl. Or a smelly person. For me, it was a guy, so, obviously. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, and I think, too, like, another AP-ism is training is the exact opposite of racing, where
We're doing fairly structured, intentional things to get you really tired so that when you rest, you get better and we have less weaknesses and stuff going on. Whereas racing is I'm trying to conserve as little as possible, do as little as it takes to win. So that could mean everything or that could mean just sit in, go for the sprint. So it's very opposite way of operating.
So then, in training, we're working on energy system developments, specificity, I mean, name all the things that we do in training. And then in racing, that's where the specific stuff comes, the tactics, the feel, the corner, all this kind of stuff. So we're always, like, hitting microphones and making things loud. But we're always, like, going back and forth so that when we enter into the race, now we're going. But it's not training. The people who do...
Oh man, you're going to be mad about the people who do intervals in a group ride or like, going to test my one minute power on this road race. Stay home. I have one person who does intervals on group rides because those group rides are actually part of their job as a, as a, um, well, I don't want to out that person.
I was going to say I already don't like them, but yeah, there's special use cases where I can get my brain records. It's one of those things where I don't like it either, but it's like, this is the best we got, and if we didn't have some stuff like this, then yeah, like doing your 2x20 on the front of the group ride where it doesn't matter what anybody's doing, you just have to go do that ride because it's, you know, team mandated kind of. Like that's, I'm like, okay, this is what we got, then we're going to work with it. That's fine. I don't love it, but.
Yeah, it's alright. Actually, I think the people who do kind of like random efforts on the group ride that violates the vibe of the group ride, it's like, you know, Monday recovery ride, the person who's attacking off the front on Monday recovery ride and looking back like, who's going to chase me? Like, nobody. Nobody's going to chase you. I think that's even worse. Yeah, it is worse. But like, you know, I'll probably, you'll probably hear some, it's like, why does that dude hate people doing interviews?
The reason I don't like it is because you can do intervals alone. If you're going to do group ride stuff, do group ride stuff. Like, get caught up in the moment. If you've got one-minute efforts to do, throw a flyer. Like, attack super friggin' hard and go for it. Just know that it could be 50 seconds and that's fine. It could be 72 seconds and that's fine. Like, right, and then... Yeah, yeah, go with the spirit of your original workout and make it less structured. I completely agree with that. Actually, one of the things that my biggest pet peeve about...
Intervals on group rides is that it's dangerous. Well, yeah, somebody's like mid-pack and they're like, oh, go harder. I can't keep in my zone. It's like, just get on the front. And then people are like, I don't want to go that fast or that slow or whatever. And it becomes an issue. And then people are like blown through stop signs and traffic lights to keep up their intervals. And yeah, I just don't, not a big fan. Anyways, oh, so it's my turn. Oh, wait, no, is it your turn? Whose was that?
Just kidding. I said I overestimated intensity. I don't know if that's, I think that's what I'm talking about. And you snuck one in there. Oh yeah, that was way down my list. But okay, yeah. Here's a big one for me. Is I would trust but not verify. So a lot of the time when I have my intro call with somebody, I'll say like, how's your ride nutrition? How's your...
You know, off-bike nutrition, or when you're, you know, dinner, how's your protein intake? What's your fats and carbs intake like? Somebody says, oh, it's this, that, and the other thing, but I'm fine. I'm like, okay, I'll believe them. But I never really, for a while, dug into, okay, how many grams an hour are you doing on the bike? What are you taking on the bike? And I'm not like some world-class nutritionist. I'm far from it.
I know enough where I can give somebody some very general guidance with this stuff and spot bad nutrition. And a lot of the time, I was having issues, because I take notes on my intro calls. I've got giant notes files for all my clients. And I would look back and go, okay, well, this person says they're really good with their nutrition, but it looks like something's off, but their nutrition's fine. That's not the issue. And if it were anybody else, I'd be like, you need to eat more.
And I just went with what they said. And I didn't say, hey, we got to talk about your nutrition again, because I don't think it's as good as you think it is. And because I think for a while, I didn't want to insult people by saying, oh, you think this is good? Okay, well, it's not good. So let's fix it. And you can do that nicely, which I've eventually learned to do. But I was not good at it at the beginning. Yeah, I think that comes with
Experience and Education. And I'll give you, if I can, like one. So, I probably was terrible at it too. But just yesterday, I had a, well, okay, it's actually a couple weeks in the making. I had a trust and verify scenario come up. And this athlete, so amateur athlete, she does gravel stuff. She's super stoked about it. And I've ridden with her a couple times. And so, like, she's smaller, athletic looking.
Nothing crazy. And so Training Peaks comment came in and said, oh, we had a field test. That's why she's like, it's like, I've, you know, felt like death on, on, you know, the whole time. And it was like, kind of like 12 watts lower than what I thought. I was like, okay, maybe a bad day. And the comments were, I, I reduced my carbohydrate intake recently because my doctor said I was pre-diabetic. And I was like, what?
and I've been coaching her for a few years and like again like she's very active you know we're training eight to maybe 12 hours a week at the highest not super crazy but again like bikes are part of her lifestyle healthy person and so if I like we finally get on the because back and forth and I was traveling and I was like okay let's make sure we talk about this so I started asking questions I'm like how did your doctor arrive to this well and she goes I have blood test okay
Did you do blood tests right away in the morning? No. Were you fasted when you do it? No. What'd you have for lunch? I had pizza and a Coke. When was your blood test? Three hours later. That's exactly what I thought. Somebody's glucose is super elevated. Right. So then we talked all about how glucose works in the body, all this kind of stuff. And I went through Super Sapiens University, which we don't even have to get into Super Sapiens.
and I'm a hack on like nutrition and I'm not a doctor and everything but I'm pretty good at blood work and so all these things that I'm just like pulling on I'm like okay listen to your doctor but get a second opinion here's why you need a fasted blood test here's why not to eat pizza right before a blood test you know and walk through and it like she's a smart person but she had some and then she started googling right and it was just like reduction of carb if anything I was like so what'd you learn it's like well I was eating a lot of like
White Pasta, you know, like sugary juices and all this kind of stuff. And I noticed that I was like kind of feeling better throughout the day if I didn't do that. But in my workouts, I wasn't. I'm like, okay. So then we talked about how to, macronutrient timing and whatever we go in college. It's like making sure carbs are in the system before we go hard. And then maybe not do that anyway. So trust verified. Don't just be like, oh, he's a doctor. Must be good. You're pretty bad. Yeah.
And that stuff always comes with a very big warning from me, too. But luckily, we have a doctor as a coach, and I can just say, Fabiano, what do you think about this? And he's been absolutely fantastic being a resource, and he's obviously an excellent coach himself, but it's been great having him as a resource. But also, I mean, I'm sure you know plenty of doctors where you can say, hey, what about this? Because, I mean, not a lot of doctors are totally, you know, versed on what an athlete's physiology looks like.
because a lot of the time, like I've seen continuous glucose monitors of signals from people like, you know, athletes and it's like their blue glucose dips way, way low and it shoots sky high, like way out of the normal ranges sometimes and sometimes that's normal, sometimes it's not normal and you've got to do a lot of extra, you know, what do you call it, just analysis and digging on that kind of stuff because like another one is like heart rate.
You know, back when I was aerobically in shape, I would, you know, every time I was at the doctor and they took my blood pressure, they're like, your heart rate's really low. I'm like, I haven't had coffee today because I know you're not supposed to do that before you go get your blood pressure tested. And they're like, yeah, but it's like, it's in the 40s. And I'm like, yeah, it's a little high today. Yeah, and I think a couple points on that is human, we think human physiology is so simple and it is not.
And we sit here behind microphones and we're trying to tell you what we've learned and we do it with humility. But all these systems that we're talking about are so complex, I feel like we're scratching the surface of it and we're learning more. Even this industry is super, super new. So we're learning as we go.
and so I think what goes into a good coach is have that humility to know it's like hey some shit may come down the pipe in five years and you're gonna have to rethink the way you do it and also a good coach will have other good people in their corner like a doctor to verify some of the stuff that's like overly complicated to the shit that we're doing like in practice as we go so we don't mess those people up so with all that said yeah
Glucose, there's a lot of, don't fear the spike. That's all I'll say about it. Fuel for the work required. So, I think that's the end, is that the end of your list? Oh, okay, yeah, go for it. My mistake was, my mistake was, and still, like I would say I'm working on this, it's not too far off from what you said, but I would text instead of call.
Okay. Now, I text message a lot. Like, email's dead, in my opinion. I know people who email like they're texting. Yeah, exactly. I'd have some of those, too. But text message is a very good way for rapid-fire communication, and I can multitask and do that, and I can get, you know, quick answers. But the reason I say that this has been a mistake is because when I receive information that's not full information, and then...
I need to assume something to say yes, proceed, or no, don't proceed, or okay, got it, I'll take care of that, and I'm wondering, or if it's something that, if the text message tells me low confidence or unsure, it's better to pick up the call and go, because if I text back and like, yeah, do it, and then they just crumble in the workout, or they really F it up in the race, or whatever, I'm like, and I've done that a lot, and no, I mean, a lot, too much.
for me to be talking about now. And so then I find if I actually pick up the call, take five minutes, stop whatever I'm doing, just be like, okay, so did you get it that we should probably do more like 70 grams of carbohydrate versus 90 because it's super hot and you're going to want to barf or something like that. Generally goes better because now we're communicating a lot better rather than text. So there's opportunities, but there's all...
So the human connectedness, real communications that we're both on the same page, I think that's good. And I'll put texting in the way of Training Peaks comments. I always encourage athletes to do that. But when a problem arises, don't just like comment back, be like, hey, let's talk. Oh, yeah, because the comments, like, I'm sure you do the same thing as me, where I compartmentalize it, where I'll look at it in the morning, I'll look at it in the afternoon if I have time, and then definitely in the evening. And that's when, you know, if somebody like if, because sometimes I remember,
Me and one client in particular, we would be back and forth at night because clearly neither of us had anything better to do but comment on one like training peaks race or something like that. But, you know, occasionally, you know, or actually oftentimes he would be like, hey, do you have time for a chat? And sometimes I wouldn't, but a lot of the time I would. And we would get a lot of good stuff done by talking rather than texting because, you know, because how many times have you done like an email consultation where it takes you four hours to write and it could have been a one hour conversation?
Yeah. Yeah, for sure. And this goes into just general workflows of things. There are some things that you need kind of like slow communication and read it. Now, this is information. But when we need to dialogue, go back and forth and figure something out, it's not email. A little bit of text. But to your point, yes, we can do it faster, way more efficient, and way more accurately if we actually verbalize to each other.
Even to the point of like voice messages, which I would say email sucks, then text message, then voice message, then talk. Yeah. Then in person. And that's probably another thing is like if you're a coach and athlete, one of the things that I try to do is I try to meet with every single one of my clients in that first year if I can. It's always been like a thing of me. And it could just be for coffee, could be for a bike ride, could be for a training camp or even better yet.
Go to the race where they're doing, where they're racing at. And I find my communication, my knowledge of them, it just goes so much further. And in the way of showing them that you care, in the way of developing performance, in a way of communication, it's all better once I have that human connectedness with my... Yeah, for sure. I mean, and that's actually one of the things that I've come to prefer is, especially when I have an intro call with somebody, I really want to do a video call.
Just seeing somebody's face and like kind of being able, I'm, because I'm not great with like voice cues a lot of the time, but I'm pretty good with facial cues now. I used to be terrible at them, by the way, absolutely terrible at reading a room. My college days were a lot of, hey, you look mad. And I'm like, no, I'm having a good time. They're like, well, you don't look it. And I'm like, oh, I didn't look around and see everybody staring at me like, what's wrong with him? So, so I really.
Call that resting, resting face. That's the, that's the polite way I heard my resting face described. So, so yeah, I just, I really like to have a video call and like, and just like really get a sense of talking to that person. Because people I haven't had video calls with, a lot of the time, they don't, they're like, in some ways, it's harder to make them, you know, to, to really develop that kind of connection that I.
kind of need as a coach to get a sense of like who they are, what they're about. And one of my, I've met a couple of people at races. Like I met one guy at nationals last year. I met one guy years ago at like a local cross race because I was there for the ECCC and he was just happened to be there. And he was like, oh, hey. And I was like, dude. And we hung out for an hour and we made so much headway just sitting there in a freezing cold spot at that cross race and just talking.
And I was like, man, this is kind of great. And that's when I started doing calls with people to start coaching them, because before it was like, hey, you good to go? Okay, here's the right. Okay, cool. All right, I'll give you training now. And that was it. That was as far as it went. But yeah, the intro call has been, and calls as we go, it's been so, so, so helpful. Yeah, and I think too, like we're sitting here, we're talking as coaches, and then we sometimes like, you know, talk to the athlete here on the side, just in this podcast. And I would say,
to the athletes listening who have coaches, do this as well. Like try to meet with your coach, whether it's on Zoom or you're passing through or you're going to the race or whatever, like try to meet with them because I'm not saying that like AI is going to take over the world and AI wouldn't be hitting the mic like that. AI wouldn't be hitting the mic like that.
AI will come and there's going to be stuff I'm excited about because I think it'll actually help us as coaches probably speed up the building process, if you will, or have tools that I can do it a lot faster so then I can spend more time with my athlete so that we can actually coach as opposed to just like program a program, right? Because that's part of what we do as coaches. But I think, you know, so to the athlete, try to call when you've got
Bigger Problems, don't just text. Try to meet your coach in person as best you can and make that effort. Because remember, it's a two-way street. Yeah, I agree. So I got one more mistake I've done. I still do occasionally, actually. Like you're still doing that one occasionally. I'm still doing this one occasionally. And this is where I will let people dictate their training program to me.
So this is a problem? This is a problem. And it started, I remember the first time it happened, I started coaching a fairly high-level mountain biker. And he had worked with a bunch of coaches, and sometimes that's a red flag, a lot of the times it's not. But occasionally it's like, this guy's worked with so many different people. And so...
So we had a bunch of calls and he was like, all right, here's what I want to do. And I didn't have the sense to say, don't do that. Like there was a lot of stuff with like, I'm going to do altitude here. I'm going to, I want to do this kind of training here. I want to do this kind of training here. And then I'm going to do this before this race and, you know, figure it out. And I was like, oh, okay. And it never went well, ever.
This is not what I'm here for. And it was like a reverse dictatorship in a lot of ways. And whenever I was not being dictated to, things started going better. But at the same time, especially somebody who is a coach themselves, this can happen somewhat frequently, not all the time, but often enough, or somebody who's got advanced degrees, like master's, even bachelor's, and a lot of time PhD in exercise phys.
These are folks who will be like, I think I need to do X. And when I think, I don't think we really need that at all. And I just didn't have the nuts to say, nope, I don't think we should do that. Yeah, I've been down that road as well. I would say I do it less with less wrongness now. That's a good way to put it in English.
In other words, I still give my athletes autonomy and choice in what we're doing. And for those who have been doing it long enough, I'll say, okay, what do you feel like you need to work on right now? And they'll give me something either very detailed or very generalized. And I say, okay, here's what I recommend we do. Here's how it looks in Training Peaks. Here's how I would model it. You good with that? Yeah, I'm good with that. That's how I found success in that way for me personally. But yeah, to the same point where...
Somebody has the education or somebody has like self-coaching, then they're like, but I really want to do, if I give them full reign, and it's not because it's like I'm a control freak. In fact, I'm not. I just gave a whole presentation last week at CTS. We were in Bentonville in part of what I call it a TP collab.
Where I want them to put stuff in Training Peaks, move stuff around as they need to, so long as it's still in the confines. See, I'm not hitting my microphone. As long as it's in the confines, in the same vein of what we're trying to achieve. So I think that autonomy is good.
But, yeah, I feel like most athletes, if you give them full autonomy and be like, yeah, go for it, I'll take a look at it. What are they paying you for at that point? Just to rubber stamp their whatever they decide? I know a lot of coaches who have complained about people like that who are like, this guy just tells me what he wants to do and then what am I here for? Like, am I your blue checkmark for whatever you want to decide for yourself? And, you know,
Man, I think, you know, when you're talking about autonomy, that's one of the things that actually goes really well when you do more communication, to go back to my first thing, where, you know, at first, especially if somebody's new to training, and they don't know exactly, oh, I can't put, like, my first four days of the week sucked, and so now I've got three hard workouts to do, Friday, Saturday, Sunday. You know, if you're not watching somebody,
You know, they're going to do that. And it's not going to go well, a lot of the time. And so you've got to keep the bumper bowling for a while. And you get to be the bumpers. And then and then, okay, well, can I do this? No, bump. Can I do this? No, bump. Okay, and then they find that middle ground after after a while.
I trust my athletes to make the right decisions for themselves, and they'll be like, ah, I just pushed this tomorrow, or should I do, I'm not going to skip this workout, should I do this workout later, or should I do the one you planned for that day? And like, and that's the kind of stuff where it really shows a person who you've coached well to making good decisions, and a lot of the time, I think these people could, in some ways, easily coach themselves, but in a lot of ways,
You know, having a coach is really good because it's having two sets of eyes on a plan is way better than one. And you've got a more objective person watching too. Yeah, I agree with that. And I told one of my athletes this morning, I said, if I'm doing a good job at coaching, I'm making myself almost obsolete in a way because I'm giving it all away. Yeah. Okay. Like all this stuff, you know, like, and he's like, that's an interesting thought. I go, but.
I go, what's so hard is it goes back to separating the emotion from reality, right? How hard this is or how much training should I actually do or should I sleep in? Should I miss the group ride? That kind of thing. And the accountability piece of that too with somebody looking over your shoulder, that's one thing. Because everything I do is not mysticism. It's very, very open. And I love the collaboration. And there's time periods where I give my athletes autonomy and I keep it in touch. But then there's the point where it's like, nah.
We gotta really dig in and here we go. And that's where I think the full autonomy or the full athlete, as long as you're super into it, right? You have performance goals, this is part of your lifestyle, that kind of thing. Having the extra set of eyes, it's part of what adds enjoyment to your life. So therefore, the discretionary income goes that way. But I'm not...
Mad. In fact, I'm happy if someone after five or six years, they're like, man, I learned so much, maybe not racing at the high level anymore, so I don't need you, but I love you. Let's stay in touch. Great. Yeah. And part of also being a good coach in that way, in letting people have that autonomy and actually being able to kind of collaborate like that, is because you have a shared purpose and a shared goal and shared expectations.
where I think a lot of the time, especially here at Empirical Cycling, one of the things that I've found is when things are going wrong, it's almost always a mismatch of expectation. And so if somebody thinks we're going to do this or somebody thinks that their goal is this and the other person doesn't realize that or wasn't communicated effectively or something or
The goals change, nobody said anything. That happens all the time. And then when somebody's frustrated or going, oh, why is this here? How come we're not doing X? It's like, oh, I thought this, that, the other thing. Oh, well, okay, well, let's fix that. And so communication, again, like you said, is absolutely key. I mean, I've worked on professional teams. I've worked in organizations of various kinds.
And anytime that there's a huge issue, it is a miscommunication of expectation. I would say that that is either the thing or a key element in every problem. Agreed. So, do you want to get to some listener questions? You got a little bit of time? Let's do it. I do have, I have probably 10 minutes. Let's get to the good ones then. Okay. Yeah, don't do the bad ones.
Is it more about managing fatigue than prescribing intervals? Depends on what you're trying to accomplish. I would say it's got to be equally both. Equally both is what I would say. Because if you do the wrong intervals, I mean, you can just go out and do like a five by five, five days a week, just to make it really symmetrical. And you can do that for five years.
Okay, if it's all about managing fatigue, that should work just fine, but that's not what we're going to find. Yeah, no, I mean, frame it up differently, because in the end, it's both, right? But what we were just talking about, too, is like, there's some athletes who are not giving intervals to. Therefore, is it just managing fatigue? Well, no, because training, I'm trying to get them fatigued.
So then how do you manage it? Well, I get them fatigued, then I get them unfatigued, then I get them fatigued, then I get them fatigued. So sure, there's a lot of management that goes on with the fatigue, but you got to get some specificity and some structure. I agree. Next question is, what's the best mistake you've made? The best mistake I made? Yeah. That's a good question.
Here's a, yeah, that's a good question. Two, actually. Yeah, I'll do one. So I was a very, I'm still athletic, I still ride my bike and do things. But back in the day, I was actually a really good runner, okay? Because I wrestled all through college, and I would have to run to get my weight low. And I was like 185, 190 in the off-season, then I'd go down like 157 in college. Yeah, it was a big swing.
All the running actually made me into an endurance athlete, probably took away from my wrestling, but I was always the person, I was always the wrestler who could go good in the third period. Then I started mountain biking, and that was way more fun, because you could go fast. So then I started racing Xterra, and I was actually pretty decent, and I placed high enough at a regional to where I could go to Worlds in Maui. And that was a time where I had CTS, or internship at CTS, and the coaching director at the time
looked at me plainly because I was going to have to miss a week or something like that. He goes, well, that was a choice, Adam. You either decide to be a mediocre athlete for the rest of your life or you become the best coach. I didn't go to Maui. But it was like samurai sword right down the middle. It was amazing advice and posed as a question.
It was great. Tim Pillow. I don't know what he's doing now, but he, uh, he was at NSC for a while. Look him up. Thank him. I will. Yeah, yeah, I will. Um, I think best mistake I ever made was starting in coaching. Um, yeah. I remember I asked my first coach, I was like, would you do this full time if you could? And he was like, dude, the market's so saturated. And I'm like, okay, well, it doesn't mean you shouldn't try, I guess. Cause I, I thought he was a pretty good coach at the time. And I was like, dude, you could, you could really do this. Like instead of working at a bike shop.
But, eh, either way. Yeah, and just as a qualifier, like, when I decided to go coaching instead of the athlete round, like, I was really sad because I saw everybody racing and I was like, man, I could have done all this and then coaching, it was, you know, boring, it was hard, I was getting my shit handed to me every single day, really hard. Thought it was a mistake, maybe I should have done it, but then in the end it worked out. That's what I mean by best mistake. Yeah. So, I've got, there's two questions that are kind of the,
Two different sides of the same coin, but I'm going to ask this one the way that this person asked me. Because usually I see it in how do athletes develop trust in their coaches? This question is, how does a coach develop trust in their athletes? Yeah, that's a good question. If the athlete's paying you and they have goals,
And you tell them then what to do. And if they do it and they're inquisitive about what's next, that's developing trust. If they don't do it, then I ask like, hey, why aren't you doing your intervals? Why aren't you doing your rests? Why aren't you doing your endurance? And they're like, eh. Like that's the best answer. Yeah, radio silence sucks. And it also sucks because you're concerned about the person.
and you don't know what's going on with them and when you ask if they're evasive it's like I you don't have to tell me exactly what's going on but say I'm really stressed okay great that's all I need to know or I got sick okay I need to know that but you don't have to tell me I spent four nights in the hospital I mean gotta hope not but you know like shit happens and so just just knowing a little bit and you know if you are in the hospital for four days and I don't hear from you like
Your first concern should not be, I gotta text my coach. Just take care of yourself. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, good communication and like, are you doing what you say you're gonna do? That's how trust is developed either way. I agree. Question is, the pod inspired me to start coaching a friend. What are common pitfalls for new coaches? Coaching your friends. I actually encourage people to coach their friends because your friends...
And you should tell this to them up front so we're meeting expectations and matching them. Your friends should not feel worried about giving you shit. Like, in a lot of ways, I tell my clients, like, especially when they have to stop working with us, like, I've seen people hem and haw over stopping working with a coach. And, you know, with us, with friends, with other coaches, all of it the same. And I tell them it's not personal.
I mean, you might like this coach a lot, and I'm sure they like you, but it's not personal. Like, this is, in a way, it's just business. Like, you know, if you're a teacher, you expect to get a new class every year. So, it's just one of those things that happens. And I want to work with some of my clients, a lot of them, forever, and I know I'm not going to. And that's just kind of the reality you got to live with. Yeah. And I would say, also to that point, there's,
There's no... Coaching your friend, I mean, there's trade-offs. Because you're your friend, you're probably riding and maybe even racing with them. You know a lot about them. Therefore, you could potentially coach them better, but you still have to separate yourself from the emotion of it. You can't...
You can't get caught up in their drama. You can't get caught up in all the bullshit that goes on when they're tired. If the plan is to get them even more tired, you got to push. You can't just soft-handed it. And so I coach some of my friends. I coach one of my best friends. I coach some friends locally that like I rip it up with all this kind of stuff, but there's almost like the professional, there's like, there's friend.
There's friend Adam, there's coach Adam, and then there's like professional Adam. You got to like mix them all together when you're in that way. And I don't, for a new coach, that's hard to do. So pitfalls for new coaches is this like tight-knit community that is like cycling and endurance. We're like, we're too friendly. So start to gain more experience, get more education, go to...
Training Peaks Universities, like get out, get other knowledge, listen to Cole's podcast, like learn how to become a better coach. And that will avoid pitfalls. And I'd say along the same lines, don't compete with your clients. It's not about you versus them. It's about them. It's not about you. And, you know, if you and people who do start to kind of have those feelings about like, oh, I don't.
If I coach them and they get faster, oh, why isn't it working for me? Or vice versa, like if you're getting faster coaching yourself, whatever you're doing with this person, if they're not getting faster, separate those two things. And if they say something about it, just remind them to separate those two things. Be like, look, I'm me, you're you, and this is about you. We're going to try to figure out what's going on because this should be one of those first lessons where you figure out what works for me does not work for other people.
You know, and you and I said this before we started recording, we were talking about the elite athlete, what did you say, curse? Or the pitfall? Probably. Where it's like, I'm this genetic freak, so what worked for me is, this is the plan, because look where it got me, and it's like, it's, a lot of the time, it's not necessarily because of the plan, it's because you got, you won the genetic lottery and the Powerball. Yep. Exactly. Oh, I like this one.
How long would you say it takes a coach to, quote unquote, dial in training plans for an athlete? Let's ask it another way. How long does it take for you to really feel like you are going to be really giving somebody the best programming that you can? Probably three months, I'd say.
That has taken a while to do, but I would say, if I have good communication, if I have good buy-in, I show them that they care, I'm focused on performance, I have good data, we have good communication channels, it's not immediate, and it takes a couple months. I think that's quick. Probably. Because for me, wow, you're way better than me at this. Because for me, it's a year. And I say it's a year because
I really need to, I feel like I need to get through a base and a build and a race season all together before I really start to know somebody very well. Because I feel like in three months we can do a lot, but I'm still missing pieces. Like if we start in like, you know, if this is an American person and we start in like October, I don't know, and they're not doing cross, I don't know how much openers they need, I don't know what kind of tapering they need, and we can kind of
And, you know, managing all that kind of stuff is...
You know, it's a totally different aspect that you may not see at different times of the year. Yeah, and I completely agree with that. And I would say I am still striving for the 100%. I wouldn't call it perfect. Perfect is slow suicide. Perfect's the enemy of good. Yeah, for sure. But like that dialing in process, that is continual. That is infinite. You're always trying to figure that out for your athlete. I want to expedite it.
and trying to figure out the opener routine, trying to figure out like how much load to bring in. Yeah, that gets dialed in for sure. But in the way that the question was posed in terms of how long for good workouts, I would say three-ish months, I mean, three cycles before I'm like, okay, here's how this person is patterning. Here's how they communicate. Here's how they respond to load, all that kind of stuff. So it's pretty good at three, better at six. It's going to get even better as we go.
AP's algorithm learns that machine as we go. But yeah, I would say three months-ish. Yeah. Actually, you answered the question better than I did because I, in my head, answered the question I wanted to ask you instead, which was like, how long does it really take to just get to know somebody? But yeah, for like workouts, just workouts and figuring out a good weekly routine, yeah, I'd say like two or three months for sure. Yeah.
Well, even so, one athlete that you and I have talked about that I recently started working with last year, we're like in the thick of that now. I would say just last week, we started to unlock that, like now we're into that final 10% of how do I get the most out of it? And that was coming up on a year. Yeah. But that's like the tippy top. Mm-hmm. Eight months.
There you go. Adam, it's been fucking awesome having you on the podcast again. Thank you so much. Good to be here. Good to be here. Thanks for asking me and thanks for having me on again. All right. So thank you everybody for listening. That was a great time with Adam. I know it was a little short compared to our usual podcasts, but you know what they say, leave them wanting more. And I hope you want more of that because we can have Adam back on. And yeah, it's a lot of fun to talk to him. I hope everybody really enjoyed our conversation.
If you would like to follow us on Instagram and ask questions for our future guests, give me a follow at Empirical Cycling. We get AMAs up there too. And as usual, if you want to donate to the show because we're ad-free, empiricalcycling.com slash donate. And if you would like to become one of our coaching or consultation clients, shoot me an email at empiricalcycling at gmail.com. It's really never too late to start with a good coach. And I like to think that we have quite a lot of good coaches. So anyway, all right. Thanks, everybody. We'll catch you in the next episode.