Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore, and today we're not joined by Kyle because we are joined by Patrick Smith again. And so this is going to be a great episode. Thanks, everybody, for listening. Obviously, subscribe to the podcast, et cetera, et cetera. iTunes rating is great. Thank you so much for all the five stars. Share the podcast anywhere that you might think it might be useful for somebody else. And also, we're an ad-free podcast, so as always, please donate at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We have some show notes up on the website. That includes a link to Patrick's website.
website that is coachpatricksmith.com. So if you have any coaching or consultation inquiries for me, you can send those into empiricalcycling at gmail.com. And if you want to get in touch with Patrick for any mental skills work or whatever you got, he's a good person to work with. So you can get in touch with him with his website. And with that, of course, on Instagram, as always, at empiricalcycling, we have the weekend AMAs up in the stories.
And if you want any Empirical Cycling merch, you can find it at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com
And so as we head into this episode, just a quick note, we had a little bit of hiss from Patrick's channel. I tried to get rid of it, but it's fairly pronounced, so I apologize for that. Ahead of time, there will be just a faint little ssss, so hopefully it's not too bad. Sorry about that. But it's a really cool discussion, and we kind of start with, why is it so hard to rest? But we really get into a lot more about athlete psychology and changing your behavior in positive ways to work towards your goals.
Especially the challenges that are faced by self-coached athletes who don't have a second set of eyes to work with them on that kind of stuff. So without any further ado, here's my conversation with Patrick Smith and I'll see you on the other side. Well, so when it comes to like coach education, you know, that's actually an interesting way to get into what I wanted to talk to you about today.
on athlete psychology in general. I think the very first thing is try and establish some of the basics. And one of the easiest basics, well, maybe not easiest basics, but one of the things that stands out to me that a lot of times gets overlooked is what gets measured gets managed.
Behavioral Science called Behavioral Reactivity and that is if you start measuring somebody, if you start giving them an assessment of some sort and they know they're being measured, they're going to start behaving differentially. They're going to react to being measured and after a couple of rounds of being measured, depending on how intrusive the measurement is and how explicit it is about what is being measured, the behavior will stabilize
somewhere, but that stabilization point, that new equilibrium point may not be reflective of prior to measurement. So it's like in quantum physics, like an observable effect. Like if you want to measure this particle, like you are going to affect it. Absolutely. Absolutely. And it's much more observable than watching quantum particles. But literally, if you go to an athlete and you say, hey, we're going to measure your
you know average wattage or time ridden or cadence the measurements you take and the new equilibrium is not going to have a hundred percent representation prior to that measurement point right and on one side of the coin in the behavioral sciences world we say okay this is a threat to your validity you know this is a threat to you making any claims that what you measured is actually what's going on in the natural world
But on the coaching side, if you can just get coaches to measure something that's going to have a material impact to the athlete, that in and of itself is a coaching intervention because the behavior is going to change. Right. And I've seen plenty of coaches, both novice and long time.
just jump right past that. Just go to like, okay, we need intricate. We need novel. We need like, we, I need to read 15 research papers before I change this interval by 30 seconds or whatever it may be. You know, they're going for the like shiny, sexy, different. And if we could get more to just recognize and start responding at the level of like what I measure.
will cause a behavioral change in my athlete just by measuring, just by them knowing that I'm paying attention to it. So how do we measure athlete psychology? So is it like mood? Is it like the subjective feelings, like RPE? Is it the training peaks, emojis? It depends on what you're trying to get at, but at the end of the day,
Behavior is critical. This is a distinction that's made between the field that I was trained in of behavior analysis versus big five personality psychology. Your big five personality psychology or some of these other wings of psychology are going to say there's these characteristics that are fixed and they are internal to you and they just categorize you prior to anything you do.
and they inform what you do. My field looks at it and says, no, what you do categorizes what you do. So it's predictive versus descriptive. Yeah, yeah. And in the same way, it's also really pragmatic.
Because if we look at like a big five personality kind of thing, they're going to say, well, you're this, this, this, and this. And that means you can do this and you can't do this. Whereas in my field, we say, okay, we see these behaviors occurring at these levels now. And they are occurring in these contexts. And some of them are being rewarded and some of them are being punished. And if we change that, so maybe we reward these behaviors and we punish these behaviors.
How does that frequency and balance of behaviors change? And how does that change in frequency and balance or occurrence of particular behaviors affect your ability to accomplish your value direction? So it's almost like bumper bowling. It's like instead of going in the gutter, we're going to guide you down to the pins somehow because you have a goal to meet that you haven't been meeting perhaps.
and we're going to try to get you there by looking at your behavior. And the bumper would be, I guess, this is probably a terrible analogy, but the bumper would be just analysis of your behavior so you recognize what you're doing and you can change it. Exactly. Yeah, that is actually a really good example if you think of the ball as the individual, the direction of the ball as how their behavior is.
resulting and then at like manipulating the topography of the table where the bumpers are, the tilt, whatever it may be as as a pragmatic like where the ball is now and where it's headed what do we need to do around this athlete and this behavior to shape them towards where we're trying to get right and so and it doesn't
It doesn't worry about the internal construction of the ball to a large degree as much as just what's going on now? How do we make an adjustment? How does that affect it? How do we make another adjustment? And one of those adjustments that we can make is simply measurement. Does that miss something that might be more fundamental and underlying about like the composition of a ball as in the person that like a big five thing might be more predictive of? Like, oh, you know that you tend to be like this.
so does it miss anything that way like is it is it all because it seems like on one level it would be all band-aids just like you know just you know correcting keeping you from going off the deep end you know in the gutters but you know is there as in would there be a better way to like get somebody to veer straight or do you have to like kind of hit the bumpers on the way down to the pins well that's a question of of process
Like if we have a ball going in a particular direction, what is the process in which we make change? And if we're in this metaphor of the bumper balls talking about direction as the product of their behavior, then the critical question becomes how do we influence behavior in a systematic manner to guide individuals towards their value?
Directions. And at that point, how much does it matter if there are unchangeable factors within that individual? Right. Because it's a question of like, okay, we're trying to influence behavior. If there is something within this individual that is unchangeable, predetermined.
Do we waste our time targeting this thing that will not result in a change? Or do we focus our efforts on those things that will influence their behavior in a manner meaningful to them? I mean, that's, man, this is way off the topic of sports, but isn't that kind of, you know, isn't there a range of people, like, in terms of what they think others are like? As in, like,
Oh, everything's, you know, culturally determined and learned versus, oh, everything's innate and unchangeable and immutable. And obviously it's somewhere in the middle, but, um, it's like, you know, do you give three strikes? Do you give people a chance to rehab or are some people like beyond, um, beyond saving? You are now navigating the waters of behavior analytic psychology. Oh God, completely by accident.
And it's okay because it also, we can steer this shit back to sports in the sense that like what you've just reflected is the nature-nurture debate. And you said it's somewhere in the middle. And like the premise of behavior analysis started at nurture and has been working back as a field.
towards understanding the, you could say, failure modes or criticisms of the behavior analytic practice where it's harder and harder and harder to discriminate between something that you cannot influence versus you can influence behaviorally. And my field, my research laboratory in particular, tries to take that bull by the horns because
The low-hanging fruit is external behavior, external contingencies, consequences, antecedent events, all that kind of stuff. The more nuanced stuff is when you're talking about exactly what you said of like cultural behavior and cultural behavior is language. And language encompasses thoughts and feelings and emotions. And there's definitely a sector of my field that's like, whoa, whoa, whoa, thoughts, feelings and emotions. We can't see it happen.
Therefore, we're just not going to touch it. It's radioactive. I feel that way about emotions too. And this is where we link back to coaching of like some coaching is just manipulating contingencies external to the athlete and some coaching is navigating.
All that culturally learned behavior, that language behavior around like what is acceptable, what is not acceptable, what's going to get rewarded, what's going to get punished and all the nuances. It's sort of like showing up to a race without shaved legs, you know, early in the spring and everybody's like, oh, look at the Wookiee up here, racing bikes, you know.
Yeah, yeah, and all of that is literally the culture of bike racing. I mean, along with like being white and male and weird in general. Like most cyclists are. Well, not, well, both terms, the acronym and the adjective. But, yeah, so, you know,
At the end of the day, there's a black hole that you can go down as far as nature versus nurture. And we've talked about this behind the scenes in how do you walk the line between evidence-based and placebo effect. And the reality is we have a constrained amount of time to work with our athletes. And so we have to make a compromised choice about where we are going to focus our energy.
And so do you want to focus your energy on a concept that everybody is telling us is fixed, predetermined, and otherwise immutable? Or do you want to focus your energy on those things that can actually move your athlete in a valued direction? Well, I think we all know the answer. So I hope. I hope so too. Well, so that gets us to kind of the main topic today, which is learning to rest.
Is it so difficult? So one of the things that I've seen so much and I think one of the hardest things to accept as an athlete is stopping for a little bit because, you know, I wrote down a bunch of notes here, like trusting the process. You know, is it a leap of faith? Are you actually going to lose all your hard work that you've put in?
Are you anxious to get back to training? Do you just enjoy riding a lot? So these are things that I want to ask you about in terms of these being behaviors and kind of how we tease out how do we get somebody to rest versus their motivations and their priorities. Yeah.
Yeah, and what you've outlined of like, are they anxious to get back? Do they feel like they're going to lose all their hard work? Is being active just fun for them? That tracks with a lot of what I wrote out when you suggested this prompt. Maybe I use a little more technical terms, but at a 30,000 foot level, human behavior is a combination of how we talk about stuff.
and external contingencies of reward reinforcement. And when we're talking about it in the concept of how we talk about it and how we respond to our own language about it, when you said being anxious to get back to work or feeling afraid that you're going to lose all of your hard work, that's a lot of the cultural language around rest.
The idea, the concept being talked about in complete opposition to strain, to improvement, to being competitive. So we have an environment where everybody's talking about rest as this thing that is against getting better, being competitive. And so when we think about like, okay, it's time for me to rest.
There's going to be that very expected language response of like, I'm doing the thing that's going to make me worse. Because you can sleep when you're dead. Exactly. Yeah, like all these different anecdotes and all these different caricaturizations of rest as opposing improvement. And so in that time where we are doing that thing.
Sure, we might have external contingencies of reinforcement and reward around rest. Like maybe we get to spend time with friends who don't ride bikes. Or maybe we get to hang out with our puppy dogs or just enjoy the fact that we have a nice comfortable bed. But we don't just respond to external contingencies. We constantly respond to our language about what we're doing.
and sometimes that's super productive gets us to do really really hard things well and at other times it can be that the entire time we're in a really comfy bed and we're doing the best thing for us physically we're also talking to ourselves about how the language of the community says we're doing the worst thing for us because you say the language but to me the language is almost like the vehicle for like a peer pressure or you're scrolling Strava and you see everybody else
Going out and doing 20, 30 hour weeks where they ride super hard every day and they're fast and it's like, man, how come I'm not doing that? And so it becomes like keeping up with the Joneses almost. Absolutely. Yeah. And that goes to your part about like really enjoying riding. Like enjoying riding is a combination of like the physical benefits and being outside. Again, the external contingencies of the riding as a behavior.
and the internal discussion about how you're perceiving writing like when you say when when you're out writing you're probably like ha I'm out when this person isn't or you might be like I'm out and I'm hanging out with my friends or I'm out and I'm doing the thing that I identify with strongly as myself.
I am a cyclist therefore I ride bikes and the counter to that the the counter discussion to that is I am a cyclist and I'm not riding bikes right now and and so we have this huge element influencing our experience of how we talk about it and it can be keeping up with the Joneses it can be really reinforcing to be out with our friends it can be really reinforcing to do the behavior that is
A big part of our self-identity. And so every single one of those is also in play when we're trying to rest. Because language is always there when we're awake. And we're only ever one word away from suffering. That's true. The corollary to that is we're only ever one word away from having an amazing time and flourishing.
It's language is so both amazing and weird in that depending on how we talk about things, we could be doing what everybody else looks at and says that's the most amazing thing in the world and we could be talking to ourselves about our experience at that time and absolutely be 100% suffer. Well, so let's talk about a phrase that I think comes up a lot with resting and the language behind this, which is trust the process.
because I think there's a lot behind trusting the process because, you know, especially when I consult with people or I take on new athletes or, you know, this empirical cycling coach takes on a new athlete, you know, somebody has a question and come to me, hey, can you look at this training or I look at the training or whatever happens, you know, sometimes, you know, a lot of the time the process is good and it just needs a couple tweaks, but sometimes the process is not good and needs an overhaul in my estimation anyway.
because whatever you're doing is just, you know, is that actually still the definition of insanity is doing the same thing and expecting a different result? I mean... What a terrible question for you. I'm sorry. Well... It's... What do we say? Knowledge is in action.
And in community action, that saying is widely used, and so many people respond to that as if it's true. Again, my field focuses on behavior. I was going to say, that's a very, yeah. Like, we try, we really, really try, and this is going to sound, I don't know, like kid glove or whatever, but we really try to focus on the individual, qua the individual and their values.
And so they are engaging in whatever behavior they're engaging in now. And they have a history, whatever unique history they have in forming that behavior. And they want to go from where they are to where they're valued, in the direction of their valued outcomes. And so if we can maintain that focus on the individual and their behavior and what we can influence about them, it doesn't...
It doesn't really matter if we call it insane or sane or purple. They just are an individual, and we're going to try and meet them where they are. That's how I coach people. That's how you coach people. That's just how I treat people in general. You are this person, and I'm not going to try to change anybody. I'll try to make them faster, but that's about it.
Yeah, there's a, talking about this idea of like changing, inducing change in others as a coach. Like one of the things in my training, and we've talked about this a little bit, kind of goes into is just because something is uncomfortable doesn't mean it's bad. Like good and bad. Well, that also doesn't mean it's good. Amazing criteria. Right. And so, and so if I can.
aspire to be someone who facilitates engaging in chosen discomfort. That's cool. I like that idea. But if I'm just, as a coach, imposing discomfort because that's how I identify a coach is, that's not cool. One of the oldest phrases that I remember coming up in coaching, I saw it and I'll remember it forever, which is,
Anybody, any idiot can make, can design a workout that'll make somebody hurt. But not everybody can design workouts that make people faster. So, and so when it comes to getting faster, this is obviously, you know, we'll talk about this on another podcast, which would be like, you know, the process of like, you know, let's call it like negotiating, moving up in a bunch in a criteria or something like that. So that's, that can be a long process with some folks and some folks just have it.
When it comes to resting and trusting the process, I think one of the first things that people think is if I rest, I'm going to lose all my improvements. Right. Which you are going to detrain some, but how do we convince somebody that taking a step back is the right thing to do? Right.
So we can assume, we can probably assume, talking about meeting somebody where they are versus making assumptions about people, we can probably assume that athletes that have any kind of significant history in training and competing are going to be responding to a lot of the cultural idioms, the rest is bad, and all the different variants of that.
and if we're going to try and help an athlete pivot to a like process focus kind of manner I mean first what we talked about at the top of the interview which was just like help them start measuring process elements that's that's one of the simplest starting points is measure process elements it both gives you data about is the process actually occurring and what elements of it might be missing and
It can induce some behavioral reactivity in the client as far as they're like, oh, I'm just now aware that I'm only doing this thing here and I'd rather have it here. I'm doing this thing up here and I'd rather have it down here. So step one, measure. Get some behavioral reactivity there. Step two, start using our language as coach. I mean, this is our primary interaction with our clients is language.
to help build a new sport and training related language behavior. And outside of sport in clinical conversations, that's what we're talking about. You know, a client comes into a room and comes in for psychological services and you're going to have a conversation. And that conversation could be very specific or it could be very wide ranging.
Clinician's goal in that moment in every single one of those little moments is to help the individual start talking about their experience in a manner that is going to result in them engaging with their world more effectively relative to their values. And much of that work relies on metaphor. It relies on constructing some
uh relatable experience that brings these what were previously disparate or maybe opposing elements into a different relation uh many different types of relations like greater than less than equivalence you know difference whatever or on the other side taking things that are sitting in this equivalence like this is the same as this and
starting to undermine that relational response. We want our athletes to respond to rest as being equivalent to benefit and getting better and improving. And their cultural environment of sport says that rest is equivalent to getting worse. And so we're going to use our language through metaphors that they can deeply connect with
and through the lens of whatever their personal values are to start reorienting these kind of relational elements such that when they think rest, they aren't thinking my coach told me I have to do this. It's not a coercive response, but it's a much more maintainable response of like, oh, yeah, rest is good. We're going to do this. And I know, you know, there's there's that that does kind of jump a lot of.
A lot of steps, so to say, but that's the ultimate goal. We're trying to get them to rest appropriately, strain appropriately, and engage in behaviors that are going to scaffold a values-oriented performance for many athletes. One of the ways I've done that is by looking at people's data and reading into it.
Typically, I think people sometimes are a little surprised, well probably not surprised, or they're just relieved that I'm confirming what they've been feeling. Because I'll look at their data and say, you haven't had a really good performance since like six months ago, and you've been hammering hard ever since, and you haven't had the same legs as you did in whenever. And this is a reason you need to rest. Right? Right.
And that first part, before you said, and this is the reason you need to rest, what are you effectively doing? I'm just looking at their data, when they had their last peak performances, and typically what happens is they build a lot, build a lot, build a lot, and then something happens, like they get a head cold for a couple days, basically they rest, whether on purpose or by accident, and then they have great performances, and then
So I'm going to interrupt you. What was the first sentence you said when I prompted you with that question? I don't remember. I'm just looking at their data. So I want to highlight what you do. You do it, you've learned it and this is the process, but what you do is what...
I'm talking about earlier, which was a lot of times we just jump right over. But yes, say that again. With measuring, yeah. I measure. There you go. And so we have a lot of... Yeah, that's what power meters are there for. That's what heart rate monitors are there for. But the data always needs interpretation. It can't just be in a vacuum. It's not just like... It has to be actionable, as Tim Cusick always says. Absolutely. And...
Unlike a lot of non-sport related clients that come into a clinical situation and they don't have a major flow of data every single day, athletes are on the other end. They're on a fire hose of data. And so one of the ways that the coach can implement this like behavioral reactivity based on just measuring something is drawing out those
Derivations from the data, those interpretations from the data and being like, hey, when we look at your data like this, what do you see? Or what do I see? And then suddenly they orient to this new way to interpret data and their response reflects that. And we do that a ton as coaches. Without even knowing that we're doing it. We probably don't even notice it. Well, it's sort of like...
just the typical scientific process. It's like, I have a theory. I'm going to go look for data to support the theory, and then we're going to see if it holds. Right. Yeah. And when you start thinking about that process, that look at the data and see what happens as an intervention in and of itself, as a coaching method in and of itself, I would not be surprised if you start looking at data and like, hmm.
How can I communicate what's already being measured in a way that they're not attending to? Because one of the things we do with our language is orient individuals to something in their environment that's there, but they're not attending to it right now. And so for athletes, that's, you know, okay, you're getting all this data and TrainingPeaks or Strava or...
Trainer Road or whatever is orienting you to X, Y, and Z, but I want to orient you to A, B, and C. And when you start thinking about that, your response is different. Yeah. Well, and I think it's also interesting that you note a lot of that kind of stuff because I think this might be where a lot of people second guess themselves is thinking about their own subjective
data and opinion of feelings on their performance versus, oh, the PMC says this, so therefore I have to be in shape. Yep. Oh, yeah. And we talked about this on the last recording of rural government behavior. Yeah, which I see all the time, by the way. So you're saying that you're behaviorally reactive to this now that we've talked about it. Yes, I see it everywhere now.
Yeah, and exactly what you were saying of like if the whole community is telling us that this number is critical, we're going to start responding to this number as critical. And as a coach, we get a special role with an athlete of being able to moderate that loud community voice.
and the community is going to tell our athletes something and our athletes are going to be like I'm not sure about that and so they're going to turn around to us and be like here's this thing that I'm not sure about and we get to provide them with some sort of response that's either going to cohere with the community or argue against the community happens once a week to me and then the challenge yeah the challenge is in crafting that response
Well, let me let me put it this way. How many times have you ever told an athlete that's wrong? Don't do it. And they just lights like light switch. Stop doing that thing. Never. Right. So so the challenge in that opportunity where they say, hey, I think something's weird here is to craft a response in a manner that resonates with them.
And that's the whole metaphor thing or analogy or putting it, providing them some sort of a pathway into experiencing this alternative perspective and orienting to it in a manner that now makes sense to them that the community is not saying makes sense. Yeah. Yeah, that's sort of...
You know, that's the crucial role of coaches, right? It's not, and that's actually what defines a good coaching relationship to me is being able to communicate something when there's a difference of opinion, whether it's between me and an athlete or, you know, well, typically what the athlete says, we need to tweak this nine times out of 10, I'll be like, I agree with you. I hadn't seen that in the data. I hadn't thought about that. You're in your own legs. You're in your own head. You're right about that. These are things that are great. You know, sometimes.
Oh, why does everybody say this? Why does everybody do this? Is this right? Is this wrong? And you have to convince them with data or with science or with whatever that that behavior is suboptimal, let's say. And if you can never convince them, then that's not a great coaching relationship because you are at odds with goals and communication, it seems.
And I'm going to push back a little bit in the way you frame that. And I know this is semantics, but my area of research is light. Well, you've listened to the podcast. You know I'm all about semantics. The pushback is our goal is not to break down the community chatter.
Our goal is not to say they're wrong. To provide context. Our goal is to bring the athletes' responses in alignment with their value direction. And the reason that I make this distinction is the community is saying one very, very specific thing. And if we get an athlete, if we focus on getting an athlete
to a point where they say that specific thing is wrong. Sometimes their behavior is only going to just tick over a half a degree away from that thing. And they're going to be like, look, I'm doing something different. And yet they're still moving almost entirely contrary to their value direction. And so just because we can attack and attempt to
to minimize or zero out this responding in alignment with the community kind of stuff that they're bringing to us does not at all ensure that they're going to move in a direction that's actually going to be beneficial to them because there's infinite other ways for them to do a thing that can be just as destructive or unsustainable. That's fair. And so our goal...
is not so much to argue with the community all the time as it is to orient our clients to a deeply meaningful resonance of like doing this thing is going to move me in a valued manner. So it's almost more like it's not just saying don't do that. It's saying, well, maybe not this, but this instead. So it's not just.
Because we've all seen the people on the internet who just shit on everything. And that's easy to do, honestly. Anybody can tear down a scientific paper or a podcast or whatever. And I'm not immune from it. I've seen people do it to me. And I'm like, actually, that's a fair criticism. I wouldn't have thought of that. But the question is, what do you replace it with? You said it's easy to do. Yeah.
Right, yeah. You said it's easy to do and I just want to point out that there's a philosophical argument that it's actually the easiest thing to do. Really? To criticize. Because every single position, every single claim is singular and there's infinite variation of interpretations, you can compose words in almost an infinite different way of critiquing.
But it's much, much harder to compose words in a manner that gets somebody to do something constructive. So this ties right back to this process versus outcome thing. And that is, as we transition an athlete to process attention, orienting to the process, measuring the process, celebrating in the process,
While the outcome might hold significant meaning for these individuals, it can be counterbalanced by the meaning of the process and in that way individuals can go to competition and nail it on every single process measure and maybe they
Don't even make top 10. But they can stand there and say, okay, here's outcome. Here's process. Nailed it on all the process. I brought my 100% today. And other people brought their 100%. And it turned out their 100% was like outcome-wise higher rank than my 100%. But I brought my 100%. And that orientation towards process can also do something really, really cool.
As you said, a good nuance critic is enthusiastic because they're focused on the process stuff. An athlete that has transitioned into this process focus can be really, really enthusiastic about elements of others' performances even when that performative outcome got ranked higher than that. And start watching world-class athletes.
and you'll start noticing that they are like, you know, in science we talk about it as like they get really geeky, they get really nerdy, they get really excited about these things that you're like, really? But they nerd out with their fellow world-class athletes in a way that makes it so that at the end of the competition they can party with them. They can celebrate each other's process wins and sometimes outcome wins at a
Higher frequency than somebody who's just dominated by outcome. Well, that's one of the hard things about bike racing, too, is that your absolute, just in terms of power output, 100% might be lower than somebody else's and you can still beat them. But a lot of the times, maybe that's not something, even if you bring your 100% process game to the thing. And sometimes, you know, that's hard to handle for somebody like, I did everything right. Why didn't I achieve my goal of like top five?
We talk about realistic goal setting, but there's also skills around how we engage in that. There's all kinds of stuff around self-identity, about responding to things as what we call capital T truth versus lowercase t truth. Yeah, there's a lot of ways that indirectly we can build athletes' skills.
so that they can show up, they can focus on process, they can really celebrate their processes, and the outcomes are, I'm not going to say less meaningful, but they're less dominant in the athlete's experience. Well, that's one of the things I've seen in more pro teams is
The good ones sit down afterwards and say, what went right? What could we have done better? The bad ones sit down and will single out a couple people and be like, you all suck today. As opposed to being constructive and realistic. It's just like, what was wrong with you? Et cetera, et cetera.
Yeah, and that goes right back to our discussion of focusing on those things that we can influence versus those things we can't. If you tell somebody that they suck, okay, it's a serious dig to dig into this idea of, well, what are the elements that I can control that affect whether or not somebody else evaluates me as suck today? Versus if the conversation starts at, what are the elements that we can control that contributed to
Good Performances Today, and what are the elements that we can control that contributed to unfavorable performances today? Yeah, well, I mean, I think that's, isn't that like another coaching trope, too, is, you know, you've got to be a hard ass with everybody, and I don't get the best performances out of them, but I think it's the opposite, isn't it? Man, your face right now. It is a coaching trope, you're totally right, and I'm just like...
Oh God, I hear that so much. And I think that's, I think trope is a really, really good word for that. I tend to use caricature, but, or stereotype. And this is drawing us back to like nuance versus whatever. But yeah, when...
When the way you learned to do whatever it is you do, and if that is coaching, is via stereotypes and tropes, you got a serious learning curve ahead as far as getting better. Because the thing about stereotypes and tropes is something about that produced some minimally acceptable behavior. It did in a movie that one time that we all saw.
And when we're talking about that conversation of like the distinction between proving the community wrong versus orienting the client to a valued direction, that source of punishment, that really aversive, grumbly, nasty coach trope is that proving the community wrong trope.
and for one out of a hundred athletes or one out of ten thousand athletes when we talk about okay they're not doing what the community says they're doing something different it turned out that for that athlete they moved far enough that it contributed to success okay because because the coach said if you do this thing I'm going to beat the living hell out of you mentally or psychologically okay but
The coach didn't orient them to that method that actually got them to success. All the coach did was saying, this particular instance is wrong, do something different. And by chance variability, the different thing produced success. And so that do something different kind of coaching method as a source of punishment, as a source of aversive stimulation.
Yeah, your clients are going to do something different. And if that's all you're grading yourself on, as far as if you're a successful coach or not, cool. Your clients are going to do something different. But... Well, it's sort of like teaching like... It's not going to be... It seems like it's one of those things where you tell somebody, like, no, not that. Then you just let them kind of wander off and be like, oh, not that, not that. You know, that's almost bumper bowling in a way. Yeah. But you might want to say... It's bumper bowling in the dark. The pins are that way.
What about people without coaches? Because I think most of the people who listen to the podcast don't have a coach. And so I think there's two things that I think might be warranted bringing up, which is the downward spiral of, oh, my performances aren't getting better, so I have to train more.
and that leads to more fatigue and that leads to worse performances versus, you know, well, why don't we go into that one first? Well, to get to your initial premise about what about the people who don't have a coach? Nobody doesn't have a coach. Oh, as in the community is the coach. I know that's a double negative. I know that's a double negative. The translation of that is everybody is coached.
Plenty of people coach themselves. Gotcha. And those people who coach themselves fall into either they coach themselves just based off of chance and like contingent learning or they coach themselves based off of like they put in effort and time and investment in developing their coaching.
Self-Coaching Repertoire. Okay. So we found the degree of semantics that annoys me finally. Right here. We got to it. Okay. All right. So we've got self-coached people. All right. Got it. Self-coached. Okay. Now that we found that limit. So, well, then the reframing based on that is we're doing this self-coaching language.
and sometimes that is useful language and sometimes that is not useful language and so if we can for those people who are self-coaching move them into a place where they can say sometimes I'm right and sometimes I'm wrong sometimes I'm helpful and sometimes I'm not and it all comes from a place of interest and care and so the challenge is not listening and doing
The challenge is trying and evaluating based on my valued outcomes. And so sometimes, you know, the self coach is going to say you have to go hard. Okay, I'm going to go hard for a little while. I've taken data on this. Now, let me compare where I am and the progress I've made with where I want to go. Am I moving in that direction? And if the answer is no.
You say, alright, when that language occurs, it's not quite accurate, I want to try something different. Try something different, measure it, evaluate it against values, rinse and repeat. That reminds me of a couple things. First is, I actually think that most people who are self-coached do a pretty good job. And it's a hard thing to do, because when I was self-coached,
Way back in the day before I knew, you know, I pretty much had become an expert before I could coach myself to even a reasonable degree. I sucked at it coaching myself and I got better mostly through coaching other people and, you know, having much more experience that way. But, you know, most people, I think, get to a point where there is some self-doubt about
The process and measurement and being objective. Yep. You got any words of wisdom or little knowledge nuggets for something like that where you're not sure if you can be objective? Well, one is why be objective? I'm going to, this might sound strange, but...
If our goal as coaches is to help clients move in valued directions, a value is a subjective choice. Fair. And so allowing an individual who is self-coached to acknowledge that the directions they choose are subjective and so the method in which they go about it will have a degree of subjectivity always can sometimes take the pressure off.
to like, oh, I'm not being objective. I must be wrong. Nobody's going to be perfectly objective. Okay, that's fair. So let's take that pressure off and then say, okay, what's meaningful to you? What's the direction that you want to work in? Now, let's say in general, maybe we don't have great precision. And I think that might have been where you were going towards is there's going to be a point where our ability to
Precisely measure valued progress may start to weaken, at which case we're like, I don't know whether I've moved in a value direction or not. That's a time to look at what's being measured and try different measurements, or a time to bring in, whether it's just a one-time consultation or an actual professional coach.
Maybe that's self-serving, but we don't live in a society of single individuals. Like, you want to be really, really, really good at something, that means you need to be really, really bad at a lot of things. And you need to collaborate with those people who are really good at those things.
so that you don't fall flat on your face from trying to spread yourself too thin. And so there is a degree to which self-coached individuals can excel and different individuals with different histories will find that gray zone in different places.
Just because you're in that gray zone doesn't guarantee you have to get somebody else, but you might be able to make significant progress by hiring people who have made an intentional effort to get better at helping in that kind of area. Here's something that I can suggest to people to do as well is even if you're self-coached, keep comments on your workouts as if you were talking to a coach. Because what I've done
When I'm either reviewing a new client's history or I'm doing something for a consultation, I look at, I just like, I load up the BKO5 chart on their workout comments and I just read. I don't know what the workout is, I just like scroll right through the comments. And I learn a lot about people that way. And one particular person stands out.
In my mind, because this is the first time that I really did this after Tim Cusick was like, oh yeah, I'll just scroll through comments and see what people talk about. So I did this, and it was hugely informative because this was somebody whose thing was just, I just got a workout every day. I just need to feel like I got in a hard workout. And he was never resting, and so that's why his performance was never improving.
and so that gave me a good in on that kind of thing but maybe one thing people could do is keep comments for a couple months and then just go back and read them because every time I go back and read whatever anything I've written I don't feel like I wrote it anymore you know so absolutely I 100% agree with this and
and one of the prompts when we were talking about doing this episode was when is mental toughness a limiter and this is something that again well another episode is worth of material but in the short one thing that showed up for me when I was thinking about it was it's a limiter when it gets caricaturized as blind persistence when it becomes stereotyped as that kind of a thing and
What came out of that, what I wanted to communicate to others is that reflection is the hard thing. To be tough is to be able to reflect on your own work. And what you're talking about of leave comments, go back after a couple months, reread them, and reflect on what you have done and how it's guided you to here. That's hard. And that's really uncomfortable. But that is some of the
Best that you can do because your comments are a measurement of where you are. It's imprecise but it's still a measurement and so going back and actually look at that data is what's going to cause that behavioral reactivity and it's what's going to really fuel that change and that is one of the most effective ways to see
to evaluate where you were and if it worked from a perspective of now we're down the road. And interestingly enough, I wrote a Training Peaks blog about values, no, not the values clarification one, about daily journals. I have all my clients do daily journals.
I gave it away to anybody who emailed me. I said, anybody that wants these prompts, you can have them. Well, what's your email so people can email you? Patrick at CoachPatrickSmith.com Yeah, you can totally ask for them. I'll continue to share them. But when people were like, well, how do I use this? I told them exactly what you tell them. Keep regular notes. Do it on a daily basis. Respond to these prompts.
And then in a couple of weeks or a couple of months, go back and read through them and do that iteratively. And if you're going to self-coach, this is the best way to take data on what's important to you because you're going to talk about what's important to you, especially if you're treating this as like you're talking to that self-coach identity within yourself. You're talking to your coach.
That's the data that's most meaningful to you. And this week I was talking to a prospective client and they were saying that they weren't leaving comments because their coach wasn't reading them and it didn't matter if they were left or not. And I was like, well, I'm going to make you leave comments or if you don't, I'm going to ask you what's up. Like I'll text you, I'll leave a comment myself and I want to know how it's going because this is invaluable information. And I think that having it,
as somebody who's self-coached is hugely underrated, I think. Yeah. Yeah. And all the same things apply that we've talked about of what gets measured gets managed. If you're using a structured journal, like a set of prompts every single day, if those prompts are asking for things that are going to lead to degradation of behavior, like overtraining, that's going to happen. And so if you're self-coached and you're trying to
explore the most useful journaling prompts sure reach out to us like I'll share my prompts any any day of the week and otherwise really take a moment before either either just add your comments without prompts because that's just gonna whatever's showing up is gonna show up in the comments or take a moment to think about what you're asking yourself
Take a moment to think about what you're measuring of yourself because you're going to start responding to it in a different way. Are you still doing that study, by the way, on elite athletes' daily or the psychological evaluation questions? Yes and no. And there's a lot of inside baseball kind of details about why that project is kind of on ice at the moment.
Part of it has to do with the Beijing Olympic Games. We've had an ongoing discussion with the Olympic and Paralympic Committee, but because they're fully dedicated to servicing the athletes competing in the games right now, we're on hold. And where that goes after the Olympics and Paralympics is yet to be determined.
For the moment, the study is kind of on hold. Okay. Well, that's too bad. Yeah. So where can people find you? They can find me at my email, Patrick, at CoachPatrickSmith.com. My website is also CoachPatrickSmith.com. Yeah. Otherwise, I'm keeping a kind of low profile at the moment because I'm trying to graduate in May. And so I've got...
Serious dissertation work going on behind the scenes. All right. So as always, thank you, Patrick, for coming out to the show. That was a great conversation. It was actually much longer than is published here, about 45 minutes longer. But I really wanted to try to keep it a little tight and a little short.
but we're going to have him back on the podcast again and if you want to hear all of the other stuff that got cut out really kind of heady technical kind of stuff let me know about that and I'm happy to leave it in because that's less editing and less work for me so that would be cool so if you want to get in touch with Patrick again at
CoachPatrickSmith.com is his website and he would be a really good resource for a person to work with if you have any kind of mental stuff that you're working on and especially performance related.
so feel free to get in touch with him and of course I am at empiricalcycling at gmail.com if you have any coaching or consultation inquiries if you want to hire a second set of eyes we are of course available if you want to hire us for coaching we are of course available and Patrick Smith is the same so also on Instagram at empiricalcycling if you want to follow the AMAs up in the stories and yeah we'll keep the plug short see you later everybody