Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore. Thanks everybody for listening as always. And of course, please subscribe to the podcast, but mostly share the podcast, especially if it's helping you out. It's going to help out other folks too. Guarantee that. So if you want to give us a great rating, wherever you listen to podcasts and iTunes, thank you so much for all of those. If you want to donate to the podcast, that's how we keep the lights on and you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. Thank you all for your donations so far. It really helps us out.
And of course, if you want to help the show by becoming an empirical cycling athlete or hiring us for consultation, you can definitely do that too and reach out to me directly at empiricalcycling at gmail.com. We have show notes up on the website. I'm actually going to go try to dig up the references for the papers that we referenced. I know of at least one offhand, but we're probably going to get more.
and of course we have a bunch of questions from the Instagram so if you want to ask a question for future podcasts we're going to do that from now on before we record you can go follow me at Empirical Cycling on Instagram and so thanks all for that and so today
This is a really exciting podcast because this is one of the biggest topics everybody's been asking for is nutrition. And so we have Namrita Brooke on the show and she is the nutritionist I refer everyone to. She is fantastic. You're going to see why we get along in a little bit. You're going to see why I refer people to her. And so this is a great wide-ranging episode. Nominally, we started out...
We wanted to talk about what should you eat on the bike and why and how much, et cetera, et cetera. We do get to all that, but we get to so much more. We get to things like the context of the ride in the day and how you cannot really separate the nutrition on the ride from what you're doing in the rest of the day. We talk about glucose and fructose ratios. We talk about solid versus liquid foods. We talk about different...
products and we talk about, you know, fueling with hydration and all that kind of stuff. So we get to a lot of really good stuff. And so I hope everybody enjoys the podcast as much as I enjoyed recording it. Talking to Namrita is always a real pleasure. And so we're definitely going to be doing more of these in the future. And so without further ado, let's get to the interview and I'll see you on the other side, of course, with some contact info. What was it you just said about there's a lot of experts?
because everyone eats so they for some reason feel like you know they can give nutrition advice based on what works for them so we were just talking about how many questions you got on on Instagram and how everyone just you know always has nutrition questions you can kind of figure out training but yeah I mean I just find it funny that um there's still so much confusion out there and I think it's all these armchair experts that lead to that confusion it's like you know there's
Everyone has a different opinion on what works for them, or sometimes works for them, and then you try it, and you're like, nope, that doesn't work. Now what? Someone else says the exact opposite thing. Try that. Okay, that doesn't work. Yeah, so I see that a lot. Yeah, I mean, I just had one of those debates recently, like last weekend. I was like, if I have a swig at Gatorade, like straight Gatorade mid-ride, like my guts turn into a knot for like an hour. And other people were like,
I don't have that problem. So actually, why is it that some people react strongly to Gatorade and some people don't? Is it the osmolarity? Is it the concentration? Yeah, yeah. So that's kind of the biggest thing. I mean, Gatorade is simple sugars, and so it doesn't have, you know, I mean, I guess technically it has sucrose, so it has glucose and fructose, but the osmolality of that, you know, is...
The more particles in a solution, the more concentrated it is, right? And so if you're drinking too much of it, or if you're drinking a little bit in combination with gels or something else, that's a higher carbohydrate concentration, then what's going to happen is your body has to pull water into the gut to kind of dilute that out to allow it to actually transport across your gut.
Yeah, I mean, I think everyone's threshold for that is probably a little bit different. And that's the other interesting thing about nutrition is it is so individual because everyone's system inside is a little bit different. And that could be based on genetics, it could be based on diet, it could be based on training and fitness status, you know, how long you've been riding and how many have you always been.
is used to taking in a high amount of carbohydrates and Gatorade, so maybe you're better at transporting that. Or maybe you drank a bunch of water before. If you're a little bit dehydrated, it does make stuff worse. So that's also pretty common for why you might react to something that's like simple.
sugars like that. Yeah. Well, that kind of sounds like that training the gut thing, which is, I've always wondered, is that a real thing? Like, and what is the mechanism behind it? I'm wondering if it's like blood flow to the intestines because the intestines, when we are eating, require a huge amount of blood and that can take it away from the legs, right? Sure. Exactly. So part of training the gut, it's actually, there's a few things going on. One, if you are generally already eating a fairly high carbohydrate diet,
And by that, I would say, you know, generally around like eight grams of carbs per kilogram per day is about, you know, on the high end of average to low end of high, if that makes sense. So if you're already eating like that, you're used to taking in exogenous carbs or taking in carbohydrates during your training, your gut transporters for, you know.
the glucose and the other carbohydrates is they're pretty good. Like they're there and they're used to working. You know, when you don't use the machinery in your body, it kind of goes to sleep, right? It doesn't, they downregulate, they go away. But if you are already used to that, so someone who's been training for a very long time with high carbohydrates eats a generally high carb diet.
They don't need to really train their gut. They're already used to that. But the other part of training the gut is also being able to handle the volume.
So gastric emptying is really important. So the stuff, the stuff, the nutrients and the fluid has to go through your stomach before it empties into your small intestine where the absorption takes place. So if it's taking a long time to get through your stomach or it's really uncomfortable, like your stomach feels bloated because you're not used to the volume and the rate of intake.
That makes everything worse. So you want to, that is trainable too. So training your gastric emptying by just like eating bigger meals before training, drinking higher amounts of, or higher rates of fluid during training. So all of that is part of training the gut. And it's uncomfortable. I mean, people are like, well, I don't ever eat or I take in.
you know I might take in like a bar or something for a two-hour ride or you know if it's a ride over two or two and a half hours I'll grab a gel I'm like okay so yes you're far off the recommendations which you know maybe a common one is like 60 to 90 grams of carbs an hour and maybe like 24 ounces of fluid an hour or something so
If you're not anywhere near that, it doesn't make sense for you to just jump into that or like, oh, I heard 120 grams of carbs per hour is where it's at. That's what all the pros are doing. But if you try to do that, you're going to end up in trouble because you haven't trained your stomach to be able to handle that rate of intake. You haven't trained your intestines and your transporters. So stuff is just going to kind of like hang out there and it's going to be uncomfortable. You're going to feel bloated.
can have all sorts of GI issues, really. But so then when they start, they're like, okay, well, I'll train the gut. So I'll do that with training. But you still have to do that somewhat gradually if you're new to this. And at some point, it's going to be uncomfortable. So training after a big meal, it's not as bad for cyclists as it is for runners. That's for sure. Yeah. So, I mean.
It just depends really on you and your history and what your regular diet is like too. If you kind of eat little bits here and there and graze all day, it's going to be harder for you to have a giant breakfast with 200 grams of carbs and then a bunch of fluid, get on the bike, and then trying to start hitting the general recommendations that are out there.
How much of it is like just what you eat? Because I imagine if you have like five Nutri-Grain bars, it's a lot different than having like a bunch of apples or potatoes or something like that. Because when it comes to things like gastric emptying, so we're talking about, you know, like food sitting inside the gut. What affects the gastric emptying rate aside from just kind of getting used to the higher volume of food? Because off the top of my head, I can think of temperature and water content, right?
Yeah, for sure. So the volume of fluid is one thing. So the higher amount or the higher bolus of fluid you're taking in, theoretically, if you're used to it, it should speed up gastric emptying, so it'll move through faster. Can you use this to help food move through? Because I'm not sure entirely, because this is not my area of expertise, and that's why you're here, but isn't it like...
Does fluid and solid food have a different gastric emptying rate even if they're in there at the same time? Yeah, right. So we just made all this really complicated. I'm sorry. I'm thinking back. But in general, fat and fiber will slow down the rate of gastric emptying.
enzymes that start breaking down food in your mouth with your saliva and then like all through your GI tract. So depending, like the more simple the food is before you eat it, the faster that's going to start breaking down. You've also got mechanical digestion and like processing with chewing. So, but yeah, I mean, in general, the heavier the food, so the more fat I would say, the more fiber.
To be honest, I don't know. I guess the protein, like if you're eating protein, it would depend on other things like the fat and fiber too. But I don't know what like the gastic emptying grate of a chicken breast would be. I don't know. Like I wouldn't suggest you eat that anyway. So I guess it's sort of irrelevant right now. But yeah, so.
So if you're eating food, like if you're eating a bar or a gel or whatever, like drinking water with that, a higher volume can help move all of it through. So, you know, you think of like the mechanical digestion, the chemical breakdown that happens in your stomach with all the churning and stuff. It does sort of turn into like a mush, I guess, or like, you know.
Liquidy, semi-solid, so it'll move through faster with the larger volume. But what else affects it? So yeah, that's interesting. Heat, which is relevant right now. It's getting hot, so if heat is a factor in your environment, then, you know, that could slow down gastric emptying, but hopefully you're also increasing your fluid intake to kind of counteract that. Exercise intensity, so you may find that it's easier
to tolerate food, drink, or even like a higher rate at a lower intensity. But when stuff gets hard, we don't have the same blood flow to the gut as you alluded to before. So that kind of also impedes gastric emptying. So those are the main factors, yeah.
Okay, so let's, well, so that was all kind of like heady, like more advanced stuff, but I was kind of fascinated to kind of chase that rabbit hole down. But why don't we get into something a little more simple, because we can kind of build on all that stuff and also get into a couple different avenues for all this stuff.
more than just carbohydrates. Like what time would you want to add a little bit of protein and possibly a little bit of fat, even though, you know, a couple of grams of fat is basically impossible to avoid at some point. Yeah. A long, longer ride. So for some people, generally speaking, if you're competing, let's just look at a race scenario. I would say carbs only up until like maybe a four or six hour race. And then anything at
for that length or longer you can start adding in a little bit of real food whether that's bars or a sandwich or you know kind of whatever again you're able to tolerate still the majority of the intake should be carbs but it's more like some people start to feel hungry or the
all the carbs start to just you know they feel kind of empty inside and so that's also pretty individual do you need the fat and the protein I would say no we have plenty of it in our bodies you know that we use for oxidation at least for fat and as far as protein if in general you are meeting your protein needs you will have sufficient branched chain amino acids to oxidize which are really the only ones that are oxidized for energy purposely
purposefully while you're training or racing. But also, if your carbohydrate intake is adequate, you're not going to need to break down additional protein to make glucose. So what would the gut feeling be like? How would you describe it?
if somebody's like man I'm eating carbs for like my four-hour race but I just I just don't feel good and I still feel even a little hungry or like I'm getting that like that gut kind of yeah so I would describe it more of like a hungry empty feeling and if your race is only four hours like if you start to feel like that around three and a half hours I think you can push through because like if you tell yourself I don't
need that but you know I'm looking forward to eating a huge meal afterwards make sure you're eating enough before your ride too so you know I think a super common mistake for a lot of athletes is they're so focused on like super specific to the gram and like you know do I need do I need to take branched chain amino acids in during my ride because it's over four hours long but
What are you doing? What are you eating before your ride? That's that's really important. So if you if you are one of those riders that ends up feeling hungry, but, you know, it's fine to take stuff in on a training ride. But I'm talking about a race specifically when performance is the goal. The carbs are what is going to fuel that effort and intensity. If you tend to get hungry towards the end of a longer ride or race, eat a big breakfast and eat something that'll.
Stick with you a little bit longer. And then again, honestly, it's not that big a deal to have an energy bar in there. Something that's mostly, again, mostly carbs with a little bit of fat and protein isn't going to disrupt a whole lot. Now, when you're going out for 100 mile races longer, if you're doing bikepacking stuff, yeah, you're going to want some real food. I mean, one, you're not going to meet your overall energy needs in that day with just taking in.
Even 100 grams of carbs per hour. You're not going to meet your protein needs. You're going to feel hungry. You're going to want some regular food. So whether that's, you know, stopping at a gas station or a fast food restaurant or whatever is on your route, it's fine. You just have to make sure that you've also trained like that.
Right. And that's one of the things that we work with specifically with ultra people is, you know, getting the nutrition strategy dialed in and practicing it because otherwise, like you get to race day, it's like, oh, no, I'm in the middle of nowhere and there's only a gas station. What do I get? You know? Yeah. So that's a common problem. I guess the other common problem is I don't really love gels or I train so much with these gels and now I don't want to use that flavor. So I'm going to try something else.
I got this from my sponsor or I got this free in my race bag but you've never tried it like don't do that yeah and then if you know that it's a self-supported ride or race and you physically just can't carry everything you need figure out what's on the route where are you going to stop is it gas stations what time are restaurants open and close like what's available and then train with that too yeah
and so when it comes to how much to eat now this is a really big question for a lot of folks because pretty much universally the guidance that I usually give my athletes is more because whenever I ask them how much did you eat on this ride it's never enough and this goes for you know athletes of all levels including races too so kind of
two things around this. So my first question is kind of academic, but kind of not is why is it that 100 to 120 grams an hour is pretty much universal? Like, why don't we control for the size of the person, like as an upper limit for carbon take recommendation? Yeah, it's super interesting. I mean, I always wondered that too. But it turns out that it's...
it's the capability of the individual and the athlete to we can measure and the intake rate right so we know we don't know exactly how much muscle glycogen you have so the stored carbohydrate but we can obviously measure the exogenous so what you're taking in during and so we can also measure you know with labeling the carbons we can label the exhaled CO2 and we can
figure out what the oxidation rate is. So what is the actual utilization rate of compared to what's been taken in? And I think it really has to do more with training status. So how long have you been training? I'm sure, you know, somewhat genetic too, but you know, what, so one, are you able to get the carbs from your
got into your bloodstream. Then are you able to get the carbs from your bloodstream into your muscle? That's another transport mechanism. And then are you able to actually utilize those specific carbs that you took in through your mouth to produce ATP? And then we can measure that by the expired CO2. So there's no...
Gender and body size are not a factor in that. It's pretty much, I would say, training status and then also exercise intensity. But actually, an interesting paper, I just read it recently, just came out looking at types of, like, different modes of carbohydrates. So gels, chews, I think bars and sports drinks.
It was all identical, right? Yeah, yeah. But they were, again, trained elite male cyclists. They probably have been training with high carbohydrate for a long time. They ate a high carb diet before. So all of the internal machinery is there and working. And they found a pretty high carbohydrate oxidation rate. I can't remember exactly, but it was like...
it was pretty high it was higher than what's normally reported in the literature so they were able to use it now there was another paper and I'm like totally blanking on who wrote it but um or who published it but it was less elite I think it was ultra runners and they gave them 90 or above grams of carbs per hour and their oxidation rates were much lower so they're saying okay well
Perhaps it's because they're not as well trained, perhaps it has to do with running versus cycling, but whatever that is, it's not like they have to take in 90 to 120 grams of carbs per hour because they're not actually utilizing it. They're not oxidizing it to the same rate as an elite male cyclist would. Well, that would be a difference if also power output and energy demand as well, right? Exactly, for sure, yeah.
Okay, so how would your nutrition recommendations for a race, so like stage one of Tour of the Gila is today, and so for a 50-kilogram woman doing that race versus a, let's say 100, I don't know, why not, 100-kilogram man, so how would your recommendation change for them? Because we're going to be looking at a difference between an FTP of like probably 230 to 250 versus an FTP of like well over 400.
Right, so the main thing is general carb recommendations or general macronutrient recommendations are always based on body weight, so by the kilogram. So in general, the female athlete would have a lower absolute carbohydrate intake, assuming we were doing, let's say, 10 grams per kilogram per day.
but if you look at the male who weighs twice as much but maybe his goals aren't the same maybe he's not racing at the front maybe he's just doing a race to finish which probably not in this case but you know his general intake might be lower so yeah like the smaller female cyclist who has a very high training load training you know volume everything
we may be giving her 10 to 12 grams of carbs per kilogram per day where the man we're giving you know eight to eight to ten so so that's the first thing like that's when I really consider body weight is for general recommendations and then when you go to the race itself you also look at okay what are the goals are you doing the race to finish have you trained with 120 grams per hour those are all factors I think about but if everything's the same then I wouldn't change the
the recommendation based on body weight. I would say, okay, both of you for a stage race like this, you know, you want to take in as much as you can, presuming you've trained with it. We know you can utilize it. It helps your performance. You get a head start on recovery and you're not starting the subsequent stage in a depleted state whatsoever. So that would be, you know, pretty much like, you know, like 80 to 120 grams an hour or like whatever you can get in. Yeah. Yeah.
You know, it's interesting you say getting a head start on the recovery because this is something that I think I've tried to impress upon people as well. And some of them don't really buy it. So, you know, you had an actual PhD in this. So I want you to tell people why it gives them a head start on the recovery. Yeah, I mean, I don't really understand why you would think that it doesn't because
Your ride is just a part of your whole day, which is a part of your whole week. It's not this like isolated, you know, your body is the system and it's this is one thing you're doing the whole day. So, yeah, everything you can get in before, during and after really impacts everything else. And especially in stage racing, it's crucial. You know, if you have if you're at the end of like a three week training block and you have a recovery week, you're not going to do anything. OK, it's not.
Super Imperative. I'm not going to lie. You don't have to rush home to eat a bunch of food and then eat every two hours. But if you're doing a stage race, it sure is really important. And I would say definitely a key factor for performance and stage racing.
but yeah so so what's happening is you know you have muscle that can store carbohydrate you have your liver that can store carbohydrate we can store a lot of fat it's I don't know how much but it depends obviously it's something like like 30 to 50,000 kilojoules or something like that for an average athlete yeah it's a ton um but yeah so like carbohydrate is we know I mean you can have your opinions but we know that carbohydrate is is related to performance
directly. So why, you know, if we're limited in how much we can take in per hour based on whatever, you know, mechanisms that limit carbohydrate oxidation, why would we want to also limit or compromise our endogenous or internal carbohydrate stores in our liver or our muscle? Now, it takes a while if you completely deplete them. So if you, you know,
Start fasted or with a small breakfast, you go out on a long ride, you're taking in, you know, 100 calories an hour, which is not enough. And then you're like kind of lax about your recovery regimen. It's no surprise that you're going to feel not as strong the next day. You're probably not going to feel great for the rest of the day. Hopefully you don't have to go to work or anything or like deal with people. But it's, yeah, so.
Constantly making sure that you're staying on top of those glycogen stores is really key. Your whole body uses glucose, your nervous system, your brain, everything. Every cell uses glucose. So I think people forget about that. They're like, oh, well, I'm looking at, you know, kilojoules, like spin it on my training ride. I want to go, like, eat a huge pizza later. Like, I'm not worried about.
they're just thinking like calories sometimes I think or they're thinking I need to lose a few pounds or I'm not really sure to be honest it's I think it's different based on like what drives you right and what your hang-ups are and I have sure encountered all of those situations and the people I coach and the people you coach I'm sure you've encountered pretty much the same things too well because I think what I'm hearing here too that I think is really interesting is that
Part of what your considerations are is the whole day's energy balance. The ride is kind of inextricable from what you're eating on and off the bike. And actually, this is something that has always fascinated me with ultra endurance is you're exercising all day, and so you still have to meet your normal energy needs. And so if you're going to ride for like 12 to 24 hours, you can't just like...
Eat carbs all day, like you said. And so I think that's a fascinating part of this whole thing. Because for a stage race like Hilo right now, if somebody's not eating well enough on day one, it's going to put them on the back foot for day two, and they're really going to be suffering for that last stage.
That's right. And honestly, there's no good way to come back from that. So like my advice is just don't put yourself in that position. Yeah, stuff happens. And but there's only so much you can do to try to recover from that. And again, because we can't just measure our internal glycogen stores, we don't really know. But if if you're really depleted, I mean, and you under fuel for whatever reason.
I would say really try to make sure that the rest of the day you're getting in like 12 grams per kilogram of your body weight of carbs. Like you could, it's a lot. And especially like with a long stage, you don't have a lot of time left after that, but do your best because you can't, you pretty much like can't eat enough at that point. Um, and who knows how much of it's going to make it in right to your, to your muscle. We don't know that.
Because from about having, let's call it, a dire situation would be like 10 to 15% of glycogen stores left, but let's call it even a 30. You've got 30% of your glycogen stores left in your legs and wherever else in your body, liver, nervous system, etc. So the rate of, my impression is, and I think you'll probably confirm me on this, the rate of glycogen repletion is not, you don't get back to 100%.
the next day. Like it'll probably take two to three or even four days to really get there if you're super depleted, right? Yeah. So, right. And so for example, if you're considering like a pre-race carbohydrate loading protocol, if you were for some reason following a low carb diet and then wanting to carb load before, I would say 10 to 12 grams of carbs per kg per day for three to five days leading up to.
leading up to the race. But again, if you are normally eating a generally carb-adequate diet, 8 to 10 grams of carbs per kg per day, you already have somewhat fuller glycogen stores. Again, I have no idea. It just depends on so many factors. But you don't have to carb load for as long, right? Because the rate is...
All the enzymes and again the internal machinery there's all these rate limiting steps so you can't just like eat you know drink a bunch of fruit juice and eat loaves of bread and assume it's all gonna go go go in and work for you the next day so yeah I mean just don't try to not get yourself in that situation take take the recovery as serious as you're taking the stage in the racing and
because, yeah, I mean, that's just wasting so much good training if you're not. It's wasting good training. That is a really, really good way to think about it. It's sad. I feel for people who just mess, you know, mess up their nutrition because they were trying to like not eat too many calories a week before the race because their training was low or they don't subscribe to like.
They're like, oh, I don't need, you know, I'm a really good fat burner, so I don't need that many carbs. And then you see them just like, oh, yeah. Yeah, I mean, even at relatively low intensities, like the amount of carbohydrates they get used is, it's kind of surprising. Right, exactly. And talk about like, we could do a whole podcast on common misconceptions, but. Oh, we will. Yeah, it's, you know, there's no on-off switch. You're always burning some carbs and.
That's why there's always lactate in the blood. Yeah, exactly. Well, so actually that reminds me a little bit before I get to my next actual question. I remember I was coaching somebody through a stage race in Europe and I remember them saying that like, oh my God, I'm eating so much more than my teammates.
And I feel weird about this. And I was like, well, how much are you eating? And they told me, and I was like, I think you're doing the right thing. And they actually had a great performance for that race. So I think one of the things that scares a lot of people, especially for races with climbing, is the body weight. And so the water weight associated with glycogen.
is one of those things that seems to scare a lot of cyclists, especially with like carb loading, because you might gain like a kilo or more in the three or four days, like leading up to a race while you're carb loading. But that's like good weight to have, isn't it? Yeah, that's one of those things that like is hard to convince someone until they've made the mistake. And then they're like, okay, it's better to, and I think there's been studies done on this too. I'm pretty sure.
I can't think of exactly which ones right now, but yeah, like the weight, it's not really a penalty because it's going to serve you very well. If you're starting dehydrated or under fueled, your performance is going to be far worse than if you're carrying a little bit of extra weight, which is going to burn off quickly anyway. You just have to be okay with that like kind of like uncomfortable feeling, you know, leading into it.
that's, I mean, elite marathoners, elite, you know, bike racers, they they're used to that. And so the more you do that, the more it just becomes part of like, not messing with your head on race day. And it just becomes part of your like performance, you know, mindset, I guess. Yeah, well, I remember listening to a bodybuilder talking about
Bulking and cutting phases and just the water weight, you know, at 250 pounds, like the water weight fluctuations of like, you know, five to 10 pounds or more sometimes is, it's incredible, especially, you know, coming out after a show. But like, I think, I think last time I talked to Andy Gallup and he mentioned that when, I think, I forget if he was involved in this study, but he said that there was a study on cross-country runners, I think it was high school or college, and during their taper, their type one fibers actually
actually hypertrophied. Like they got larger, which they did with a biopsy and then looked at the cross section. And that was because they were actually gaining muscle glycogen and associated water. And so the cells were actually just swelling. Right. So fascinating. Yeah. And I've heard of like bodybuilding coaches talk about that too.
When you have that, it actually makes your muscles look bigger. So it's, you know, for fitness competitions and whatever, like, it's actually a good thing. But yeah, I mean, I get it for a cyclist, especially in a climbing race or in, you know, a running race where you, um, the, the common like thought is I want to be as light as possible. It's hard to swallow that. But once you figure out that.
you know your performance is directly related to that or could be worse if you didn't do that then it just kind of makes sense and you just deal with it yeah yeah and I mean I've worked with those athletes and I'm sure you have too where you know they're they're getting lighter and they're like yay this is great but the power output's dropping and it's like
the power-up is dropping more than the weight they're losing in terms of watts per kilo and it's like you were actually a better climber when you were heavier. That's true and it's so good to have a coach you know like you to point that out because there's so many that that aren't and um yeah it's really it's unfortunate but I'm I know because I you know I work with some of your athletes and I I really appreciate that insight from you and like
You're a data person too and you're a reasonable guy. You understand performance and you understand all these things. It really matters. Something like that is so mental for an athlete. If they're constantly thinking they're too heavy, that's just not good. You understand the same things too. I remember when I was looking for a nutritionist to recommend to people, and you're the person I recommend everyone to, to the point where I'm sure you're probably way too busy at this point.
I'm not sorry about that, by the way. But like, you know, it became apparent you had kind of the same overall driving philosophy of performance and just, you know, no fad diets, like all science based. Actually, that reminds me, I've always wanted to ask you, I was going to look this up, but I'd rather just ask you on the podcast. What was your PhD on? Yeah, so I looked at carbohydrate and caffeine and the...
effects on mental and physical fatigue. And then I compared trained athletes with untrained, so just like healthy recreational college students. Yeah, so partially exercise, physically nutrition, partially cognition and in the brain. So really interested in how that all works together. And I think that's also why I really enjoy, you know, a lot of your content because RPE for me and like,
The brain and the brain's involvement and decision-making and pacing and all the stuff, including appetite and what drives performance factors is so important. Data is great, but using it with RPE and being in touch with hunger and thirst and sodium appetite, for example. I know you've heard me talk about that.
We can't just blindly follow guidelines and look at numbers. We have to, our brain is the most powerful controller in the body. So when it comes to performance, like if you're not listening to that, then I think you're just, you're selling yourself short. Yeah. Yeah, that is, I think that's a, I was thinking like, that's a great insight, but it also shouldn't be an insight so much, should it? I know, right?
Yeah, I think that's why your RPE meme was so great. Thank you. It's like, I'm not really a meme person like you, but I was like, this is the best. I love it. I'm not a meme person either, but I made one and people liked it and I made another and people liked it and people were like, do more. And I'm like, all right. And, you know, just secretly just between you and me and the like 10 people who are going to listen to this podcast.
you know it's it's actually great to like get people to follow my Instagram page and that gets people to listen to the podcast and I think that's one of the nice things about it but also I hope to try to like impart a little bit of wisdom with the memes too even though
Every time I post one, somebody's like, well, that's not how it actually works. It's like, I know, I know it's a joke. Actually, I want to ask you one thing about your PhD because, you know, you had said, I hope I don't have to crack out my biochem textbook for this podcast. No, this was like so long ago. Okay. Yeah. But what is, like, how does...
How does caffeine affect carbohydrate utilization? Because if I'm not mistaken, it's been a while since I've thought about this too, it basically creates cyclic AMP, which creates blah, blah, blah, which increases cortisol and catecholamines in the body or something like that. And it increases glucose utilization at rest, right? But does it affect it at performance? That's just by memory. It's been a while. Yeah, to be honest, I don't remember that.
I think there's probably studies that say it does increase carbohydrate oxidation. Again, I think there's so many other factors that could lead to that conclusion. I don't remember that I saw any difference in carbohydrate oxidation between carbohydrate and caffeine versus carbohydrate alone. Interesting. Okay. But it also could have been dependent on the exercise intensity we were using. Again, other factors.
But it did influence fatigue or time to fatigue. It also improved mental performance on a cognitive test following physical fatigue. Interesting. So, yeah, I mean. Well, did it improve or decrease time to fatigue? I would think it would improve, right? Yeah, sorry. Improved, yeah. Okay, yeah, I just wanted to double check. Yeah, increase the time before someone.
was fatigued. And then we had him hop on a computer and do a cognitive performance test. And during the caffeine plus carb trials, they actually did better than the carbohydrate alone, which not super surprising. But yeah, if you're a caffeine responder, there's definitely people who don't use it. And you've probably figured out by now if you're a responder or not.
Everyone I had, and I don't know what the percentages of non-caffeine responders or people who it makes them feel worse, like jittery or perform worse. Oh, that's like a super responder. Yeah, right. Well, if you feel jittery, but if you're not, if you feel like it negatively impacts your performance, then obviously, you know, don't use it. But everyone I had in my study, which I think I had 24.
I mean, everyone was a caffeine responder. So that was pretty cool. Yeah. Well, cause it, cause I would, it sounds like almost like a responder is somebody where like it overclocks your computer a little bit and performance improves and, you know, it generates a little more heat, but it's fine. But like a non-responder is somebody where like it way overclocks and you don't get that extra performance or something. That's what it sounds like. Am I right? Or am I probably wrong on that? Yeah, no, I mean, yes, no, I had an athlete I worked with.
She would eat a caffeinated gel, which, you know, some of them are like 25 to 50 milligrams. She's like, I can't. I can't do it. Wow. Yeah. And then, you know, there's people who, again, you've probably figured it out by now if you've tried coffee because you've heard, you know, coffee and cycling, coffee and science, coffee and everything like goes together, coffee and functioning. And you're like, but it doesn't do that for me. So I don't drink it. So I wouldn't try caffeinated like caffeine.
before an event or during. Yeah, I mean, it's fine. There's other things you can do. If you're a responder, if it works for you, it's a wonderful ergogenic aid. But if it doesn't work for you, then there's no point in trying it. Yeah. Well, I mean, for some people, it's just an aid to just...
wake up and get through the day. I may or may not be on my sixth cup of coffee today, so I'm going to abstain from judgment from anybody, no matter how much you do or don't drink. Okay, so training rides, a little different than a race, right? So like an endurance ride, is there a general recommendation for an endurance ride? And does it change once you get to a certain power output?
So, like, let's say, you know, I, like, let's say I'm going to go out and do an endurance ride, and I've barely ridden my bike in a little bit, so I'm going to do it at, like, 100 watts, so I'm not really going to burn that many kilojoules. Let's say one of my pros goes out, and he'll do, like, 250 watts or more for an endurance ride, so he's burning a ton of kilojoules. So, like, is there functionally a difference in that kind of thing?
for a nutrition recommendation, or is it pretty much going to be about the same? Okay. I kind of, like, got a little bit lost in the example. Oh, sorry. No, it's okay. So, I mean, if you're super untrained and 100 watts is, what percent of your FTP? I don't know, like 50. Yeah, so, I mean, you're burning some carbs, again. You're burning...
Fat. Again, I'm going to go to what did you eat before the ride? What is your purpose? What are you doing the day after? Are you trying to do another endurance ride? Are you trying to do, you know, tempo workout or what? Like, so do you need full glycogen stores? If you eat breakfast before your ride at 100 watts, I think you can get away with, you know.
Depending on how long the ride is, if it's longer than 90 minutes, maybe 30 grams of carbs per hour or something. Because there's no point in just completely depleting everything. You're not going to take in the exact amount that you're expending anyway, so you're still going to be in a deficit.
You don't need to be fasted, I guess, if that's your question. However, is it going to hurt you? Well, if you're going to hop on your bike like once and it's been a while and then you're not probably going to ride again for a couple of weeks, it probably doesn't matter. You can just eat breakfast, go ride, you know, ride super easy and then have a meal afterwards. That is pretty much what I do, actually.
which is fine but if you're trying to do something bigger the next day or you're trying to build if you're now following a training plan and each ride builds upon the next you're going to want more so for an endurance ride because you're still burning a good amount of fat your energy needs are lower than if you're working harder so overall your percentage of fat
oxidized from your body will be higher. Your carbohydrate needs are lower. Still, I would say 30 to 60 grams of carbs per hour is probably fine, even for someone really well-trained who's just doing a ride at 50% of max or 50% of FTP. Actually, it was your example.
If that same rider the next day has a hard workout or a race, then I would say be on the upper end of that, so 60 grams of carbs per hour, and then make sure that you're going home and getting right on your recovery. So your post-ride recovery meal, and you're already thinking about the next day. It's not different from a stage race where you're fueling for the current day and the next day. So yeah, it's always like my answer should just always be it depends.
True scientist. Well, I think it's fascinating because that's a perspective that I have not heard that much. And actually, I haven't really considered that much myself. I mean, like if you, you know, ask me academically, I would say, yeah, yeah, of course, it depends what are you doing the next day. But like, generally speaking, it's not something that I usually consider when it comes to...
How much you should eat on a ride. And I think that's something that a lot of folks probably don't consider as well is what am I doing tomorrow and the next day and the next day? And at what rate approximately does it take me to fully recover my glycogen stores and just generally from the ride? And what do I have coming up? So it's interesting to like, because half of me was like, maybe we can...
Come away with some recommendations just in a vacuum. But also at the same time, it's like you can't really do that and have a really good nutrition plan or training plan at all. Yeah. So here's here's maybe a good takeaway, which is it's not really a recommendation. It's more of just a takeaway. But do you have a performance mindset or do you just have, you know, whatever, like I'm cycling, I, you know.
I'm doing this to burn calories and eat a lot of food after. So, like, if your mindset is, I don't really, I'm not on a training plan, I'm not doing anything to train for performance, I'm fine just, like, tooling around and riding. I mean, you probably don't have a coach at this point, but maybe you do, I don't know. But, yeah, so it probably doesn't matter. But it's still not really helpful.
Like let's say someone's riding their bike for weight loss. So they think, okay, I'm not going to waste my calories on drinking sports drink and eating gels. I'm going to eat like a huge meal and like drink four beers after and like eat chips and, you know, whatever. That happens for people who don't have a performance mindset. They are more coming from like diet culture, like fitness culture, I guess. I don't know.
Like your ride to eat junk and that's right. Right. And so they're just thinking about calories, burning calories and then eating calories later. But then they're like, you know, probably eventually they're like, I don't know, this doesn't feel that great. Or now I really want to do better at cycling, but I need to lose weight and I need to get faster. So I need to get serious about it. And so they contact a coach. They, you know, eventually contact someone like me as well, but for nutrition. But yeah, they're like, oh, so I need to eat like.
Three to four hundred calories an hour, maybe, you know, or eventually or work up to that. That seems crazy. But yeah, like, I mean, you know, your your training plans, you don't just do it's it's rare that you just do like one hard ride and then you sit around for a few days. Each ride will build upon the next. And if you don't take the easy days easy or if you don't.
If you don't fuel a hard day and have another longer day, even if it's an endurance day coming up, why suffer through that? That brings me to another question that's kind of the higher intensity stuff. Let's talk about moderate intensity for a second. Maybe tempo or sweet spot or threshold type rides or maybe a set of openers or something like that.
moderate group ride. So does the recommendation for carbohydrate intake per hour change a little bit or is it still just kind of like, you know, getting what's reasonable for you? Right. So you're burning a little bit more. You're using a little bit more carbohydrate, you know, as the intensity increases.
If you're one of those people that generally for low zone two rides you're pretty much sticking to 30 grams of carbs per hour I would definitely bump that up to 60 maybe a little bit more especially if you're doing you know let's say you're doing like sweet spot ride or over unders or something and then the next day you're doing like two hours of tempo yeah I definitely would be taking in no less than 60 grams of carbs an hour maybe more
because again why not if you can tolerate it you can fuel that effort you can recover from it and then you know when you're off the bike come Sunday night let's say you know you've done two big rides you hit all your numbers you felt good your your RPE was like where it should be you slept well then you can just like fuel your body with really good healthy food and you know it's
That's part of it too. Again, we're not just counting carbs. Off the bike, you have to make sure that you're getting your nutrient and your energy needs met. Recovery is not just about restoring glycogen. It's about all those other things that are happening in your body that require energy. Again, getting a head start on that recovery is part of it.
The higher your weekly TSS, you know, the more you're training, like the more I would say you need to be taking in per hour as you can tolerate it. And so what about the very hardest rides? So like VO2 max, maybe like some FRC, like some one minute hill wrap, something like that. So like, let's say somebody was going to go out and do, you know, 10 by one minute all out hills with like 10 minute rests.
going to be basically impossible to eat without vomiting something up for a lot of people doing something like that. So is it better to like front load or is it better to like get in there with your stomach feeling okay than you can eat afterwards if you got to ride more after that? So what would your recommendation be? Yeah, probably that. So I would say making sure you're starting out hydrated and with full carb stores. So leading up to that ride, whatever you did the day before, you know, make sure that you're okay.
If you're doing like typically a VO2 ride like that, you know, it's either going to be a pretty small percentage of the ride or it's just going to be a short ride that you knock out. So for that, like you can just fuel for that ahead of time. Have full glycogen stores. You don't need to worry about like the time is another factor. Right. So like for for anything that's super.
Short and intense, time trial, cyclocross, whatever, like you don't need to take anything in during it as long as you're starting out hydrated and, you know, with full glycogen stores. You had a good big carb breakfast before, your liver glycogen's full, your muscle glycogen's full, your blood glucose is good, you know, it's not...
So those are the main factors for that. And then I would say like if you're doing VO2 intervals at the start of your ride and then you're going to ride for a couple hours, then you can start fueling more after that. So maybe, you know, 60 grams of carbs an hour. If you're one of those people that, again, has a pretty high training load and you're constantly doing four to six hour rides, then yes, most of your rides are probably going to be 90 grams of carbs or more per hour.
Um, but that's not everyone. So again, it really just depends on, again, like, what are you, what are you eating regularly? Are you meeting your carb needs on a regular basis? Yeah, that makes sense. Cause I had, I had actually written down a very tongue in cheek question for you that I was, I'm not going to ask you in seriousness, but now telling you that I was going to ask you as, as kind of a joke. Um, it was going to be, um,
Once you burn more than 400 kilojoules an hour, do you have to eat 100 grams of carbs an hour? Yeah, so right. I mean, I think we've covered that. But the answer is no. And also it depends. So, yeah. So, okay. Carbohydrate distribution in terms of glucose and fructose and glucose-like carbs and fructose-like carbs that use the same transporters.
So just generally glucose fructose. So like sucrose is one to one glucose and fructose. They are stuck together with what is an alpha one four bond or something. I don't quote me on that. It's been a while. But what is the recommendation for glucose like maltodextrin, just change of glucose or like, you know.
Sucrose, like, you know, people can just put sugar in a bottle and use that. So what is the recommendation for the, like, right ratio and when do you have to start adding some fructose or really thinking about that? Because can you really eat 120 grams of just straight glucose an hour and have it be effective? No, no. So when straight glucose was tested...
The upper limit of carbohydrate oxidation was like a gram per minute. And so that's how they arrived at that 60 grams of carbs per hour. So more than that, if you're trying to get 90 grams of carbs an hour, that's when, you know, the recommendation is to take in multiple transportable carbs. So simple carbohydrates that use different transporters to get across the gut lining. So you can actually absorb them and then...
Measure them in the expired gases so you know that they've been actually oxidized and utilized for energy. As far as the ratio, so I think earlier on it was like 2 to 1 and now I think there's been some more research that suggests that a ratio of like 1 to 0.8 is more tolerable for people from a GI standpoint.
Glucose to fructose, right? Glucose to fructose or maltodextrin to fructose, yeah. And so sucrose would count in that, right? In terms of being like one-to-one? Yeah, sucrose is one-to-one, but here's where it gets a little bit more complicated. So if you're going 60 to 90 grams of carbs an hour, yeah, that might be okay for you. However, the osmolality again, I'll...
We'll go to that. So the smaller particles, the simple sugars are more particles in solution to achieve that carbohydrate amount. But if you're using something like maltodextrin or clustered dextrin, it's bigger particles and not as few. So the osmolality can be actually lower with a higher carbohydrate amount. So like scratch super fuel, for example, has 150 grams.
An osmolality of like 150, I think. Our plasma is 280 to 290. So it's hypotonic. Not as concentrated as our blood and plasma. Right. But it has a lot of carbs. It has 100 grams of carbs. But it's in a ratio of like, I think it is 1 to 0.8, I think, of multidextrin, or sorry, cluster dextrin to fructose. So it's not going to...
upset your GI. You're not going to draw that extra fluid in to dilute it, basically. So that's kind of the other issue when it comes to, it's not just the ratio of one carb to the other, it's the concentration and how much are you trying to take in. Yeah, and this is actually something that I want to do a whole other podcast on, is like concentration of drinks and using...
like liquids to fuel. Um, but you know, this is actually something, one of the questions that I got a couple of times when I asked on Instagram, um, you know, we're going to talk about nutrition. What do you want to know about ride fuel? And a lot of the questions were, um, is solid food better or is liquid carbs better? Or like, do you compromise hydration by doing this, that, and the other thing? And so this is part of the equation, right? Especially in terms of like hydration and gut comfort, right? Yes, very much so. It's, um,
so gels I think gel introducing gels and really sugar like simple sugar sucrose based drinks is where people really start to get messed up because one if both of those are really hyper tonic so like more concentrated than than plasma so again you're you know you've got to wait your body's got to wait to pull in
water from your body that dehydrates you, that slows gastric emptying. You got this stuff just like sitting there waiting to be pushed through your gut lining into your circulation. But in that meantime, you're just not feeling good. So if it's fine to use gels, that's such another misconception that gels are not good to use. You have to drink the right fluid with it. So you want to drink water to dilute that out.
And it's quite a lot of water. It's like way more than you expect. It's nearly half a bottle, right? Yeah, it can be. Again, it depends. Whatever works for you, right? Yeah, it depends on your intensity. It depends on how hydrated you are. It depends on the heat. But yeah, so it depends on all those other factors too.
In general, I would say try to find, if you're trying to get calories from your drink, it's totally fine. I hate when people are shamed for drinking sports drinks, but it happens. But yeah, choose something that's hypotonic. So it will empty through and be absorbed in your circulation faster.
It facilitates hydration and it also facilitates nutrient transport across your gut lining. So if you want to use gels, figure out how much... I also would avoid... There's so many products now that have amino acids added and tons of electrolytes. All of that contributes to osmolality. It's not just the carbohydrate type and concentration. So it's all those particles that affect the osmotic pressure.
so simple products and you know I how do you know what those are well they're not releasing osmolality for most products scratch is great because they do but most drink companies won't give you the osmolality but it's trial and error it's figuring out okay yeah I can't use those gels I don't like using that particular brand or the super salty ones especially with my drink you know it's like
That's all part of the trial and error. Yeah, so a lot of it is just, you know, kind of start with the basic recommendations and figure out what works for you, right? Yeah, and those may change for the conditions too. So making sure that now as the weather is finally getting warm for people, at least where we are, it's what works for you in colder weather. You know, you may find that it doesn't work for you as well in the heat. So, okay.
Try drinking more fluid. Not necessarily more concentrated fluid, but more fluid to hydrate you, like water or something hypotonic. Yeah, because I always find that in the winter I can take just a regular bottle with scratch in it, but in the summer I have to reduce the amount of scratch I put into a bottle and add extra salt.
Like that, that works for me, but, and that's, that's something that I had to learn over the course of many years. So, um, and that's not something that works for anybody else or, you know, a lot of other people that have recommended, oh, you should try this. A lot of them come back and like, that was terrible. I'm like, all right, then don't do it. Right. Yeah. And, and that's completely fine. Again, like that's, that's kind of the problem with, um,
Nutrition companies and supplement companies giving these recommendations and like sponsored athletes walking around saying this is what this is the best thing to use. Well, OK, if it actually is what you're using, it may work for you, but it's not going to work for everyone. And I think that's where a lot of the confusion comes in. And, you know, just knowing that you have to like shop around and like buy a bunch of different things and see what works in what conditions. And once you find it.
Stick with it. Yeah, I mean, it's amazing the amount of...
because I was really like this as a teenager where I would really look up at somebody and I was like, all right, what is this person eating? What are they wearing? How much do they sleep at night? How much coffee do they drink? I have to do all these things and I will have their powers. Right when I got into cycling, I did the same thing with Tom Bonin and Johan Museu and I was like, oh my God, these guys are so fast. I want to be like that.
I read some of the training sessions and I did that and they did not work for me. Right. Yeah. And that reminds me of your FTP meme too. Like, you know, if you're detrained, like, no, this is what my FTP used to be. This is what I'm going to train at. And like, you're just not going to have success or this is what, you know, you think you can hold, but no, like be, you are an individual. And I think part of tapping into you, like your individual,
performance capabilities is recognizing that and like working with with your body and your physiology and and maybe in time probably you know you stick with it long enough your your training age increases your experience increases all that machinery has upregulated over time you know with all the adaptations from training and nutrition and diet and and all of a sudden you're a different athlete and
Patience is always rewarded in cycling, right? It really is. And that's, you know, I can't tell you the number of people I've consulted with where, you know, that is pretty much the recommendation for, you know, that's one of the things I tell people, like, if you're going to consult with me, you know, we're not going to write you a training plan because...
I don't know how things are going to change, and I don't know exactly what you need, but that's something that has to be figured out. So I try to give people the tools to figure out what works, and I think that's actually what I like so much about you, among many other things, is that you're always trying to work on what's best for this person. Every time I see you...
interacting with one of my clients because they've got working with you for the nutrition. It's always like, okay, try this, try this, try this, try this. It's not like this is what you should do. It's like you give a long list of things to try. Yeah. Yeah. Because everyone, everyone's different. You can try to like push a plan on someone or a recommendation. And I mean, you and I both know that's not going to work. Yeah. And I think, you know, the reason
We we have success with athletes and have successful athletes and have great relationships with them is because they trust us because we understand and we listen to them. And it's not I always draw so many parallels with training and nutrition. It's not, you know, it's not it's not that different. It's all part of the same system. So, yeah.
All right. So do you want to take some questions from the Instagrams? Let's do it. Yeah. All right. So I got a ton. So thank you all for submitting. I will be doing that from now on at Empirical Cycling. By the way, Marita, where can people find you on Instagram? Because you've got a really, really good account with another nutritionist. I love following your stuff there. Yeah, thank you.
So my good friend and colleague, Kelly Pritchett, she's in Washington. We joined forces because we were so frustrated with like, not just, I mean, just like bad advice out there. And like, you know, people charging a lot of money for like, really general recommendations and steering people down the wrong path. So we're like, let's start like a simple endurance athlete, focused, evidence based, easy to understand. Both of us really
care about like translational science, like applied science. So how, okay, that research paper is great, but how do I apply that? So it's called Inside Sports Nutrition on Instagram. I mean, I'm personally on Instagram too, but all I post is like my dogs now and my baby. Your dogs are great. You've got GSPs and that's, I'm all about it. So if you're interested in that, you can follow me, but you're probably more interested in Inside Sports Nutrition.
I wish I could post as much as you do. We've talked about doing like weekend AMAs too, but I'm going to send them to you. I'm going to send them to Inside Sports Nutrition. I'm going to, I'm going to, um, I'm actually going to suggest you do that there and I will send people your way. Cause, um, you know, cause again, like they can ask you all the questions that they asked me. Uh, cause what I have to do right now is I have to kind of call these down to a couple of really good ones. And so I think the first one that I got that, um, that I think actually all
meld a bunch of questions into one. Sorry if I'm not going to answer somebody's specific question, but here it is paraphrased. What do you think would be a good candy for ride fuel? Because I know a lot of people use Haribo.
Over a certain amount, I always get a lot of farts with Haribo. So, you know, are there other similar things that are pretty good? Or is that like pretty much the good, like cheap gold standard? You know, it's super common, like Haribo and Swedish fish. But to be honest, I'm not a candy expert in like the breakdown of glucose versus fructose and in those.
They're probably all pretty much the same. I think what might be happening is, yes, you're eating a lot of concentrated sugars, and if you're not drinking enough fluids with that, or getting enough sodium, so try maybe the salted version too, the gummy bears. That's another thing that also influences transportation of the...
Carbohydrates, you know, through the gut lining, like you need the sodium glucose transporter. So you need sodium. Yeah, so I don't know that like the type of candy really makes a difference. I would try drinking a little bit more and making sure you're getting enough sodium. All right. Okay, so here's one from a professional mountain biker. How the hell do I fit 100 grams of carbs per hour into my pockets for a four-hour ride or race? So that's a situation where I would...
use carbs in your drink. I don't know what you're drinking. If you're drinking water or noon or something, try even like regular scratch. It has some carbs. It's not a ton. So you still have to eat a bunch to get that. But if you try something like scratch super fuel, you know, that gives you a hundred grams of carbs. Depending on the type of racing you're doing, you could wear a hydration pack. Sometimes, you know, if it works with your bike fit and
For endurance races especially, it can be really convenient. And again, it's kind of like we talked about carb loading before, like the weight penalty so you can actually get your nutrition and hydration is inconsequential. I mean, it's more important that you're fueled and hydrated throughout a mountain bike race versus like, you know. Yeah, it's going to be hard to eat that much of just solid food if that's what you're trying to do. Yeah. Or use gels and drink water and see if that works. Yeah, so.
So as much water as you can and maybe like just pockets full of, you know, 80 grams gels, something like that. Yeah, I am. Yeah, it does kind of get difficult. Like, you know, especially I know that this particular athlete, there are.
you know a lot of the pro mountain bikers that they're racing with get a lot of support and sometimes these pro mountain bikers that don't you know they can't bring somebody to hang out in a feed zone or like ride between different feed zones for these super long like marathon races like you know they're limited to like whatever they can carry.
Yeah, it's true. There's some really streamlined hydration packs now. They're not like the big clunky ones that they used to be. So that's something you can consider. You can wear it really close to your body. Still stay somewhat aero, you know, whatever that means for mountain biking. But yeah, like taping gels to your top tube. The chews and bars and stuff, it's just really hard to get enough, especially like...
in a technical course. And that's another thing. Like if you can stay on top of your hydration and you have some carbs in there too with a pack, you don't have to worry about finding a safe place to, you know, to take in fuel without crashing. Yeah. Okay. All right. Here's another good one I like.
Is there a difference between eating a bar quickly versus nibbling it over an hour? So like if you're supposed to get like, let's say 60 to 80 grams an hour, if you have it all at once versus spreading it out, is there a benefit or a drawback? So that generally I would think of as like a gastric emptying type of question. So again, like we talked about with fluid, the bigger bolus of fluid, the faster gastric emptying will be. As far as a bar,
I mean, again, if you're going pretty low intensity, it probably doesn't matter if you're really hungry and now's a great time to eat, you know, you're pulled over on the side of the trail or road and you want to eat a bar, it's probably fine. If you're racing, I would take the approach of making sure I'm staying on top of my hydration. That's really what's going to, you know, push gastric emptying, increase that rate.
Every time you have a chance to have a bite of your bar, whether it's a bite every 10 minutes or, you know, just half a bar and then another half later, I would say that's probably better for a race scenario versus just like a bunch of solid food in your stomach at high intensity at once. All right. Okay. So here's another one. I'm not going to ask this exact question, but I'll ask something that's going to make a more general point, which is if somebody is going to wake up early in the morning.
and do a really intense ride because that's the only time they can train. Like you're up at 5 o'clock and you're on the bike at 520. What's a good way to fuel for that ride, you know, knowing that it's going to need some carbohydrates? Yeah, this is a really common one. So the day before, making sure that you fuel during your ride.
and or like recovered after it. And so you had your carbs after. So basically, my point is you're not coming into this early morning ride with compromised glycogen stores. It's better rather than eating right when you get up and hopping on the bike 20 minutes later. I would say grab some water, you know, grab some some fluid and then eat right before you get on the bike or as you start warming up. So within five minutes of the start.
Because if you eat 20 minutes before that 520 a.m. ride, your blood glucose is going to go up, your insulin is going to go up, and it's still going to be elevated when you hop on the bike. And you may experience what's called rebound hypoglycemia. So your insulin is still high, you know, which you need the insulin at rest to get the glucose out of the bloodstream into the muscle. But then you start pedaling too, and your muscle starts taking up glucose again.
from the blood through non-insulin dependent mechanisms. So you're now all of a sudden in a hypoglycemic state and you have low blood sugar. So to avoid that, it just doesn't feel good. It doesn't necessarily like impact your performance, but if you've ever just felt like kind of like, oh, at the beginning of a ride, that could be why. So I would say, you know, get up, drink, do whatever you do to get dressed.
As soon as you're about to hop on the bike, either grab a bar or a gel, some sports drink, start pedaling. And depending on the ride, you said it was intense, so I would take in another, so I would take in 30 grams of carbs right when you start, and then I would take in 30 grams of carbs 20 to, I don't know, yeah, 20 minutes later. That is fantastic. I think we could probably do an entire hour on just talking about morning rides.
But I think that's a great recommendation just in general. All right. So here's one. So when it comes to more natural carbohydrates, you know, like apples or potatoes or stuff like that versus more processed stuff, what is the...
Is it an overriding thing to think about with that kind of stuff in terms of just whether it's going to be good nutrition? Because I think you had mentioned something about fiber content would affect this, but also I'm thinking water content probably affects it to some degree, but also how does this affect the guts processing or is it more just one of those things of the osmolality once it gets in there is going to be the biggest thing?
You don't tolerate the gut comfort. Is it all the same? Yeah. So I think it depends on what carbohydrate amount you're trying to achieve per hour. If you're trying to get 60 to 100 grams of carbs an hour, eating fruit, eating, you know, apples is not going to be the best way to be able to fit all that food in to get the carbs. So that's the first thing I would think about. Also.
Again, if you're doing an intense workout, blood flow is compromised again to the gut. So you want the easier, I guess, more processed carbs, right? Versus less processed. So I know tons of people love eating potatoes on the bike, which, you know, they taste really good. They're cheap. They're high carb. But again,
A potato doesn't have, you think about like for a large potato, you might be getting 28 or 30 grams of carbs. It's not really from a performance fueling standpoint, it's not enough and you're just, you can't eat enough. So, so I would save those carbs for your meals before and after the ride throughout the day. That's a great time to really focus on complex carbs, high nutrient, high fiber carbs to meet all your other nutrient needs.
Your gut health needs, you know, everything throughout the day. But again, if performance fueling is your goal, I would do it with bars, drinks, chews, gels. Yeah, I think that's interesting because every time I eat like a potato, I am super full.
for like two hours and then I am starving because it's just, you know, it's like super filling and then it's not enough calories in general. And it's even worse if I add like eggs to it or something. Oh my God. Right. Yeah. But then like, you know, there's some endurance races that at aid stations, they have like salted boiled potatoes and it's the best thing ever. So that's like something that.
you can look forward to and you can have but it wouldn't be like the cornerstone of my fueling strategy so I am all for eating as many fruits and vegetables as you can but like I think that's how I would structure your normal daily diet which again is super important for performance and fueling but the time and place for those like convenience foods and sports nutrition products is
during your training rides. All right. Okay. So just a couple more. So how would you readjust nutrition based on glycemic index or is this even worth looking at? Yeah, it's sort of similar to my previous answer. In general, I think a lower glycemic load is better. And I'm not going to just say glycemic index because you can eat a high glycemic index food like rice.
but combine it with coconut curry sauce or something or chicken, so protein and fat to lower the glycemic load so your blood glucose doesn't go up as fast. But right, so like in the early morning fueling example, five minutes before is a good time to have something that is a higher glycemic.
Index. So a banana, a gel, whatever, because it's going to go into your bloodstream faster and contribute to, and then like by then your muscle starts contracting and starts taking up the glucose. So, you know, you're utilizing it versus eating a high glycemic meal 20 minutes before, spiking, if you could see my.
fingers are spiking blood glucose, insulin, and then it tanking as soon as you start. Right. So, so before a ride, I would say lower glycemic index or load right before and during the ride, higher glycemic is good. Okay, cool. All right. So this is just a very general question. So when making your own ride nutrition or looking at the nutrition facts that like
Is there a certain amount of carbohydrates or fats that you would probably try to avoid in terms of like grams per serving or like per like, let's say 20 to 40 grams of carbs? Would you try to limit it to like two to four grams of fat and protein for that ratio? Or should it be just like zero optimally? No, that's fine. I mean, I don't really like pay too much attention to that. I guess what I would pay attention to more is what are the ingredients of the bar?
versus a nut bar or a nut butter bar. I would pick something that is more predominantly oats and fruit. So, you know, like more carbohydrate based. And yes, like what binds it together might be nut butter, but that's not like like a Laura bar, for example. Or like a Cliff bar is a great example of a higher carbohydrate bar that still has a little bit of fat and protein, which I don't really count that. But then you have some of these lower.
carb bars that are more like, you know, lots of nuts and seeds and stuff. Yeah, like egg whites. Yeah. I've had those and they're great if you're not working out, but I couldn't imagine eating them in a workout. Yeah. Right. So that's kind of what I would look at more. Like what are the ingredients versus like the specific grams of carbs and fat? Well, I look at the specific grams of carbs, sorry. I don't really pay attention to the fat and protein as much as I would like what are the main ingredients.
I was going to say something else about that. Okay. Well, collect your thoughts and I'll ask you one last question. And I got a couple of people asking about this. So a bunch of people are asking about Martin, M-A-R-T-E-N. Is that how you say it? Martin? Martin. Basically just, you know, is it actually God's gift to nutrition?
is pretty much what everybody's asking. Is that just marketing stuff? Yeah, so I will say that most people I know who have used it like it, but the hydrogel, like the verdict is still out on it. I will say for a high carbohydrate rate of intake, like if you're trying to get 120 grams of...
of carbs per hour. The idea is that like the carbohydrate is kind of protected. So it's not going to, it's going to go through your GI tract faster because it's protected in this hydrogel. And then, you know, not impact the, be like hyperosmolar and make you dehydrated and all that. So that's the idea behind it. I don't think there's any like convincing research that improves performance necessarily versus
a non-hydrogel carb, but there is one paper I can think of where I think it was female cross-country skiers, I don't remember if it was only females or females and males, but they took in 120 grams of carbs an hour, Nordic skiing, you know, high intensity of the hydrogel, and their carbohydrate oxidation rates were high, they performed well.
and they didn't have GI distress which is kind of like the main takeaway for me is like okay can you take it if you're trying to get in that amount of carbohydrate intake can you take that in with using Gatorade and gels if not can you take it in using Morton and you know you might have a better time tolerating it at lower intake rates if you're trying to take in 30 to 60 grams of carbs for an hour I don't think it would really make that much of a difference I think that
The Game Changer might be, you know, at the higher rates. It might be more tolerable for some people. I don't know. Have you seen any more research on that? I haven't been, like, following it because I wasn't blown away by it. But from an anecdotal perspective, most athletes I work with who use it have enjoyed it and liked it.
I actually look at very little nutrition research because I have about 400 papers that I have on my little docket of things to read. And so I'm just never going to get to that area of the literature. And that's why we have experts like you on the podcast so that I can ask all the dumb questions that I've always wondered about. And then you can tell me what's... They do a fantastic job with marketing. They sponsor a bunch of really successful athletes. And so I am, you know...
I think you always have to be kind of like aware of that but just knowing like if I'm thinking about the science behind the hydrogel versus you know when you're thinking about osmolality and gastric emptying and all those things we're talking about it kind of makes sense that it would help at a higher intake rate whereas you know more particles other forms of carbs may not be as tolerable so that like it kind of makes sense to me but I don't see how it would be any more beneficial at a lower intake rate.
I don't use it. And I, again, I have some people who do and some people who are completely fine using scratch super fuel. So it just depends. Yeah. Pretty much everybody I coach who has those high oxidation rates, they've either found gels that work for them or they found a combination of like gels and candy or whatever and scratch super fuel. That's pretty much the majority of folks. Yeah.
Alright Namrita thank you so much for coming on where can people find you? So Instagram I guess is probably you know the easiest way to find me inside sports nutrition again I also coach nutrition with Velocious and Basecamp so Basecamp is an off season or off yeah off season training program so I coach nutrition there and then my colleague Kelly and I are
Planning on doing a two-part webinar series in June, specifically on evidence-based practical sports nutrition strategies for endurance athletes. So you can find out more about that at Inside Sports Nutrition. And then, yeah, I mean, if you work with Coley and, you know, are interested in nutrition, then they can reach me through you. What's your email address if people want to reach directly to you for, like, a nutrition consult or nutrition coaching?
Yeah, it's namritabrook at gmail.com. That's B-R-O-O-K-E. Yeah. Mm-hmm. And, oh, you kind of glazed over this, but Velocious is the coaching company that Tim Cusick and his wife run. That's right. And so if you have watched any of the WKO5 webinars besides mine, you've probably watched one of Tim's because he's done like 90% of them.
and Tim coaches Amber Nieben. And so Tim really knows his stuff and Tim has assembled a really, really good group of folks. And that was one of the reasons that I reached out to you initially. I was like, oh my God. Yeah, that's how we connected. Yeah, I was like, oh, Tim works with her. She must know her stuff. I gotta see if she really does. And like, oh my God, do you ever. So thank you so much for coming on. And I cannot wait to have you back on again. So if any folks want to suggest topics, I have a whole bunch for Namrita, but if there's anything specific.
Thank you, it was fun.
All right. So again, Namrita, thank you so much for coming on to the podcast. That was a great time. I had a great time. I hope you all had a great time listening. And of course, if you want to get in touch with her directly, that is again, Namrita Brooke at gmail.com. And that is the same on Instagram. And she is a nutrition coach. She's a regular cycling coach. She is involved in collegiate cycling. So I want to talk to her about that at some point. And of course, Inside Sports and Nutrition on Instagram, really, really, really good follow with her colleague, Kelly Pritchett.
and of course me as usual you know Empirical Cycling and that's on Instagram and also at gmail.com for emails for coaching inquiries and consultation inquiries and all the usual stuff and of course if you want to support the podcast with a donation thank you all so much helps keep the lights on you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate we've got links to everybody's everything up in the show notes and so you can check that out of course empiricalcycling.com up in the podcast episodes and so I think that's going to be about it for today
And I can't wait for the next one So thanks again everybody for listening See you next time