Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore, and I want to thank everybody for listening as always. I want to ask that you subscribe to the podcast and also share it on forums or with friends or whatever if you think that there's some good information in here. iTunes ratings and ratings wherever you listen to podcasts are wonderful, especially if they're five stars, if I may be so bold. And also remember that we're an ad-free podcast, so if you'd like to donate to the show, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We also have these show notes up on the website. There aren't any for this episode, though.
we also have merch at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com and if you have any coaching and consultation inquiries questions and comments you can please email empiricalcycling at gmail.com and also don't forget in the Instagram empiricalcycling in the stories weekend AMAs so give me a follow if you want to participate in that or you can just read
So today, I'm starting a new series. Well, it's not really interviewing. Obviously, I'm not a good interviewer, and I wouldn't want to sully the name of the good trade of interviewing people and the journalists and everyone else who does that kind of thing well. That's obviously not me. So this is just conversations. I have a little bit of a roadmap for these, and we're going to touch on some points. But otherwise, it is completely free-roaming.
And the reason that I'm starting this series is because I've been told by several people that some of the conversations that I've had with other training folks, coaches, scientists, researchers, that these are interesting, which I certainly always think is true, but would potentially be good podcasts. So we're going to start to do that. I have a couple guests lined up.
The first guest that we have today is Alex Carmona. Now, Alex is a coach at Empirical Cycling, and so I'm sure some of you listening to this are coached by him already, and you already know everything that I'm about to say to be very true, which is that Alex is a great coach, but he's also really fast. He's been racing for a long time. He's been coaching for a couple years.
and he's also been coaching himself for a little while too and so I thought it would be really interesting to kind of have a you know a broader talk with Alex because I've never actually chatted we talk about you know coaching other people all the time but we haven't talked about him coaching himself so this is going to be a little bit more focused on that so we get into that a little bit and so I hope that this is interesting to people to have this kind of you know
So I hope that this is enjoyable and I hope that everybody enjoys listening to these kinds of things. So if you do like that kind of stuff, you can let me know. You can shoot me an email. Also, if you have any coaching inquiries for me or Alex or our third coach, Fabiano, who is also excellent, by the way, just shoot me an email, empiricalcyclingatgmail.com, also for consultation.
inquiries as well. And without further ado, let us get right to the interview. Actually, one more ado. So we had a problem with the audio file, so I've cleaned it up as best as possible. And I apologize for that off the bat. So I cleaned it up as best I could. So the background noise on Alex's channel is going to come in and out. And occasionally, if he and I are back and forth a little bit, you are going to hear me delayed.
about a second and a little quieter, and that's embedded in the audio file, and I did the best I could to clean it up, so I apologize for that. You know, all the audio engineering skills in the world, can't really fix that, but I think that the interview was really good, and we wouldn't be able to do it as good the second time, so apologies again for the audio. Hopefully, it's pretty minimal, so hopefully it's not too distracting.
Now without further ado, let's get into it. Why don't you tell the story about how you got started in cycling and kind of how you eventually became a coach with me here at Empirical Cycling. So I started being coached in 2013 by Steve Weller, his company is Bell Lab Coaching. Yeah, I was racing with a bunch of guys, they were all being coached by him. They're like, oh, you got to work with Steve, blah, blah, blah. So I was like, okay, sure. Like, I want to coach.
So I worked with him, I really enjoyed the relationship I built with him and the way he did things and yeah, really liked that experience and I think it kind of left me feeling, you know, I really enjoyed this and I would love to be able to mentor other cyclists kind of the same way he did for me. So it was actually a funny thing that had been coming more and more into my mind as I had, you know, like gone from, you know.
Cat 3 to Cat 1 and felt a bit more experienced. I was like, you know, I'd like to maybe be able to offer that to other people at some point. Well, let me ask you, like, what was it about your experience with him that you really enjoyed specifically that made you think, I want to pass this on to other people? Yeah. Gosh, what was it exactly? I mean...
He was just a really down-to-earth, nice guy, you know, and I felt like I could talk to him and tell him what was going on, and, you know, he just got it. He understood he had been through the stuff I was going through, so just that kind of support, you know, and this kind of tough thing you're pushing through, that really, that helped. I really appreciate it so much, you know, and so, yeah, I really wanted to be able to do that for other people.
I would say that's the biggest thing. Yeah, just that kind of, that buddy in your corner, that like friend, friendly, you know, relationship really just meant a lot. Yep. Yeah. And so that led you to wanting to, you know, be a coach yourself. And I think you would actually, you would sign up to be a coach with him briefly, right? Because I remember you having a business card.
yeah so yeah so funny enough like I had been kind of thinking about coaching more and more and then kind of out of nowhere he reaches out to me and is like hey man you ever thought about coaching like would you want to coach for me and I'm like dude yes like holy shit of course so yeah so I mean you know we kind of
began this process of having me coach for him. And, you know, honestly, I don't know exactly what happened, if it was a bit on my part or his part, but it just didn't really kind of come to fruition like I think we both thought it would. And, you know, so, yeah, so that kind of, I guess, went nowhere. And then I took, like, you know, a year off basically from racing.
Kind of give myself a break for the first time in five years of, you know, uh, you know, catting up and just, uh, just going, going full bore with racing. So I took a break and then, um, uh, totally missed racing and training hard and all that stuff. And I was like, you know what, this is like in my blood. This is what I love. Like, I'm going to keep doing this. So started training again. And then, you know, um,
Bunch of guys I raced with, they were working with you now, and you were this big coach and stuff, and I'm like, okay, Cole is onto something here, so I was in, I think, Columbia at the time, doing some of my own training, and I was like, you know, if I'm coming back and I want to really do this right, why not start working with a coach again, and kind of...
wanted I guess a fresh perspective or something different something new just try something else so I was like hey what the hell like reach out to Koli and see see what he thinks about coaching me and stuff and then kind of the same time I was like you know he's coaching a bunch of my friends and like you know I don't know his deal but you know I know Koli and he's a nice guy like what the hell like I'll just say hey man like you know want to ever think of taking on assistant coach and then I just you know I just threw it out there for shits and then
I was like, holy shit. He said, yeah. Cause I can tell that you've got that thing of, you know, cause like I've known you for a while before that and you've always been like the nicest guy anybody's ever met. Oh man. And, and like, not only that, but like, you know, you were like a selfless racer, even though, you know, kind of want to take your own opportunities and stuff. And, uh, and I was like,
Yeah, I think Alex actually has like the right personality to be a coach. And also, you know, you've got this deep history of training. And you've, you know, and I was like, I think I remember I said something like, I want to train you for a little while, just so you kind of get the hang of it. So what was the big difference between like training with training with Bell Lap and training with me?
Oh God, I don't upset anyone here. You won't upset me, don't worry. Are you or Steve? I mean, I don't know. I just, I have immense respect for you and for Steve and for, you know, I guess coaches in general and stuff. And, you know, everyone has their approach and their experience, you know, and I respect that. But, you know, I think, yeah, I mean, the biggest thing I noticed is like...
You're like, hey man, we're going to do this really intense block of VO2 max work. And I was like, oh, okay, I've done VO2, I'm into that. And I'm like, sure, let's go. And then you're like, I don't know. And then yeah, you threw me into it and I was like, holy shit, this is intense.
So I think the kind of more, I think this is a word, specificity. Sometimes I use that word and I'm like, is that a word? I'm like, yeah, that's a word. Specificness. Yeah, I think the specificness, the specificity of your program and what you were signing and stuff, that was the biggest difference to me. And I think, you know, that really, I think, yeah, showed the biggest results, you know, like.
We want to improve FTP. Well, let's go hard with FTP. And we did. And man, that was huge for me. And I saw the results and I'm like, ah, you know, I kind of wish I had been doing this for a bit longer. Especially, you know, I think once you get to, you know, for athletes who've been training for so long, right? Like they need something new, you know, and they need to push harder than they put in pushing before. And that can be, I think, challenging.
So I think I was definitely there. I've been coached for a long time. I've been training for a long time, doing a lot of the same stuff. It's time for something new to push through the next level, and I feel like you did a great job with that. Wow, thank you. I just want everybody listening to know that we did not plan that out. It just happened to be. I didn't know where that question was going to go. But I appreciate it, man. Thank you. Totally. I think that's actually one of the things.
that does make a really big difference when somebody is well-trained is it's not only the specificity, it's the overload in specificity. And I think that, you know, you've found even working with people who are relatively new, who, you know, not like right off the couch, but who are pretty well-trained can handle the training load. I think, you know, in you and your athletes, you've seen the results that that kind of thing can get, even if somebody's not, you know, really well-trained and needs a change of program.
Totally. Definitely. Yep. Well, so what's like, what do you think is probably the easiest thing that you've found as a coach? So what's, what's like your favorite stuff about it? And what's the worst about it? Don't name names. We're going to keep everybody anonymous. Oh my God. What's the best about it? You know, I think, yeah, I think honestly it's, I think a big part is kind of was talking about.
With my coaching experience being coached, it's just that kind of one-on-one talking with people, supporting them, and hearing their experience with training or whatever, and offering kind of support and saying, hey, you know, like, yeah, you didn't do as well as you want to do, whatever.
But like, you know, let's look at this aspect of this aspect or like, you know, you know, just kind of offer my perspective on it. And yeah, I like just kind of be able to do that, have those kind of Yeah, it's a lot of talking about what happens off the bike as much as on the bike, right? Exactly. Yeah. Like, I mean, I think at times, I'm like, I feel like I'm more of like a bike therapist than a, you know, coach.
Every coach is like that. I usually tell people, like, you know, grown men all the time tell me that they cried. And I'm like, I get it. I've been there. I've done that. You know, I've quit bike racing five times when I've gotten dropped from the Cat 4 road race. Then I get back to the car and I'm like, I'm going to train harder, damn it. I've done the same shit. Well, I mean, yeah, that's the stuff I kind of love, just being supportive and hearing people out. Yeah, and you've had a tough time, too, in your coaching, I think, because...
Half of it has been when there's basically no racing. Yeah. You know, I've, you know, it just kind of all happened all of a sudden, you know, and I kind of realized that I'm like, Oh my God, like no one's including myself has raced in like a year. And I'm like, you know, yeah, that's been not as, I don't say not as easy, but it's been definitely different. You know, when you have events, races, whatever going on, I mean, you know, um,
that gives helps to give a lot more focus you know to what you're doing but without that kind of main focus and drive it's like well you know you gotta people are gonna want to keep riding and training but that gets that can get tiresome in itself and has its own issues you know so kind of helping I think people have needed a little bit more support and also you know I think more off the bike time you know a little bit more easy time because I mean we just it's unrealistic or unreasonable to expect people just keep
Trying to, you know, or training and grinding and pushing and pushing, you know, it's just like, that's not going to necessarily work for everyone either. So it's been definitely figuring out a balance, I think. No, I completely agree with you on that. And that's one of the things that I found is, you know, without racing, I was like, oh, we've got this vast ocean in front of us. And like, we don't, we can't see any islands to steer towards. Right. And, you know, usually having a race or something like that, it's like, okay, now I've got a marker for
this season, and now I can work backwards from this marker and I can fill in everything I need to. And then, you know, without that, it's like, well, what are we doing? Okay. How do we build fitness with no specific goals in sight? Yeah, it's been hard. And people, you know, some people just want to push and push and push until either they cry uncle or I tell them to stop. You've done the same. Yeah.
Exactly, yeah, I think, you know, for a lot of my athletes, or I think, like, there was a good, like, December was, like, a very, like, okay, you've been training all year, you know, like, you gotta chill, which I feel like usually comes, but I feel like, I don't know, I thought it was maybe more important this year to really give that mental break, I mean, biking and training aside, I mean, it's just a rough year, right, for everyone
One of the things that I think that I started appreciating this year that I didn't as much before was that mental fatigue is real fatigue. And it'll affect you on the bike as much as anything else. Yeah, exactly. Yep. And so I didn't train you for that long, actually. We've had a lot of discussions on training, but then you went and you were like...
I'm going to take this opportunity to train myself. And you and I have actually never talked about that. So I want to talk to you about that right now. So what's it been like training yourself? And this might be some insight into other self-coached athletes who are listening, because I know there's a lot who listen. Yeah. What has it been like training myself?
I mean, I like it. I'll say that. I like, you know, I really enjoyed having that structure that like, hey, you got to do this to this day and that's just what you got to do. You know, that really helped me, I think, stick to the training, progress, etc. You know, at this point, I don't want to say I'm beyond that, but I think I have a good, I've developed a good intuition with training, you know, so I don't, I know I can.
I know what I need to do. I don't want to say I know everything, but I know for the most part what I need to do, how much or little I can rest. So I feel like it's nice to have that flexibility of being able to train the days that work best for my life to train.
and then rest when it makes sense to as well. That kind of flexibility, I really, that's probably my favorite part of just coaching myself. Yeah, it's not only like intervals by RPE, but it's like a whole program by RPE almost. That's a great way of putting that. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, exactly. I've found the same thing myself.
Today I know like, oh, I didn't sleep well last night. My sprints are going to be garbage today. So I'm going to buckle down on getting to bed at a normal time, which I've sucked at for most of the last year. And yeah, tomorrow's going to be better. And it is. And it's like, part of me is like, I lost today. But this is also the same thing that I do with my athletes too. And you do with your athletes. Somebody's like, I had a bad day. I didn't do the ride. Or they text you like...
Should I ride today? The answer is no, or warm up and give it a shot. Like, how bad was your day? Yeah, same stuff. I mean, that's also one of the things that I knew that you were going to be really good at. Like, when you asked me to come be a coach, and I was like, yeah, I know that you've got the sympathy and the empathy, but you also know when to push people. You can tell what somebody's talking about. Yeah, exactly.
I think also coaching myself was helpful with that, you know, because you kind of, you know, I'm like, I like that in flexibility and I want other, you know, I would like my athletes to feel like they have a flexibility as well and that they don't, you know, they're not going to die or lose all their fitness if they don't train this one day and that things can be moved around and accommodated for, you know what I mean? I think often athletes are like, is it okay if we push this a day or switch this around? I'm like...
Totally. Like, that is totally fine. Like, it's going to be okay. And, you know, you have to be able to have your life because I think, you know, I think just generally that's just a huge lesson I've learned is like if you don't build in that space, you know, mentally and in your life for other parts other than bike racing, right? Like, you're going to burn out. You're going to not want to do this long term. And I think for me, you know, my goal is to like build.
healthy, strong, long-term cyclists and bike racers. Yeah, I mean, I think you're doing a great job, personally. I would tell you if you weren't. Probably not on the podcast, but I want to also ask, what kind of guinea pig stuff have you done to yourself with training? Because I do guinea pig myself all the time, and that's part of the reason that I have a hard time with my own training consistency, is that
I push myself really hard. I'm the only athlete that I've ever really overtrained. I took a very long time off the bike. So what have you done to yourself where you go, I don't know if this is going to work, but I'm the only one who's going to suffer from it. Yeah. You know, I almost don't want to say some of this stuff because I'm like, don't do this, even though I did it. I'll just give it a general outline.
General Outline. No, I think probably the biggest offense or the biggest thing I did is, and I think I've talked to you about this a bit, is, you know, messing around with fasted training and, you know, kind of happened almost on accident, but it got to a point where I was like, I'm basically training almost all the time or, you know, at least during the week when I'm training before work, you know, I'm riding fasted and I can put out.
really good numbers. It got to a point where I was like testing, doing FTP tests fasted. And I was like, and I set new PR that way. And I was like, well, this works for me, you know? Did you do anything harder than FTP fasted and have good numbers with it? Because usually typically studies, well, here's the thing is like, as long as you're eating carbs the rest of the day, like, you know, your glycogen stores are still topped up, you know? Yeah. Yep.
I have to go back and look at everything but I mean it was you know I was basically doing everything all my training fasted I'd say for at least you know maybe a two-year period but you know I I didn't do it a thing where I was like I'm gonna you know train fast this day with x workout you know and maybe that one does include really you know intense intervals or like that
over FTP and then do the same workout with eating. I should have done that. We should also put it out on the podcast that you eat a...
I think the scientific term is a metric shit fuckton of carbs. Yes. Like the number of bananas that you bring to the house for a stage race is legendary. Like you can clear out a grocery store of bananas. Yes. Yes. Okay. And I think that's, yeah, that's also worth touching on is like my diet is very high in carbohydrates. So I think.
It just worked naturally for me because I'm never skimping on the carbs. I feel like I'm always topping up, right? Are you eating on the bike during these rides or how long do they usually go fasted? Yeah. Or like on no breakfast, we should say. On no breakfast, yeah. Only with coffee. Yeah, you know, I mean, usually it was like two, maybe two and a half hours at the most and I wouldn't eat anything on the bike. You know, I would get home and then like have immediately like a big smoothie.
stuff like that. Yeah. But longer than that, how did you find? Yeah. Yeah. So I, I did do a few, yeah, I did do a few long rides, totally fasted. I've only done a few, maybe like, you know, less than five. And I think the longest was around five hours, no food before, no food during, you know.
And I don't, I, you know, honestly, I don't know if I would ever do that again. You know, it was like fun. It was an interesting experiment more to saying, hey, can I do this? You know, can my body do this? And yeah, it could. It was, it was, it did it. I'm alive. But I don't, you know, I can't really speak to it being really beneficial or what it really did for me other than just giving me, you know, having done it. Yeah. I mean, I find.
That kind of training, like I'll do like low carb stuff with people sometimes. And I've done a lot of low carb with a very small handful of athletes. And we'll talk about some of the next couple of upcoming podcast episodes we'll be getting at some of the effects of that. But I rarely, rarely have people do fasted rides. And I usually find actually that people who have to wake up at like 5 a.m. and they have to get on the bike by 5.30 or they're going to be late for work.
They usually they actually do need to eat something and it seems to some people are good at that and some people are not good at that. So do you have athletes who are in the same boat as that? You know, actually, I believe I only have I have one athlete who does the fasted riding. It's, you know, from everything he's told me, it sounds basically the same thing that I did. And he's had fine results with it.
And, you know, I think if it's a harder workout or a longer workout, you know, he'll eat stuff and take in calories. But I think he's similar in that he's like, you know, vegetarian, vegan, eats a lot of high carb foods, you know, so I think that it works for him as it kind of worked for me. Right, yeah. Okay, so in the vein of self-coaching, what have you found are like the plus sides and the downsides?
like accountability and objectivity. Cause you know, you've, you've asked me advice, like, what do I do with athlete X, but you haven't said, what do I do with myself? Like you have not come to me for advice on that. Um, so like, so what, uh, so I have not been giving you any objectivity on your own training. So like, what do you find coaching yourself? Um, you know, it's kind of the effects of that. Like it does work well. Does it not work well? Like, are you pretty well self-motivated? Yeah. I mean,
I think if you're coaching yourself, it really helps if you have good self-discipline, which I would say I do, and that's not a super hard thing for me, or it never has been. So I think really the biggest thing is just writing out a plan like I would for any of my athletes and saying, okay, these are the events, these are the goals, this is the timeline, et cetera, et cetera, and just filling it in, and then just sticking to that plan. And I find it much easier to stick to if the guesswork is sticking out, I have it written out.
Yeah, that makes it a lot easier to stick to. Yeah, I mean, that was one of the things that I've found with self-coached people when I do consultations is either they don't give the plan enough time to work.
or, you know, they're also like not sure what to put in the plan. And, you know, I think you actually have an advantage in that way because, you know, you've been a coached athlete for such a long time that you kind of know the routine. And as a coach of other people, you know, you have, you know, like 20 to 50 times the amount of programming experience as like the average self-coached athlete does just coaching themselves, you know. So I actually...
Just had this thought now, like, what would you say about the idea of, like, if anybody out there is, like, coaching yourself and you have a friend that's coaching themselves, like, getting the two heads together and talking about each other's training plans and, you know, because that also sounds like it might create more problems than it would solve. Yeah, I think it could go either way in that, like, you know, if the people are decently informed, like, kind of comparing.
results or methodology might be helpful, but everyone's different. So it might not, and it might just lead to more confusion and worse outcomes. So I don't know about that. No, I actually think you're right on that. Okay. So have you had any insights into training and coaching that you think
Man, I think this is, like, I have a unique perspective where, like, I never would have learned this before if I weren't, like, coaching other people and myself. Yeah, I think something that's become more clear to me, and this is kind of a cliche saying, but, like, you know, know thyself. How so? Or, yeah, I think, you know, understanding your...
Limits or, I guess, your weaknesses, things that you don't do well, and then intentionally trying to improve those things. You know, figuring out what you do well, what you don't do well, and what needs to happen, what needs to be done better to get to the outcome that you want. So are you speaking on the bike or off the bike? Like general training philosophy?
Yeah, I'd say everything. I'd say it all. Training philosophy, if you're a bike racer, your racing tactics, your race craft, stuff like that. Like I said, figuring out what you're good at. I think it's interesting you say that because I find that there's two ways to coach folks. And one is...
You know, people who really want to like work on their weaknesses. Like so somebody's not like a great tactical thinker, you know, I'll say go watch YouTube videos of crits and like how they set up for the sprint or like how they set up for a breakaway or like, you know, also, you know.
With the Know Thyself, like, do you have the watts to establish your breakaway? Like, if you have a 600-watt sprint and, you know, you're in a men's field and a crit, like, you may not be able to get separation. So you've got to, like, you know, you've got to, like, follow an attack or coax somebody, you know, give them a gel to attack or something like that, get you out of there. Exactly. You know, developing that kind of thing. So, like, you know.
like leaning into your weaknesses but also like leaning away from them because I know a lot of people for instance I coach a lot of people and I know a lot of people and so do you who don't like crits because of the constant you know you know silly stuff of like danger to your life and limb and bike and things like that just kidding they're not silly but like that's why people don't want to do that that's why they want to be in road races and then
You get into the road races, and there's varying degrees of mindset for that kind of stuff, I think. And so there's a lot of people, I think, also who just get into road racing who, like, just want races of attrition, you know? And I think I've talked to a lot of people where, until I vocalize that to them, they haven't realized, like, oh, that's exactly how I want... I just want the rest of the field to melt away. Like, I don't want to have to be involved in RG Bargy. I don't want to have to attack, stuff like that.
Yeah, I think so. It's like, you know, I guess not so much like know thyself, but it's this process of like knowing yourself, I guess. So just kind of being aware of things and trying to get a better feel of, or I guess what I'm trying to say, just having that focus inward, you know, and...
Having that be in your mind. So, you know, I think after a while of racing and training, you know, some patterns will appear, right? Like, you know, yeah, if you're getting dropped from road races all the time or like certain outcomes are happening, you know, pay attention to those outcomes and think about what they mean, you know, maybe for getting dropped from, you know, road races, you know, maybe you need to work on your FTP or drop a few pounds, whatever.
But unless you're not keeping, you know, paying attention to those things, you're not going to really progress. And I think, you know, if I can use myself, for example, I think I thought if I rode hard and showed up to races every weekend, I would just get better at them. And that didn't happen, you know, to a point that worked. And then, you know, you get to cat two and that's just not going to work. That's just not going to work. Already done that. Exactly. And so for me, it was really like, okay.
I gotta understand these races better, I gotta understand the courses better, I gotta understand who I'm racing against better. You know, I had to really just really examine and reflect on what's gonna change the result I'm looking for here, what's gonna get me to where I want, you know, I can't just show up and expect the same results, you know, so I think unless you're trying to be aware of those things and look for those patterns.
and then be intentional about changing your behavior or whatever you're doing, then you're not going to continue to progress. Yeah, I think that's a very elegant way to put...
What I've been doing very crudely with people where I say, like, you only have so many cards to play. How are you going to play them in this scenario? Like, what's your winning scenario? And then let's work backwards. So it really does require a good analysis of somebody's skill set and also their mindset. Like, do you want to be in a bunch sprint? No? Okay. Let's take all these options off the table then. Right. Exactly. Yeah, exactly. And if I could just for a moment, to all the bike racers out there, if I could just impart some knowledge.
Do the extra legwork. If you want to do it on a race, it's only these rare freaks that just show up and ride away and win. You're not going to do that. Don't try to do that. Don't think you're going to do that. Study the courses. Study who you're racing against. Know as much as you can before going to the race. And that will do...
a lot for you. That's my little trick, little secret nugget of information there. I agree with you completely. I mean, one of the things that I tell people a lot is, especially newer folks in racing, the more experienced folks, I don't hear this nearly as much, but newer folks in racing are always looking at the course. Like, oh, the course is going to do this, course is going to do that, so how should I pace this or that? And it's like, well,
It depends on what the rest of the people are doing. Because they are going to dictate the race more than the course unless you're all alone or unless it's a really, really obvious thing like the 20-minute climb at Hilltown. You've got to make that selection and then you can decide what happens in the race. But even that climb is still, you know, there's still some tactics on it. Yeah, for sure. And I think that's a good example too. Like, okay, there's going to be a climb here.
Then you got to make sure you're at the front of the group going to that climb, you know? And I think that's the difference of just showing up and like being like, okay, whatever happens in the race happens. Just, you know, the race is going to go away from you and you're going to be left in the dust. So, yeah, there are a certain amount of things in your control and you should try to control them as best you can, but also, you know, seize opportunities and whatnot. Yeah, exactly.
I forgot to follow up with you on this, which is, you know, what are the downsides of coaching yourself that you found? Yeah, the downsides. You know, I think especially with this year with COVID or, you know, lack of races and events to keep focus, you know, I think I've kind of just, you know, I was doing some structured and focused training and
doing some of those kind of like experimental workout things on myself and seeing what how that what results came from that and stuff. But, you know, at a point I was just kind of like, you know, I don't I'm just going to like ride my bike because I like riding. And I think I think that can, you know, I think mentally for me, that's been good. But I think also like, you know, training wise, that time could have maybe used a bit more constructively. So I think sometimes that kind of total flexibility, freedom, you know, if you're not careful, can lead to just, you know.
A lack of progression or focus in training. It kind of relates that too. I think if you are getting coached by someone else or following someone else's plan, you're going to be doing stuff that you didn't think of. Even if you're the best coach ever, there's more information out there. There's other methods, ideas, ways of looking at things. Oh, totally. You're missing out on that, and I think that can be really important.
Well, actually, let me ask you a pointed question then, because my answer to this is yes. How often has your training been influenced by, like, Instagram or, you know, popular articles and whatnot? Oh, God. You know, not...
That much? You know, I think... Oh, you don't spend as much time on Instagram as I do, I think. I mean, I'm on Instagram. Maybe I'd say more like Strava, honestly. You know, I see people putting in big days or doing certain stuff. And I'm like, ah, like, I got to do that. You know, why am I not doing that? You know, that's what gets me a bit more, you know, especially if you follow pros and like the shit they do. It's just like, oh, man, I'm...
I suck. I'm not training at all. I only rode 30 miles today and this person's riding like over 100 and therefore, yeah. Anything else in your mind that you want to touch on? I think just the thing I've learned or I'd say an important thing that I've learned just not just with bike racing but life in general and I was actually talking to somebody whom, a friend of mine who I'm actually going to start coaching the other day was just like, you know,
mentors are like so useful and helpful and important in life you know and if you're able to kind of have that relationship it's yeah it's extremely helpful if you're trying to get better at anything you know and so I think with as a coach you know that's essentially what I'm offering like I'm
I've done things and gained certain knowledge that I'm going to use to help people who don't have as much experience as I do, you know, reach certain goals. And part of that is, you know, offering a different point of view. And so I just, I guess, yeah, I think, I guess in short, what I'm sort of trying to say is, you know, get a coach. But like, I just think, I mean, whether you're trying to get be a better bike racer or like,
you know learn a craft or a skill or whatever you know it's just like this is a really
is a great thing to be able to do and like for sure you can learn on your own and try to figure stuff out but like just having someone else to help you along is invaluable and those conversations, the relationship you build in that is I think worth it in itself so you know I would say for anyone just even if it's someone you know who's stronger than you that you talk to sometimes or like an older rider that you like maybe get good information from you know like seek out those relationships.
or you know if you're able to get a coach you know get a coach and work with them and see what you can learn and pick up and I think you know that's to me that's just been a hugely positive and rewarding experience being coached myself and then now being able to coach other people.
All right, that's our show. Thank you, Alex, for coming on. I really enjoyed this. I have a great time with Alex. I learn something every time I talk to him. So if you learned something and you really enjoyed listening to this, please share the podcast with someone. That is the best thing that you can do to support us if you are in the mood to support us. We love that. Thank you. Also, if you want to support us by donating, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate because we are ad-free. Of course, we don't have any show notes here.
We've got merch, again, empiricalcyclingpodcast.bredless.com And if you have any coaching or consultation, inquiries, questions, and comments, if you want to work with me, if you want to work with Alex, or if you want to work with Fabiano, please send us an email, empiricalcyclingatgmail.com And with that, we will see you all soon.