Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm Kolie Moore, but I'm not your host. Kyle Helson is going to be hosting today with 10-minute tips on bro science. If you would be so kind as to go into iTunes and give us a nice rating and a comment or two would be awesome. And you can also support the podcast at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. And for all coaching and consultation, inquiries, questions, comments, please email empiricalcycling at gmail.com. Here's Kyle. Hey, everyone. I'm your host, Kyle Helson.
I'm all by myself tonight. Cole's got the night off. And today I'm going to be chatting with you all about bro science. Shout out to Don Mazzetti. Love those videos. And some tips to help you avoid falling for these very common dubious claims made in the exercise, the sports and fitness industries. I remember the first time I ever heard some quote unquote advice that even to a relatively naive person like I was sounded
really kind of ridiculous. My freshman year of high school, I was like 14 at the time, I was introduced to lifting weights while I was playing on the high school football team. One time in the gym after school, I heard a teacher who I would see there a lot and who I actually had for freshman econ casually remarked to me saying, you know, if you want bigger muscles, you'll lift more reps. And if you want firmer muscles, you lift heavier weights. I don't.
I don't know why this story sticks in my head so much, but it really does. And I think it's a particularly good example of bro science because most often bro science has some tiny core of truth that has been wrapped up in a big ball of crap and makes some sort of absolute claim that isn't true or really shouldn't be made or is, you know, kind of iffy at best.
The idea if you want bigger muscles, i.e. hypertrophy, research recently shows that the classic hypertrophy rep range, which is 6 to 15 reps per set, shows only slightly better results in terms of muscle mass gained than rep ranges that are higher or lower given similar total intensities.
a great example from the cycling world is that if you quote if you want to go fast in the spring and summer you have to spend months riding in the little ring in the winter now there are plenty of benefits to lots of off-season zone 2 base miles like we talked about in episode 7 what is base really but that doesn't mean it's the only way to get fast and it also doesn't really mean that it's what works best for everyone like
You could imagine someone who is particularly limited on training time if they only have six hours a week to train, you know, and that's two days a week maybe and a long ride on the weekends. Like in the wintertime, if they're just going to do those six hours a week in zone two, they're really not going to be developing enough aerobic stress to really get faster like they want to do. They're so limited on time, they're going to have to up the intensity.
and telling them to just do six hours a week in Zone 2 isn't going to really get them very far. This kind of goes to show a couple examples of bro science and you can kind of tell that bro science makes a lot of either emotional arguments, arguments from authority or absolute claims and as Cole often likes to say
The true sign that someone is an expert about something is that the answer that they gave when you ask a complicated question is always, well, it depends. And in this case, if it's, oh, you always have to ride in the little ring, oh, you always have to lift four sets of ten or whatever, always, always, always, they're making these absolute claims that probably aren't true.
Recently, with the rise of, I think, social media and the more sophisticated sports science and sports research that has gone on, a lot of these bro science claims have become a little bit more believable and probably therefore more likely to get, quote unquote, more people to fall for them. So, a lot of times, this more sophisticated bro science has some sort of scientific backing, be that a paper or two.
that are highlighted as being the reason that you should follow this methodology or buy this supplement or something like that. And especially with supplements, nothing could be more dubious than a study or even a few studies on the efficacy of a supplement that are funded by that supplements manufacturer. Like their whole point is to show that this is good. And so they're going to go out and try to find some study that will show that it works and that you should buy it and you should give them money.
The other thing is lots of supplements like to take those studies and then slap university tested on the side of advertisements. You're like, great, lots of things are university tested. That doesn't necessarily mean it's good or helpful or useful. You know, lots of placebos. Placebos are used in almost every drug or supplement study all of the time. And those, you could argue, placebos are university tested. But does that mean they're effective? Well, no.
This goes to say that no science in any field, biology, chemistry, physics, engineering, you name it, material science, what have you, should be believed based on just one study or experiment. And this is a critical part of the scientific method, is that these results must be repeatable by anyone who conducts the study.
Biological sciences often have a rather low bar for a standard of proof. The way that this is quantified is typically referred to as a p-value, and so for p-values, lower p-values are better, meaning that the study results are more likely to confirm the tested hypothesis.
Good result that is publishable is usually less than or equal to 0.05. Now, this means that there is a less than or equal to 5% chance, or 1 in 20, that the tested hypothesis is not true and that random fluctuations cause the results of the study. Now, you may say, well, 5%, like that seems...
Really, really bad. Why is this bar so low? And that is often because it is typically very hard to conduct studies on living creatures, on humans, animals, what have you, because there are so many other factors that come into play if you're trying to study physiological responses. There's no way you can really coop up humans to study some sort of training method or supplement or things like that where you can control
every aspect of their life and their environment for that period of time. No one would subject themselves to, oh, come test this workout methodology, but you have to live in this dorm and we have to control how much food you get and we have to control how much sleep you get and we have to, you know, limit how much screen time and dose out food in specific times and intervals and all this stuff. It's just not worth it and no one would sign up for those studies. So that leads to this rather low bar.
But this also means that lots of results in biological and biomedical sciences just kind of barely meet this p-value standard and so you really want to see this result repeated over several studies with slightly different conditions, slightly different populations, all these things to really kind of believe that this effect is real or this
Training Regimen is real or the supplement actually works. XKCD has a funny comic talking about this about p-values where they look at jelly beans and say, oh, you know, the random chance that jelly beans are linked to increased acne and then, you know, on the off chance that the 20th color of jelly beans that you try does correlate with increased acne rates, boom, the news media is filled with, oh no, don't eat jelly beans because they cause acne.
We'll link to that comic in the show notes. You can see that there are many reasons why a company or a trainer or a person is going to want to sell you on their trick, their methodology or their secret or their supplement or whatever it is because that's monetarily and financially very beneficial for them. However,
You should probably be at least a little skeptical of the people who claim to have the quote silver bullet. There really aren't any silver bullets and people claiming to have one or have found several or whatever it may be are probably
withholding information at best if not outright lying to you. So hopefully that helps and you can avoid getting taken by bro science claims in the future.
We'll see you next time on the Empirical Cycling Podcast. Hope you enjoyed this week's episode. Thank you Kyle and thank you guys all for listening and I hope you guys enjoyed this podcast on bro science and avoiding bro science. So if you'd like to support the podcast you can do so by subscribing to us and by telling some friends about the podcast and also by going to iTunes and giving us a rating and possibly a comment that really helps us in the rankings. If you'd like to make a donation to the Empirical Cycling Podcast you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate.
So if you've got any questions or comments or coaching or consultation inquiries, you can please send those to empiricalcycling at gmail.com. If you want to follow me on Instagram, I'm at empiricalcycling. If you want to follow Kyle, he's at khelson10 and he's got a lot of cats on his Instagram. So give him a follow. And with that, I want to thank you guys as always.