Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore. Thank you, everybody, for listening. Kyle's got the day off because we have a special guest today. So, of course, as usual, subscribe to the podcast, but, of course, mostly share the podcast. We really appreciate all of the sharing the podcast that is happening. So, of course, give us an iTunes rating, five stars, never goes amiss. Thank you so much for all of those. And, of course, we are ad-free. So if you want to donate, if you want to support the show, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We have some show notes up on the website linking to our guest.
today. And of course, if you have any coaching or consultation inquiries, questions and comments, just shoot me an email at empiricalcyclingatgmail.com. We are, of course, always taking on athletes and we will always do a consultation no matter what time of year, no matter what your questions are, we will be able to at least help you out if not answer them outright. So, of course,
On Instagram, that's at Empirical Cycling. We have some weekend AMAs happening, and I usually ask for questions for each podcast, but I knew this one was going to go long, so I didn't this time, because today we have Matthew DeRosch, who is a former MMA fighter, and of course he is also a coach of many, many things, and he has a very inquisitive mind, and we had a conversation a couple weeks ago, and I thought, we should actually sit down and just do a podcast, because, you know, even if we're the only two people who find it really interesting,
We definitely find it really, really interesting. So we have a very long conversation coming up. And he's a really interesting guy. He's got a lot of very interesting questions. And he has a very nascent YouTube channel at ResilienceHPC. And of course, ResilienceHPC up on the Instagram and .ca.
for resiliencehpc.ca is his website, and so if you want to check him out, he's a very fascinating guy, and you'll see why as we get into the conversation. So without further ado, let's get into it, and we'll see you on the other side. At what point did you decide to stop doing MMA, and what was your thought process there? It's funny, and this is actually why.
Was your body breaking down too? Or were you just sick of like forgetting math and getting knocked in the head? Well, it's actually a little bit of both. My body was consistently breaking down through, you know, you're throwing your limbs at each other at high velocities and bone on bone and stuff like that. Over time, yeah, you do accumulate injuries and you're always going into fights injured, right? Some people are going into fights with broken limbs, right?
Crazy, crazy stuff. Oh yeah, 100%. I've seen people go into fights with broken arms. I've seen people go into fights with broken hands. But the real problem for me was the neurological consequences because I had started looking into concussions before I even really got into MMA.
because I played a lot of other sports, hockey, rugby, all these different things, even powerlifting. Yeah, the Canadian sports, yeah. Exactly. Yeah, so I understood that there is a neurological consequence to subconcussive blows. Even though I wasn't getting flatline grade three concussion, I knew that these accumulated traumas was going to rear its head someday.
I think that the disconnect there for a lot of fighters is because it takes 10, 15 years for the symptoms to actually show up. The dissonance is such a large gap, right? So for me, I knew that they're already coming out with technology and things. We're already starting to detect it much earlier. And I seen, oh yeah, even though I'm not feeling symptoms, I know this is going to be a problem and I have to deal with.
When you're going into a training camp and you're going to put everything into it, if there's a little bit of that in your head where I'm like, oh, if I get knocked out, oh, if I, there's just, there's a little bit too much resistance because I try and explain this, you know, to other athletes as well. Training for an event is extremely stressful in itself, right? Like I'm sure you understand when you're training for this peak event, it's a huge thing.
You know, the amount of effort that goes into managing just the logistics of dealing with your family, dealing with work, just that itself. But then you have this thing in the back of your head where you're like, there's one individual out there that is training specifically for me, you know, to kick my head in. And he's trying to figure out every weakness I have, every, you know, deficiency I have, and he's going to try and exploit that.
Well, you're trying to do the same to him. Exactly. So you're sitting with that stress in the background. And that's honestly, I think one of the reasons why fighters age so dramatically is because of that low level stress. It's the out of the ring stress. Exactly. The constant wear. Yeah. Well, it's, you know, that sounds like...
That's like World War I kind of battles, you know, just like drawn out forever. And then just one day, like, you know, there's a show with your name on it. But if you make it through, it's like, you know, what do they call it back in the day? Shellshock? Yeah, Shellshock, PTSD. The shelling. You know, but, you know.
I mean, it's no joke. I did Taekwondo for about 10 years. I stopped writing when I was a freshman in college around 2000, 2001. And I got my fair share of knockouts. And I remember...
After every one, because this was like the mid-late 90s, and I was actually selected for some pretty high-level international teams, and I was never allowed to go, because the places we were going to go, my parents were like, oh, you're going where? No, you're not. You're going where in India? No, no. Have you heard about the fighting that's going on there? I'm like, it's on the other side of the country. It's fine. And they're like, no, you're not going. But there was no conception of that kind of stuff, and I remember getting knocked out in a tournament once.
But I got up fast enough that they didn't call the fight off. I just stood there waiting for the clock to run out. And the guy was just standing there like, well, I won, but you feeling okay? Yeah, yeah. And those things, looking back at it now, you don't notice every time I've suffered fairly dramatic subconcussive blows to the point where I'm probably at a grade one concussion.
Like constantly? Yeah, there's these little changes and we know that through concussion testing now that individuals plenty of times don't go back to baseline. Like for example, like my partner, she had a fairly serious concussion that I honestly believe that she's never gone back to baseline since then. There's certain things with her coordination, her balance, vagal tone, like autonomic nervous system functioning. I think there's specific things that, you know, and especially...
Athletes don't want to add all these little things to correct some of these problems in the first place. So the process was just too much to me. We're having a family. I just I'm not going to for the little bit of glory. Right. It's not. And I love the competition. I was in it for the competition. But, you know, I could still go out and roll and I can still go out and play spar and do those things if I if I really want to. So, yeah, I mean, it sounds a lot like a lot of older Criterium racers.
and actually a lot of clients I've had who start in their 30s and 40s who have a wife or expecting kids or have kids, a lot of them will just race and just not even contest any sprints. They enjoy the speed, they enjoy that aspect of the competition, but they're not willing to risk themselves or their family or whatever. And so I think that...
that at the very least is a really good parallel between fighting and bike racing is that, you know, the level of risk that you're willing to tolerate. And, you know, bike racing is, it's, you know, in some ways it's a sport about managing risk. And, you know, it's like, for me, my, my best, like, I was never able to like get to the line with like just three other people or something like that. Like I had to.
Go there with like 30 other people in a big bunch sprint. So I was always like, you know, it's one of those things where, you know, just you should just roll the dice straight up. I don't have good odds of ever winning a bike race like that, you know. But it's like you and one other guy and it's like 50-50. Like who's going to come out of there able to, you know, see straight and walk and, you know, whatever it is. That's a really good point on.
Risk, hazard, managing these things. It's funny because I don't, this is a huge field. Like if you get into mountaineering or skydiving, risk management is like a huge portion of study. Like they put out these accident reports every year. You can go online and read them. And the FAA does the same thing for skydiving. So you can go out and read these accident reports, the thought process of the individuals involved, if they could glean that if someone survived.
And that's a thing that I think is kind of lost in other sports, whether it's through the training process or whatever it is, is understanding what you're willing to sacrifice. So for example, when I go out and climb with an individual, I'll be very clear in relaying to them the risk of doing it. Yeah, the risk might be low or the risk might be high depending on what we're climbing. But unless you're willing to have a piece rip out and fall and slam from...
60 feet onto the deck we shouldn't engage in this if you're not willing to risk that and it sounds super dramatic and stuff like that but I've always known that people whenever shit hits the fan the people that weren't willing to accept that risk end up the most you know
absolutely dismantled from the event, right? They cannot cope with the consequences afterwards because they weren't ready to take those risks in the first place. Right, no mitigation strategy. Exactly. Well, actually, thinking about concussions, I was actually surprised because I listened to an interview with Dale Earnhardt Jr. who was talking about his concussions, and I didn't know how, you know,
Pt-able concussions can be for some people, but also for some people, there's just no coming back. And what's the state of the stuff at this point with concussions? What kind of doctors can you see for that kind of stuff? There are people that specialize in it, right? But they're few and far between. Very few. Yeah. For example, even where I live now, I've seen a concussion clinic open up.
in the last few years, I believe. But if you go in and kind of look at what they're doing, or if you look at most of the concussion clinics around, they're at a very, very basic level of operation. So they're doing some basic coordination testing. They're doing some basic cognitive response. But a lot of things that are going to be the problem down the road aren't necessarily...
going to show up in those. For example, we know that gait is a huge parameter of understanding future, right? But a lot of people aren't even into that feel yet or autonomic function like we were talking about earlier. A lot of people don't have the ability to understand those well or test them well. So I think there's just, it's good that they're getting better, but I honestly don't believe that.
if you can get back to doing a certain balance test on your foot or, you know, pressing the numbers at a certain given time that that means that, hey, you're back to baseline. I don't believe that. And I, it's funny because I'm always reading some of these random Russian journals and they've been kind of ahead of the science on this for a long time, right? They've actually got some pharmacology. Yeah, they've got quite a bit of pharmacology out there that is used for traumatic brain injury that's shown.
some insane results, like absolutely insane results, but also their protocols and stuff like that. And it's just, there's a little bit of a disconnect there. Like Western kind of science is getting up to it, but they're still kind of grabbing the bull by the horns a little bit too much rather than trying to finesse their way into understanding the underlying importance of, yeah. Anyways. Actually, well, I wanted to ask you,
specifically, because you come from MMA. What kind of stuff, I mean, it's probably still going on, a lot of it. What kind of stuff did you do in MMA back in the day to train or cut weight that you know for a fact now is absolute bullshit? There's a ton of stuff, man.
I don't know where to start with this actually. Like I think the weight cutting thing, I just had a conversation. I went back to my buddy's gym yesterday for the first time in years and they were talking about weight cutting. And I think there's a lot of misguided information going on there with like rehydration. Oh, I got an IV. I'm fine. It's like, you know, your brain is going to take several weeks to rehydrate after a weight cut that dramatic, especially, you know, most guys are doing 15.
to 20 pounds in one day. So 24 hours of water cut in one day. I'll give you an example of a weight cut that I did, right? I started, I was at 210 pounds. I got a call for a fight six weeks later at 160 pounds. So that's, you know, 55 pounds, roughly whatever, 55, 60 pounds. Sorry, 50 pounds. Yeah, 50 pounds from 210. So that's 50 pounds.
a month and a half. The damage that I did to my kidneys, it's funny because people don't think about these things. When you get stage one chronic kidney disease when you're 45 because you wanted to get a slight advantage in a few fights, is that worth the trade-off? Because with MMA, we're seeing these really dramatic protocols going on.
We don't even really know the long-term effects of that because boxing is not as extreme in terms of weight cutting as MMA is. And some of the methods that they use, like for example, when I was on, I did this show back in the day for MMA and some guy dumped alcohol in the bath because he said it's going to dry your skin out better. I ended up taking a seizure 24 hours before a fight and still went out there and fought. I've seen this happen to guys before too, taking seizures during weight cuts.
It's just there's so much dogma from wrestling, all these other sports that have kind of worked their way in, and it was all built off of nothing. It was all built off no science. So at the end of it, I started really getting good at understanding rehydration, glycerol, some of these things that are hyperhydration, understanding how much weight is adequate to cut.
and how much can I get away with without dehydrating my spinal fluid, for example. But also just the training too. And this carries over to any sport that I've ever heard. You get into sports and people just say, oh yeah, you got to work on your pedal stroke or you got to work on your gait. For training, it was always get a good jab. But what does that actually mean? Can you explain to me as a coach?
What does getting a good jab actually mean at the neurological level, at the muscular level, right? Well, because I know how I would describe it and I know how I would want to quantify it. But the question is, you know, how do you, well, a lot of people probably don't have the equipment to measure that kind of thing. Like I would want high speed camera. I would want to look at speed.
like maximum speed. I would want to look at force. I would also want to look at like isometric force or like what can you bench press, that kind of stuff. And it's one of those things where like that's what I would want to see. But I think the weight thing in MMA is it's a lot more extreme than in cycling. But in cycling, I feel like it's a lot more chronic. Like in MMA, it's like really acute. Like you're going to cut 50 pounds in six weeks. Or in cycling,
you're just gonna be perpetually underweight and you're never gonna quite have the right amount of power and that's actually another thing that's I think is interesting between cycling and MMA is like in MMA you don't have anything like a power meter where you can go oh wow I'm really I'm really underperforming today you know because it's like I get light okay I can I can make the weight class is it like this thing where you start big and then you end up really lean in a cut and like people think that that makes you really good?
Yeah, and it doesn't. It's people think they're getting an advantage by cutting weight. I can tell you for a matter of fact that the performance metrics whenever you rehydrate, because I've done this testing, you do not go back up to anywhere as close to baseline. And not only that, just think of your cardiac system, like dehydrating yourself to that degree. Think about the plasma volume loss, right? And you're going out there for...
for five rounds or three rounds, and it's one of the most cardiovascular demanding events. It's just, there's so much misunderstanding, and there's just not been a rigorous scientific background behind some of this stuff. Now, obviously, guys like Andy Galpin, Andrew Usher, guys that are getting into the field and applying some science to this stuff.
the more there's and that's what the big difference like we're talking about Russian science well there's so much science on combat sports and Russian literature like probably 20% of the papers I see out there on some type of combat sports because they understand so many factors that need to be kind of whittled down but it's funny because we're talking about weight cutting and cycling this is something that I've seen on several other podcasts we're talking about weight cutting and I'm like
You're in a sport that is probably one of the most isolated physiological sports there is, and you want to tell me that you're going to deplete yourself of nutrients, but you want to adapt physiologically? It's just such a hard thing to wrap my head around where it's like... Well, let's unpack that a little bit because I think that's a super interesting point. Because I think what you're saying is cycling depends so much on...
your actual fitness, whereas like MMA, not so much. Like MMA, you can have a VO2 max of 80 or you could probably have a VO2 max of like 50 and you can fight about the same. Sort of like in team sports where it doesn't matter if you can squat more or if you can like do 20 razor curls. How well do you play soccer? That's the big question. Like how's your team? How's your coach? How's your strategy? But yeah, I think that's super interesting because
That is a lot of the focus in competitive cycling today is just the physiology, the power. And I think there's one of the reasons I started the podcast is because I was having the same kind of questions that you do. Like before we started recording, I said that I think I'm your one YouTube view on one of your things from your website.
from resiliencehpc.ca, right? Yeah. And so I go under the individual training response and I'm watching it and I'm like, these are exactly the kind of things that I had, the kind of thoughts and questions that I had like years ago. And I started just questioning everything. Same as Tim Pudlogar, who was on the podcast a couple episodes ago.
He had the same thought and you're in the same boat as us. So I consider you a kindred spirit, not only because we're both sitting next to all of our books, like you've got a library behind you. So what was your path between MMA and what do you do now and like where are you at now? Because you coach and you work with a lot of different sports. Yeah, I work with anyone I can get my hands on really because
I'm starting to work with some fighters again. I work with a couple of hockey players, strength athletes, anything I can get my hands on. I really want to try and whittle down and ask the questions that I think are, I don't want to sound like I'm on a pedestal or anything, but I think there's just a lot of nuance out there that's being missed with some of these sports and approaches.
Basically, I just want to figure out the pillars of, you know, what are the differences in recovery processes for certain things? For example, like a sport like climbing, what are the recovery demands of training your tendons several times a day compared to training your muscle fiber a couple times per day? You know, what are the demands of the sport is really a big...
that I think everyone should start at. And when you start at that point, what are the demands of the sport? Then you'll start to find what are the good questions I should be asking? Because when you look at cycling, I think a lot of people don't start there. They just start from what are the best people doing? What is the guy down the road that's winning the local tournament? What is he doing? And then they start from this kind of reverse order. That's a very human thing, isn't it, though?
Yeah. You know, like I remember when I was like 13 and I was super into like Nirvana, I was like, I need Kurt Cobain's shirt, I need his jeans, I need his guitar, and I will be that guy. And then it turned out that I was glad I wasn't that guy. Yeah, I hear you there. So like with most sports, actually, the first point of demands is actually perception, reaction is vision.
right vision is the first portion which it's funny because I I can maybe count on my fingers how many people have even you know thought about training their vision in MMA it's starting to get more popular now in sport in general just in health and wellness but vision is basically everything and I noticed the people that were always the best at any sport team sport kind of
they were just perceiving things quicker whether it's Wayne Gretzky in hockey he was never the fastest skater he was never the best at change of direction or hardest shot or whatever it is it's his ability to see things better than the next guy it's the same in fighting if you watch what Mighty Mouse does right Demetrius Johnson he's doing things on a speed that's so high but
If you think about it, why does he play video games for like eight hours a day sometimes? Well, he's training his vision without even knowing it. And he's perceiving things quicker than the next guy. So really buckling down and realizing, okay, this is where we should start is with vision, right? Training our vision, binocular, convergence, divergence, all these things. And then work out from there. What is the next step, right? Well, we want to have a good base of physiology. What are the demands of the physiology?
and then, you know, strategy and all these things that get layered on top, but, and rate of perceived exertion is a big one. It's funny because I seen your post on Instagram, which I think is one of the funniest posts I've ever seen of the, of the cycle of RPE to, you know, heart rate to power back to RPE. Exactly. Right. And it's so funny because the wisdom I see in most sports actually work that way. Like you start off relatively with.
the right answer. And then you try to like grasp for the next thing on the table and then you come back and find it. But yeah, well, that's, oh man, it's so funny that I've had to, oh, I haven't had to, but I've had the opportunity to, I guess, explain to a lot of folks that, you know, no matter how much physiology you learn and you figure out how to apply, a lot of it.
is reinforcing the basics. Actually, I would say almost all of it is reinforcing the basics. And it's like remaking your entire training program to target this one certain aspect of physiology is like getting the cart before the horse. But if you think, how does this help me in the training stuff? But a lot of it is like if you learn one thing.
You're like taking a step out into the darkness. And then you can turn around and go, I know the way back here. But as soon as you take a couple steps and you think you know the way back, all of a sudden you don't. And you've got like half of the puzzle and you don't know the missing pieces. But the more pieces you have, the more you see the gaps in the puzzle. And you can go, oh, I've almost got a map here, but there's still the fog of war between me and all these little pieces of physiology that are taunting me that I don't know yet. Yeah.
It's true and I think like you get this with certain athletes the people that like really stick to the internal perception like they stick to the things that are important which I think a lot of them is like internal perception rather than this external focus I don't know if you've seen this in cycling maybe you could elaborate on this but like the individuals that understand
you know they call it interoception and research right like the ability they start off with the ability to maybe detect your heart rate as one component that they would use in research for an athlete's ability to understand what's going on in their body but interoception basically the understand the the ability to understand some of these thresholds some of these abilities to understand their effort like if you look I was talking with Jim Arnold about this with like Speedgate Golf
where these coaches would have their runners go out 10 or maybe 6 or 8 or whatever runners go out at the same time and they're running 20 meters. But they have to time 20 meters at exactly 2.3 seconds. And the person that hits 2.3 seconds is the winner. So they're connecting their perceived exertion to their output.
And this is something that I don't think a lot of sports really spend a lot of time thinking about. But realistically, this is a really good kind of concept to carry over because power is power. Power is a different thing. We obviously know it's fairly stable. We know power is fairly stable. But when we're talking about riding for several days in a row, like in some of these bigger tournaments, power doesn't always equal power.
RPE is kind of an important, I don't know, maybe you can talk a little bit about this too. Yeah, well, because you're getting towards, you're getting to pacing. Yeah. And the pacing is a lot of what I try to work on with folks, especially if they don't have a really amazing natural ability at it. Like most people need to work on pacing. I need to work on pacing. A lot of my athletes need to work on pacing.
And so what you're talking about with being able to time 20 meters to 2.3 seconds, that's pacing. And it's sort of like if you've got a flat time trial that's 20K, being able to pace yourself so that you explode on your very last pedal stroke across the line. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Exactly. That's good pacing. And so I think that's...
One of the things that carries over between sports, because I was watching the Spanish Grand Prix yesterday, and the ability of those drivers to know their lap times, to be able to feel the pace and be like, I've got a little more pace, or I need to back this off. And they'll do it within a half a second a lap, or a second a lap, and that's absolutely mind-blowing to me. And then you can get a fresh set of tires on and then go a full second a lap faster.
your first time out without having like practiced, oh, I can take this corner a little faster. Like they can feel the car. And that's kind of like an RPE in sports and in cycling, especially is how I think about it, obviously, where if you are, well, obviously the RPE thing too is fascinating because I want to do a podcast on this soon. But having set points for RPE is actually super important, I think.
to start with, like having a common language of RPE between you and your athlete. And it doesn't ever have to be the same between people. I know other coaches use different set points on the scale of one to 10 than I do, where I think a six is threshold for some folks, but a seven is threshold for me. And we have just different ways of describing it, but we're all trying to get to the same point. And so when you start thinking about RPE, it's sort of like...
we needed a how we needed a way to describe the boiling and freezing points of water or like just temperature in general. Right. So like we use water like and why does you know why do we have 32 Fahrenheit instead of zero? It's because some scientists back in the day decided to make a brine of like ammonia and different salts and try to make a liquid that had the lowest freezing point he could find. Yeah.
Then of course we have feet and the less used version of feet which is hooves, we have the hooves and thumbs Yeah, it's a good point and I don't want to rehash what I've already talked about online but in that discussion too we were talking about how can we practice that in several different aspects and anyone I have in the gym
I explain to them this is a great opportunity to work on RPE so whether you're doing an isometric let's just say I have an athlete say I want you to do single leg bent knee calf raises to 15 reps to failure pick a weight whatever weight you might be able to do 30 reps but I want you to fail on the 15th rep so I want you to modulate your effort to hit 15 and fail maybe it's adding more co-contraction
Or the same thing with an isometric, you know, modulate your effort to fail at 30 seconds. And the more you get these reps in, and obviously not all your weight training is going to be centered around that, but use some of those opportunities where you're building different capacities in the weight room to take advantage of understanding that connection in your brain because you ask an athlete to go out and sprint for 50 seconds.
So you tell them 50 seconds, it's going to be a different sprint than if you say 10 seconds, right? Yeah, very. So I think it's just some of these internal processes that if you spend a lot of time trying to develop, especially in a sport like cycling or running, endurance sports, you'll gain quite a bit in understanding, oh, I can hammer on right now for sure. Yeah. Yeah. And in cycling, it's a little different.
Than a lot of other sports too in that we actually are using like different energy systems like over and over and at different times and repeatedly even. And so it becomes extremely different to like pace. Like if you are solo off the front in a criterium, you've got to accelerate out of every corner. And that becomes very different than putting out a really steady out and back like 40k TT. Even if you do it for the same amount of time. And it can require different training.
It can require different practice. It can require different sessions. I'm saying can because it doesn't always. Some people can do either way. And, you know, a lot of it comes down to like technique and all that kind of stuff. And so and then, of course, being able to adjust your effort for how tired are you on the day? Because Joe Martin's stage race just finished up yesterday.
And, you know, that last race and even the time trial on the second to last day, it's very different than if you do the same time trial without having raced two road races two previous days. And so adding all those factors can help. But the most important, of course, is making sure that you have your best effort on that day, regardless of all the other things, because you...
should be able to adjust your effort based on your RPE to that day. Yeah. Yeah, it's like that's the difficulty of sport is because you spend so much time for this one little moment to express whatever you're trying to express. Yeah. And I think a lot of people don't realize that there is going to be, you can train all these capacities and qualities, but there's still this
thing on the day where you're still going to have to modulate. You don't just go out there and just, you know, just blow out the lines, right? You have to still modulate and tune up. Yeah. So it's, yeah, it's a good thought. And like, while we're on this, I wanted to think of like, because we were talking a little bit there about training in the weight room, like when you, when you approach
cycling and connecting that to the weight room. Obviously, there's not a ton of research out there, right, on connecting cycling. I just actually read a review the other day on Ron's dad was, you know, difference in sexes between men and women and weight training and cycling. But there's just not a ton of literature out there on the connections between cycling. What is it that you...
What is the conversation you're having with an athlete whenever you're saying, hey, do you think it would be beneficial for you to be in the weight room? What are the qualities that you're trying to grasp when you're in there? What are you trying to get out of that for athletes? Usually it's why are we in there. For older athletes, like 40, 50 plus, usually it's for health.
to make sure that if you do crash in a crit that you don't break your hip wide open and need a replacement or need to spend six months healing or whatever it is. But the other thing is a lot of folks, I think, see some of the research out there that says if you do some weight training, you will increase power at blah, blah, blah. And a lot of it is just straight up from neural drive.
It's just really simple, basic. Your brain gets used to putting out more signal to contract larger motor units or contract the same motor units faster or something like that. And then that gets us into the questions of sprinting and why are we doing this? What kind of power do you want? And for a lot of folks that go into the gym, first of all, some people just like it.
And that's okay. I just like it too. But when it really comes down to it, if somebody wants to improve their sprint, the first thing we have to do is think about the training that it's going to take away from being on the bike. And think about long-term limiters. Because what limits somebody in a bike race that's longer than about a minute is mostly going to be aerobic.
and so if you are trying to get to the end of a criterium and have a great sprint like if you get to the end of a crit and you are and like fresh you've got like 1500 watts and at the end of a crit you've got like 1100 and you want more at the end of a crit you don't need to hit the weight room you know it's like it's like it's the the criteria is too narrow it's like I like I'm not sprinting hard enough therefore I need to train my sprint better it's it's backwards it's I'm not sprinting hard enough at the end of a crit
I'm too tired. I have depleted myself. I need to get aerobically stronger. Because if you look at a crit, the power surges over threshold. But if you're surging at like 350 watts over and over again, and your threshold's 300 watts, that is a very hard day. If your threshold is 380 watts, surging at 300 or 350, that's nothing. Absolutely nothing. And you are going to get to the end of your race, and you're going to maybe be down like 50 watts.
And then that gets into pacing and saving energy in the group and reading the race and all that kind of stuff. So the weight stuff, it's hyper contextual. I wish there were an easy answer. No, no. That is a good answer because I think a lot of people miss that you need balance in whatever sport you're doing, especially when you have this whole
life load outside of sport, right? But if you look at even professional athletes in many different countries, a lot of them on their off seasons would play other sports quite competitively to the point where they're like almost at a professional level at other sports, right? To find balance and qualities outside their sport. And I think that a lot of people are chasing the wrong things in the gym sometimes.
And there's actually better applications of what they could be doing to get where they want to go, but they're chasing the wrong things. They're not getting exactly what they think they're getting, I think, rather than just understanding that this is just like a balance mechanism. You need balance in whatever sport you're doing, right? Because if you're sitting down at a computer for eight hours a day, going out and sitting on a bike, right? You're going to need some more balance outside of that to try and...
gain homeostasis in the long run, right? Yeah. Well, and also I think going back to the research on weight training and cycling and what research there is, a lot of it has cyclists that have never been in the weight room before. Yeah, of course. And there's a lot of new gains to be had.
that I think color a lot of studies. And this is one of the things that I think that you were mentioning in your video that I was watching. And I was like, man, this guy's right on. It's the same question I was asking. Because you're thinking about the test group. You're thinking about where they are in training. And the subtext to that is when somebody is new at something and they just start doing it, there's a very, very rapid...
with improvement in ability in a very short amount of time. And the same thing goes in like aerobic stuff too. Like the first thing that we usually do is gain plasma volume and that increases VO2 max and that increases threshold. It's pretty simple. And you can get there by doing endurance riding. You can get there by doing threshold work. You can get there by doing VO2 max and high intensity stuff. And the questions start piling up about like, what is the mechanism?
that makes this yield this adaptation. And so the mechanism that helps us when we are new at something is not the same one that helps us when we are well-trained and we are looking for like another 10 watts of threshold per year, if that. Or sometimes it's like, okay, this person doesn't have any more threshold to gain. Let's see if we can get them more endurance or let's see if we can work on their sprint.
or see if we can work on their reading the race or anything like that. And so as you go, the studies get a little bit less applicable as you get further and further into being a very well-trained athlete because that's where I think the science only can inform like 30% to 40%.
of what you're doing. And I see, by the way, I see on your page, I see a very large amount of equipment that you have, like infrared thermal imaging, spirometry, metabolic analyzer, pressure mapping, lactate stuff, et cetera, et cetera. Like you have a ton of stuff that in cycling we don't because you work with so many different sports.
And what I want to know from you is how well does that stuff translate into gains, yeah, in other sports, but also is it sort of like in cycling where there's very little, like without power meters, we would have very little to measure baseline fitness with other than like how well can you climb this hill?
or how fast can you go over this course? But there are so many different factors. So when you've got all this equipment and you're testing athletes and you're training them, how much is it where this equipment is super useful or how much of it is just getting a sense of what somebody needs to train and then regardless of how they perform on that test later, you can see that they're better.
because of the training. Like how does that balance work with you and with other sports? Well, I think it's funny because this is one of the questions I had for later too is understanding like, you know, we're talking about softwares and stuff like that, but the real, so this stuff does just right off the bat, I'll go ahead and say that it increases buy-in because it's an objective thing that an athlete can see and say, hey,
It's not just me telling you that you need this. This thing here is showing you that there's probably a potential area to be down the rabbit hole when it comes in regards to this metric that we're talking about. Whether it's applying pressure into the ground when you're walking, that is going to transfer to pretty much everything else. It's something very simple, but also just some of the testings with coordination and balance on a pressure map.
If you go out and I ask you to march with your eyes closed or step on the mat with your eyes closed and you're doing a 180 degree rotation, your brain, the sensory information from your feet is obviously off. There's probably something there to be gained in understanding like whenever you hit the ground when you're running, your brain actually is probably sending some like essentially information that is not.
going to benefit you in the best way. So can we pull that apart and try to understand, you know, how can we improve that sensory information starting at the feet up? Maybe it's something as simple as textile insole, right? It could be something as simple as changing the surface that you're doing some of your exercises on, right? It's the same thing if I told you to go out and do something with very fine motor skills, like play guitar with a glove on.
What's that sensory information, right? I used to play guitar and that would be awful. Yeah. Even though I like to climb, I would hate it. You don't know what's going on there. So some of these things, yeah, first and foremost, it's just going to give another objective voice to the athlete that's saying, hey, this is something. And it can, for example, make a huge difference too. Like I had an athlete come in with a seven liter lung capacity. Wow.
Right? And he's a small guy. He's not some six foot nine rower, right? He's a runner. And off of some of the popular side that he was out there reading, like Breathe and all these other books, I think, you know, he kind of had misconstrued maybe some of the type of breathing that would be beneficial to him. But we're saying, no, like you have this massive lung capacity. Let's try and see if we can organize your breathing in a better way so you're not hyperventilating.
So, you know, you're getting good coordination of your breath. It's just kind of a little bit of a shortcut. Sometimes you find a shortcut with it. Sometimes you don't, right? Sometimes an athlete comes in. I gave blood in my arms, like all messed up. Well, let's throw the thermal camera on and see what's going on there. And maybe it's a little bit of a shortcut so we can pinpoint it. It's just... Well, I have a question about that. It's like, I mean, when you say it increases buy-in, in a way that sounds to me like...
It increases the effectiveness of how you can assess an athlete. Yeah, exactly. Because a lot of these things, for example, I could probably do some of these things with my eyes. Let's say, for example, with a powerlifting athlete, right? I want to see, I want to understand the technical proficiency versus the actual strength that that athlete has, right? A squat for me, the squat to me is not a good predictor of strength in the legs.
There is so much coordination going on there, you know, and I'm not trying to throw powerlifters under the bus. I did it for a long time too. So I'm just trying to say that it's not the best predictor of raw tissue capacity, right? Yeah. What is the capacity of that tissue? So maybe I put them in a belt squat and connect it to a crane scale and then throw a moxie on there and see what's actually going on at the muscle. Cause that's so simple. Like the more complex you make a movement.
The less of an ability for the athlete to actually send input into that, right? Yeah, you're removing components of the kinetic chain, which everything that we put in increases losses, which is, you know, among other things, one of the reasons that, you know, if we did like a bench press, if we took the bench away from the shoulders, the bench press would be like less than half of what it is. Exactly. Dude, I went on the leg press because somebody had...
taking the squat racks or the trap bar or something a couple weeks ago. And I didn't realize how much I could leg press because I'd been squatting and I messed my quads up. I was just like, oh my God, yeah, I could do this for like, I could do 10 more reps if I wanted to, but I should stop here. And then I'm shaking and my quads were quivering for a couple of days afterwards. I was like, oh, wow.
Or as you might say, the capacity of this tissue is high. Exactly. Higher than I might have otherwise realized. Exactly. But that's one of those things that I learned on myself that we have to be careful with that kind of stuff. And I think that it's cool in a way that you get to use so much equipment.
Because in cycling, we've got a power meter and maybe a lactate thing, and that's going to be about it. There's not a lot of other stuff that really helps us, unless you're going to get into bike fitting and biomechanics and that kind of stuff. There's really nothing else. A lot of it's just understanding what is the limitation of this aspect of your performance. Yeah. Yeah, and the thing with that too is...
is with endurance athletes, the training load and time is already so high. So I look at all training as when we're making changes in training, I look at it under two categories. Is it a substitution or is it an addition? If I have to add something to the process for the athlete, that is putting extra time demands, extra stress demands versus
Can I just simply change something that they're already doing and takes no extra effort and it'll get a slightly higher yield and adaptation? And I think that's where endurance athletes are already kind of limited in that realm because they're already training 10 plus hours a week, right? Whereas with powerlifting athletes or whatever it is, some of these team sport athletes, it's a little bit less and they might have different time schedules. If you're a team sport athlete,
and you're 25 or 35 years old, you're probably professional or you know what I mean? So it's a different kind of thing where a lot of professional individuals do these recreational sports, which is a totally different thing, right? Yeah, no, I think that's a really interesting observation because that puts into words something that I've...
known sort of about endurance athletes, which is just the limited time and the limited ability to train and recover. The recovery is a big one because if you've got a full-time job and you're training like 10, 15 hours a week on the bike, if you try to go to the gym on top of all that, suddenly you are very, very stretched thin. And it's not like the physical load because if you're a professional athlete and you've got all day to just do this stuff,
You can wake up in the morning, have a leisurely breakfast, go ride, chill out for a couple hours, take a nap, get an extra lunch, walk the dog, then you go to the gym in the afternoon for an abbreviated session, and then you can do something else the next day. But if you've got work and travel and family stress and all that kind of stuff on top of that, suddenly it adds up. That level of stress on the body adds up. It's almost like training without turning a pedal.
Yeah, it's a totally different story. And that's like, if you're going to add something, you should be very certain that it is going to yield a very high benefit. You know, like if you're substituting, it's kind of like, yeah, let's play around a little bit. Let's try and figure out what works for you. But talking about recovery is, I think 90% of people's effort should be into
You know, we think we have a lot of things understood with recovery, but there's just a lot of stuff out there that I don't see folks experience. Like, for example, the reason why I've always been really into recovery is whenever I first started training, there was an individual I followed up here in Canada, he works with a lot of individuals, and he's out there. He's out there, but he's actually got the education of, you know.
of someone that I would consider like a doctoral degree, right? Like this guy's a fairly well-read individual. And he talked about something called working in. And, you know, I took that into pretty much everything I did and understanding every time and it transformed. First, it was this understanding that if you're consistently just working out.
and expelling energy and you're not gaining energy back in. I know this sounds like ethereal here and esoteric, but what I'm talking about is just... It sounds like eating enough. Exactly. Basically what I'm talking about, what it evolved to was autonomic nervous system state, right? But what it was is if you're constantly in the sympathetic state, I was looking for ways to find these micro rests in everything I did. So instead of like pounding music after my set of five deadlifts of whatever weight,
I would sit there, tune in and basically try and find stillness in whatever terms you want to find that so I can get this micro recovery and then it turned into the ability to shift states from going from a fairly low arousal of parasympathetic to a very high arousal really quickly and then shifting back and the better you get at that you're stealing more recovery time and I found my recovery went through the roof with this stuff.
I started experimenting with TENS, transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation through essentially the auricular nerve for vagal stimulation so trying to increase vagal tone through putting TENS on basically on your earlobe and on your neck essentially to increase parasympathetic stuff after work just everything down the box there were some things I found really good gains from but nothing I don't think just
in my own bias opinion lived up to the ability to control those nervous system states. So it's the same with cycling and I take it into everything I do now or running or anything if you're doing an endurance sport is finding some of these micro rests and I'm like whether it's trying to get my heart rate down and just manipulating my heart rate throughout the run or whatever or just trying to understand that.
Not everything is just hammering down and stressing your body. That's not like the path to getting more reps in, right? Yeah. Well, that's exactly what I tell people about recovery and rest is that 98% of it comes from eating and sleeping. And then we have a very big asterisk for stress.
And if you are stressed constantly and your sleep is suffering and you are to some degree in that sympathetic state all day because of job stress or life stress or whatever's happening, that affects your recovery so much. And even in young athletes, even older athletes who are more experienced and you would think, oh, he's got massive training base. He shouldn't be able to be affected that much by this. Oh, yes, absolutely.
You can be that affected. Like I've seen it affect people's basically effective FTP by like 30 or 40 watts or more. And depending on how stressed they are, and you'll see a massive drop in like peak power if they go do a sprint or something like that. And so it's, you know, because that all tracks with that like in-between level of stress. And I actually have inadvertently found myself doing that. I used to...
Go to the gym with headphones on and I would just like blast metal and rock out for like two hours. And now I don't do that anymore because I would always get to a point where I had to like turn the music down. And I was like, okay, I'm done being stimulated. Yeah, exactly. Pull it back. But it's sort of like, but along the same lines, it's like I cannot watch a TV show or a movie when I'm on the trainer that has those ups and downs in mood because my mood will follow those.
Like that scene, that big energetic scene with the explosions is over and they're in the office talking now, like my power drops. Even if I'm just riding endurance, it's just like, I don't feel like training anymore. I'm done riding. So yeah, I think that's fascinating, man. Yeah, it's, and I mean, this is, when you look at why athletes dope and take PEDs, like a lot of it.
Yeah, a lot of it's for the recovery, especially sports outside of endurance. That's why people take steroids. It's because they're trying to enhance their recovery. And I think it's a very simple thing and it's funny because the more experience you get in life is, yeah, your answers become more basic and your answers become more cliche, but it takes you a long time to get there and the real ability is being able to...
try and portray that on to someone else's perception of what they think is going to make them better too. As a coach, that's what you're trying to do is instill that hard-earned wisdom. That's why I love books. To me, books are the most insane thing ever. People have spent their entire lives trying to figure out this one thing.
and they're going to give it to you for $20. It just doesn't make sense to me. Right. It's the same with you. Like all the stuff that you put out there and I'll go out there and say it right now for sure. It's like you have one of the best podcasts and exercise science period, not even just in cycling because you're putting so much effort. And that's the big thing you see with the guys that are like, for example, like Einstein, these guys.
and it's something I'd noticed when I was a kid. You're not comparing me to Einstein, oh my God. No, no, I'm just throwing it out there. The individual that ends up giving the most benefit back is the person that just cares the most, right? It's the same thing with coaching. Like if you look at Charlie Francis, one of the reasons he was such a good sprinting coach was because he cared so much about his athletes, right? He cared so much about giving the correct information.
The same with you and your podcast. Like you can tell you put a lot of preparation into trying to give the best information possible to the individual because you don't want to mislead anyone in any wrong direction. Other coaches can sometimes be a little bit intellectually lazy and just say things. And it's different with you. I can even tell by the way you speak, you're very careful on how you portray things. And that goes a long way in the long run because as an athlete, a lot of it is just...
You spend so much time going around down these wrong directions. It's, you know, the people that get there the quickest is a lot of the times who have a really good figure to guide them and prevent them from going down too many wrong directions. And they get there a little bit quicker than the next guy, right? Yeah. Well, I mean, I've had some really great mentors in school and also just in cycling and in science in general.
I remember once Tim Cusick pointed out to me how careful Andy Coggin was with his language. Whenever he would post somewhere or speak somewhere or write something, the language was always extremely, extremely careful. And that's one of those things where I think that this podcast isn't nearly as popular as it could be if I tried to simplify stuff and just do this.
you know your miracle intervals right here and we all know you know here in the real world there's no such thing and that a lot of that kind of stuff comes down to like data manipulation and all that kind of stuff and that you know a study you know may come to some conclusion but you know you know you and me we read that study and we'll go I don't think that's true at all because we're like trying to put together a lot of stuff a lot of information into the same
and explain a phenomenon. And I think the very basic thing that I always try to think about is, does this match your experience? Does this match those thoughts you have about, like, is my FTP set too high? Maybe. Like, I remember, and back in the day, I remember, like, doing FTP intervals. I was, you know, my coach was giving me, like, three by 15, then four by 15, and that was pretty much what I got.
Four by 15 minutes, zone four. There you go, five minute rests. I can do that. And I just wasn't getting faster. And I was like, there's got to be something else to this. But he's the coach. He must know everything. He must know the best. And I would even assume that he knew my recovery rate and how I felt and all that kind of stuff. And I would just trust it blindly. But I've learned from that kind of stuff in such a way that
I'm always asking my athletes, how are you feeling? Like I want to see that RPE rating and training peaks. I want you to describe how your legs felt. And whenever I describe, like to go back to the RPE thing, I will describe what a seven should feel like. I will describe what this eight should feel like. I will describe what this sprint should feel like or how I might pace it. Like, you know, if it's a minute max effort, how I would do it is I would start by in the drops, out of the saddle, into the bottom of the hill.
I would start at like 80% of a full sprint and I would just maintain that effort until I had to really concentrate on maintaining that effort that I would sit and just like just grit my teeth and close my eyes and think of England and I will write that like I don't usually copy paste workouts and anything for anybody so I actually write by hand every workout every week except for like lifting I can copy paste and make some small adjustments that was pretty easy but yeah otherwise
And it's very individualized in what I think this person needs to work on. And they had a similar workout last week. We'll go, oh, I think you need to work on this. We'll modify the workout, add some notes, et cetera, et cetera. So I think the caring about people thing is also just recognizing that everything is super individual with people and that everybody needs a little bit something different. And some of the biggest mistakes I've ever had in coaching is besides violating
some big rule because somebody says they're fine and I should not believe them when they say that they're fine. I'm looking at their training load going, you need rest. And they're like, I can keep going. No, I'm going to stop you right here. You've been training for 10 months straight and racing and you have felt fine the whole time, but there's more to your fitness, but you need a rest first. And I was actually going to ask you because
I sent you that webinar from Dean Golich. What did you think about that? The one on performance model. That dude, he's got some early wisdom, I would say. Especially with all the different sports that he's worked with, right? This is something that I see in very few individuals because there's not a lot of individuals that really...
to venture out into these different, because it takes so much time. No one has time for that anymore to try and understand the demands of like hockey versus, you know, like motor sports, right? Like who has the time for that? But he obviously over the years has found time. Maybe that's why you don't, you don't see him on like Twitter, what you're saying. He's probably just like stuck in the dungeon somewhere trying to figure out the demands of some new sport.
It's funny because I really took from he was talking about using some of the processes that militaries use and anywhere he could get anything. And that's what I really think is I call them gamers, people that will like basically they hold no ego. They just go in and get what they can from things like that's a big thing I see with individuals that whether it's they're an athlete or a coach, that they have the humility to understand that.
Hey, I could probably learn something from a powerlifter. As an endurance athlete, there's nothing I could learn from this guy. And vice versa, like a strength sport athlete, like an Olympic lifter, what can I learn from an endurance sport athlete or endurance coach? And just having the humility to understand that all these sports and endeavors have spent decades trying to figure out these physiological processes that gain adaptation.
And you might find something there and you might not just not even from the physiological side, but just from the process side of training and managing an athlete. It was really good to hear that because you just don't see that a lot in sports. I find everything's going this, you know, specificity route of.
Everyone has to be hyper-specialized and kids have to be hyper-specialized in everything they do. And it's easy now because there's so much information out there to hyper-focus on these little things. But I thought it was good because he was talking about understanding the error measurements and whatever you're doing. Understanding...
The actual percent gain that you're going to get in a year, and even if you add those up, where does that leave you? Those things are super important. And just getting those little, because it transfers over to someone like, remember I brought up Dan John when we were doing that talk there, our last conversation.
that's the same type of individual no one listens to Dan John because he just says very basic things but he actually if you listen to what he's saying he's giving you this it's like it's insanely a complex way that he's got there right like if you listen to how he tries to approach winning the track meet with his team that is actually less physiologically capable than the next team if you listen to how he tries
to go about that process. You learn a lot from that. And he's kind of said the same thing that Golich talks about. It's like, show up every day, do this three times a week, and 10 years later, you'll probably get there if you're consistent, right? And yeah, it's just these little things. With an athlete, it's just staying on top of the little things. How much time do you spend every year being sick?
Can we just go get a $12 bottle of vitamin D? We know that athletes are going to deplete their vitamin D stores quicker than the most average individuals anyways. And even soccer players in Brazil are deficient that are spending hours outside every day. There's just little things I think like, yeah, is vitamin D going to improve your performance on a time trial? No, but does it mean that you can't use it to try and enhance the overall process of gaining?
2% a year or whatever it is. I just think that there's these little things that if you're just very consistent that don't take really any addition and you think about the long-term process rather than this just short-term gain, if you always keep in the back of your mind the long-term process, like just tattoo it somewhere on your hand or on your bike, handlebars, wherever, just a long-term process, right? Yeah, just...
That old school Russian stuff about developing the organism in the right direction with the right response and all the... That's funny because that reminds me that I've got... It's like my very, very, very long time ago, the very first person I ever started coaching. I did for nothing, obviously, because I didn't know shit. And she would send me every couple months a gift.
Something, you know, coffee or something like that. And one time she sent me a top cap. It's like this little green anodized thing, and it says on it, pain. That's it. It's still on my bike. And I remember when I got it, I was like, God, it was like 2014 or something like that. At the time, it meant a different thing to me then than it does now, because at the time...
I was very much in the mindset of you get out what you put into it. I didn't have any conception of genetics or anything like that. I remember I had a coach who said like me and one of my friends were being coached by him and my friend goes, hey, how come I can't just like do FTP work for the next year and take my 330 watt FTP and turn it into 400? And the coach goes, well, you would have to do a year of FTP work. And so that's all I thought was between me and a 400 watt FTP.
Between my 280 and 380, I thought it was just going to be a year of FTP work. And then I realized that was not the case. And so now that little pain top cap, it's more ironic to me now than anything. I see it and I'm like, yeah, it's going to hurt sometimes, but most of the time I should make it not hurt. It's contextual and it's changed over the years for me like that.
I don't know, an adorable anecdote, possibly. Yeah, we all get caught up in that too. Like whenever I consulted with you, I go through these cycles. It's like the song that never ends kind of thing where it's like I go through these cycles of getting really excited about things.
And then it takes me like four weeks to realize, or unless someone snaps me out of it, that, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, we're back here. This is where we're at. This is just a thing. It's a shiny object. And you just got distracted for two minutes. And I think that's just, it is like, I'm a younger guy. So the maturity level, it's still like, I understand that it's going to take me some time to like, for my initial instinct to just be like, ah, whatever.
you know but because I'm such a like trying to find ever since I was a kid I was like trying like I thought dude like I thought I just had this secret because whenever I was a young teenager I'd figured out PubMed I figured out what Google Scholar was when I was like 14 so I thought I had this secret that all these other kids didn't have and I was gonna be like you know I'm gonna be a professional athlete in all these different sports better than Bo Jackson
and all these things because I had this secret, right? And it's funny, that's never really left me even though I've failed miserably at pretty much everything I've ever done. But it's just that excitement of discovery and exploration and trying to find all these little different rabbit holes. It's still going to kick you, but you just have to, you know.
As you mature, you're going to be able to be more conservative in your view on everything. Yeah. Well, you've got that self-reflection in your methods. You've got that introspection, but not really introspection, that like, woe is me kind of Sylvia Plath introspection, but like self-doubt introspection, like what here does not work? What's not being effective? How do I improve this for the next round of whatever's going on? And I think that's...
I think that's what I think is so interesting about your approach is that you work with so many different sports and you've got so much equipment and you've got so much knowledge and at the same time you're like, how does this work? I'm not really sure. I should reach out to some folks and I should do more reading and I should get more books. Same here, except I have the fortune to only be into one sport really, which helps with my specificity, but also when it comes to things like strength training and
other stuff. I have probably half the knowledge you do or less because I've been applying it to this one little thing. When it comes to plyometrics, I am absolutely clueless. I know that they're basically useless for cycling with maybe some very few exceptions, especially if you're doing PT, they probably have some effect, but I don't know anything about PT, so I'm in the dark with that kind of stuff too. I think that level of self-doubt
is so helpful when it comes to just being able to, you know, learn. And I think, you know, because one of the things that you had mentioned that you wanted to maybe touch on here is like, you know, what other stuff has, you know, have I learned from or like what other stuff, you know, influences me. But I want to know the same about you. Like what non-sport stuff has been super helpful to you?
This is like, it's funny because I told you even before this, like whenever I sent you over some of these questions and stuff like that, I was like, shit, he wants to know my answers on these. And it's like, I think about them constantly all day, right? But I don't formulate my thoughts. I just, a lot of that is just broad. It's kind of understanding that
Everything may work, but it's just the window of applicability. For example, in some of my reading on hormesis and studying in hormesis is understanding that hypergravity for mice is a great stressor that can aid in plenty of different adaptations that are going to serve that mice and longevity in the future. But there's a specific time frame that that hypergravity has to be applied.
Right? If it's too early, too late, the adaptations are actually, they're awry. And they actually end up causing detriment. Developmental process. Exactly. So, I mean, it's just kind of an overarching is that there's so much to learn, but the context is so important for everything where, you know, yes, this might be really important for this athlete to learn, but is it...
The appropriate time. Is it the right context? Is it applicable at this time in his life? And understanding like, you know, for example, I'm sure there's plenty of athletes that you could give them a much better program that might gain adaptation, but their ability to adhere to that would be so low that you would get nothing out of it. A lot of them don't have the time to write that much. Exactly, right? The endurance, it's so simple. It's so simple. That's a huge factor. It's just the time.
They don't have the time. I don't know. I think actually if I could say this, this is actually something that I've learned because I've gone through so many different iterations of trying to get good at something, whether it's climbing, skydiving, or whether it's endurance sport or lift, anything. You go into these groups and
you realize that there's a lot of the dogma around it is just ego and the real learners this guy called Travis Haley he runs this he's got like the sports science lab if you go in there it's just like this he's got 360 like virtual reality where you go in there and eye tracking and biomechanics and realistically the guy is so far ahead of anyone else in the realm of like
the shooting is just insane. But like I went and took his course and the stuff he was talking about, nothing was about shooting. It was all about vision. It was all about biomechanics. It was all about cognitive processing. But everyone in that field has this huge thing to uphold where they're scared to talk about something like that because it might sound woo woo. Right. And I noticed that in any different.
individual sport that I've went into is the individuals that, you know, can cut away that stuff earlier, cut away that dogma earlier and just ask questions and challenge everything. Those individuals end up, you know, getting a lot further, a lot quicker because they realize the things that actually move the needle and they're not just going out there and doing that workout so they can post it.
on Strava or whatever, and it looks good rather than, hey, I'm going to go out and look like some geriatric folk engaging in physical activity for a couple of weeks because it's not appealing to most people, the things that move the needle. Anyways, yeah, I don't know. It's not a good answer, but it's just kind of off the top of my head of what I think is... What about you? Well, because I think you're...
You know, your thing is very much like my thing. My thing is much more in the reading and you're much more in the doing. So I pretty much ever since I went back to school in like 2007, I've been reading like various versions of like pop sci books. Like the very first one that I read that made me want to go back to school was How the Mind Works by Steven Pinker. And I wanted to do neuroscience.
and I just like straight up walked into the neuroscience department at BU and I was like, could I go to grad school? They were like, no, you have a degree in like music production. You are not going to grad school here. But if you had something that was like biology, so why don't you take some courses and then we'll talk about grad school. So like take, you know, go to night school for a year or two and, you know, keep in touch with us. And I did. And I eventually didn't want to do that because I was exposed to so many more things because it had...
answered so many fundamental questions of like, when I eat an Oreo, why does it make me have energy or get fat? I understand that now. And that was like a fundamental question I had growing up. But I kept reading books that had nothing to do with exactly what I wanted to study, but it was like kind of tangential in a way. And just taking classes and just reading books on like...
Oh god, if I look around, what do I have? Let's see, of course I've got Daniel's running formula, I've got Neil Burt's bike fit, I have of course Comey's strength, power, and sport, etc. But I've also got two biographies on Hans Krebs, and I've got books on sexual selection, and I've got books on developmental biology, and I've got books on
Developmental Neuroscience and all sorts of stuff and I'll just like read it sometimes I'll just crack it open and just browse and other times I'll read it cover to cover and a lot of that kind of stuff has if nothing else has helped me figure out you know the history of some of this stuff but also like just very large like you don't have to remember exactly which insect it is
where the males hatch early and impregnate the females before they even hatch out of the whole cocoon womb thing. It's like some really weird thing. But is it going to help me in cycling? No. But is it a cool fact? Yes. But did I learn other stuff in that book that has helped at least formulate a thought process? Yeah, sure. And I think that's the reading widely.
And occasionally you find a road back to where you started and what you're actually working on. And I think that's the coolest thing in the world. And I never know what it's going to be. But once in a while, I'm like, oh, yeah, I know this thing from like developmental biology, like from like Jerobos and how their feet develop and how they walk. That's vaguely informative on pedal strokes and all that kind of stuff. And sometimes it just means...
Don't fiddle with what's not broke. But other times it means this is definitely a problem. You need to see a bike fitter. So I don't have a good answer either, really, other than just reading widely. That was a good answer because I think you actually approach it in two different ways because when you talked about specialization and you hone in on this one thing, it's kind of like what Miyamoto Musashi talks about. When you do the way intimately,
You see it broadly through all things, right? So you've done, you've honed in on cycling. And this is something that I actually have a problem with is just like, just sticking to one thing for a long time. And Dean Gollich, it's funny because I listened to a podcast with Dean Gollich and he said, and it's like, okay, I'm taking this. I have to like...
and implement this now for sure is because he said if he has one regret is that he scattered his effort way too much when he was younger rather than honing in on one thing, getting everything he could get out of that one thing, understanding it to the nth degree and then moving on where I, you know, I just, I'm all over the, I got seven things in the back of my head at all time that stresses me out.
And it's like for you, you've honed in on that one thing, but you also come to it from the other way and you go outside through all things and try to find back home. Because I've also got those seven things that are stressing me out. But I only have one sport to worry about. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean, and that's funny because like there's, it's really like a two-pronged approach at this point for me, which is my experience with coaching and my experience learning and like in the academic more type stuff. And so...
I'm always trying to bridge the two. And there's not often where you really get a good link between the scientific literature and how you should modify somebody's training plan. Because at the very least, it should jive with the basics. It shouldn't make you think, oh, instead of this person, if this person can ride 20 hours a week,
Why aren't they most of the year? Oh, is it because I think the high intensity training is going to be much better for them because this one paper says so? I'm not going to do that because I know that volume is a huge component of aerobic fitness. And so I'm going to make the stuff I learned fit with what I know experientially. And that's really the empirical part about empirical cycling. Empirical is not always about measurement. It's about direct scientific...
observation. It's about, you know, figure out just what works and, you know, the long process of why does this work? Yeah, it's, I noticed, yeah, it's funny because we actually, we did like a podcast the other day on VO2 Max.
Intervals, how to train via to max story. We just kind of gave a brief overview of some of the ways you would approach it from low end, low intensity, and some of the ways you would approach it from the high intensity realm. We didn't talk too much about the middle, which you can, it's just like, we just didn't have time. We were talking about the high intensity, I actually brought up, it's funny because I noticed it on your podcast first, which made me really go back and read that again, because whenever I read that,
and RPE matched. It was the first thing I noticed when I read the title. As I started reading more and more and more, you tend to forget that the whole basis of that study was built around RPE. But I did notice it. It's funny because I took it into such account when I've read Seiler's other work because a lot of Seiler's work with VO2max was based around RPE. And yes, that's an important factor. RPE is an important factor for the stress load on the athlete.
It's when we're trying to hone in on something specifically, that's not, here I am. I should not be, you know, telling him how to do research. But I'm just saying, it's like we have, I think there should have been more emphasis on understanding, hey, this whole research was based around this. Let's keep this in mind throughout the, like, if you would have kept reading that throughout.
the paper, it would have kept things in perspective, I think, a lot more for athletes going out there, right? Yeah. Well, because one of the things that I always try to do with papers is I look at the data first and I try to draw my own conclusions. I try to look at what was the protocol, what was the measurements done before and after, and then what was measured and what do I think about what happened. Then I go back and I read the author's interpretation.
And a lot of the time, I would say 50 to 75% of the time, I'm looking at the data and I'm going, I have no idea. I'll go right to the bottom of the paper and I'll read their conclusion and then I'll go read the abstract too. And then I'll read the intro and I'll get some background and I'll be like, what exactly are they solving for? And honestly, like half the time or more, I'm like, I don't need this paper in my mind.
This does not solve anything that I am interested in. I hope it solves something for somebody, but it's nothing that I think is useful at the moment. And I'll save it anyway. I've got a giant library of papers, but not a lot of them are top of my mind of, oh yeah, this paper really changed the way that I think about something or other. Like David Montero and Carson Lindby are two of the people whose papers consistently make me rethink everything that I'm thinking about.
because they really, really, they really break down in a lot of ways that other folks don't. What are the components of like say VO2 max? I think that's a really, really good one because with VO2 max, we have several things that drive it and a lot of people just look at VO2 max. It's sort of like looking at lactate in the blood.
like there's rate of appearance, there's rate of disappearance. There's also what's going on in the muscles. There's several different places for it to go. There's several different places for it to come from. And so it's very contextual and we need really precise measurements. And even those precise measurements, even with like tracer studies are still open to interpretation depending on what you think is happening in the cell. And so with VO2 max, like Montero is one of his studies on something like
like early endurance gains are hematologically driven or something like that for the title. And he basically gives people endurance training or whatever and looks at, he actually looks at plasma volume. He looks at red blood cell content. He looks at all sorts of like underlying physiological measurements to determine what is driving the VO2 max change as opposed to just the VO2 max goes up.
Because, you know, historically VO2max is like the easiest marker for a lot of people to figure out somebody's aerobic fitness. But there's more under VO2max than just that. There's like peripheral utilization. There's how much muscle mass are you using. There's, you know, there's stroke volume limitations potentially. Like, and in the VO2max series in the podcast, by the way, if anybody's listening,
The, the, all the stuff before the Ronstadt episode really needs like, like double or triple the listens that it has because that adds context to the Ronstadt episode and why I came to those training recommendations, which, you know, everybody wants to just be told what to do. I understand that. Again, that's why this podcast isn't that popular. It should be though. Thanks, man. But that's, that's one of those things where
figuring out the components of the measurement is huge. And so it's like, I spent weeks, like Kyle and I recorded one of those podcasts like two or three times before I found the right study that explained exactly what I was trying to explain in the podcast in whatever episode. And it was the one on one leg versus two leg knee extensions. One leg knee extension, you could get up to three liters a minute.
But there's a VO2 peak. It doesn't plateau for an increased workload. But you do two legs, suddenly you're at four liters a minute. And now you've got a central limitation rather than a peripheral limitation, which is pretty much what happens in all healthy individuals when we have sufficient muscle mass. So the muscle mass drives the utilization aspect. And so then it becomes, where do you want to measure? It's like measuring voltage.
on a circuit board. Like you can put a ground here and you can put your lead here and you're going to measure voltage or amperage or resistance in different amounts when you measure between two different points. Yeah. So anyway, so that's the Vietta Max example. Well, what you said there, I think a lot of people won't realize that what you're saying is if we would have
If research would have went that direction in the first place, we would have been a lot further ahead. For example, heat adaptation, hypervolemia, the addition of more plasma and red blood cells over time. It's like four weeks when the RBCs start to increase. Additionally, those first two weeks of the plasma volume change, if we would have understood
The components earlier, or if we would have extrapolated those earlier, took away that earlier, we would have got to heat training a lot earlier than we did. We're just seeing it become popular now. We're just hearing about heat training now to increase VO2 max, right? But if we would have broken things down, like you said, which these guys do a very good job of doing, if they would have broken down the components much earlier, we would have been there, you know, because we probably had the... Obviously, like even the paper that you sent me with the...
The phlebotomizing of the athletes, right? And the VO2 max. Like if they would have, if people would have picked that out and said, this is what we're trying to get at here. What are the components, right? Because if you understand the components, then you can start understanding how to shift them.
In the proper direction, you would have understood that, yeah, heat is a good response to increasing hypervolemia, right? But I mean, exercise physiology suffers, like cycling, suffers from tradition, like a lot of sports. It's like the unwritten rules of what's acceptable and not, and like what constitutes like an exercise domain or not, or, you know, what lactate is doing, blah, blah, blah, inflection point, and like, then that gets to like...
you know your test protocol all this kind of stuff is it's it's really really uh it carries over for years even when some some folks very convincingly show that this thing is more complex and all the data we have for x y and z might be wrong like assigning interval training at different percentages of vo2 max
And every couple of years, a different group of scientists figures out that that's maybe not the right way to do it. Even though people have known since the late 70s or early 80s that that's probably not the right way to do it, it's slowly growing. Sort of like exercise intensity domains. This is one of the biggest things that annoys me. It's like you don't have to hit VO2 max to be in the severe intensity domain.
Some people will say that's a physiological response and you need something physiological to explain blah, blah, blah. And I'm like, look, we can see it in the performance. We can see it in a power curve. That is the most fundamental thing. There's a big shift in RPE. There's a big shift in a bunch of different things that we can measure. Who cares if you hit VO2 max or not? Yeah. Measuring the wrong thing sometimes. I think it's just these hyper-focus on these.
Yeah, these certain metrics that kind of cloud people's judgment, especially like when you're looking at the training processes, like, yeah, just take a look at any study. I think it's like, I always do this thing when I was a kid and being like, always thinking like, if there was an accident to be happened, I was going to be the one in it. You know what I mean? So when I looked at training, when I started looking at training, I started looking at it in a different lens right from the get go. Like I was looking at those three non-responders and saying that that's probably me.
That could be me. Rather than looking, oh yeah, the mean average went up. I was looking at it from the perspective of, hey, this doesn't obviously, it's not a hard rule. I just think that a lot of that is lost with people understanding they always want to think that they're going to be the exception. It's like, yeah, it's a good thing to keep in mind that the mean average moved up, but it's not like this hard rule. Yeah. I mean, in my last WKO5 webinar, that's one of the things that I...
I had is like, I was like, look, you have to put a workout into the meat grinder of the athlete and you've got to see what kind of sausage comes out the other side if you even get sausage. The black box. The black box. And, you know, that's one of those interesting things where like sometimes I'll give somebody like heat adaptation training and we'll see via to max go up. And sometimes, sometimes it doesn't. You know, like right now it's like.
It's a hot outside here. And so everybody's, whether they know it or not, they're probably getting a little VO2 max adaptation if they're not well-trained. If they are well-trained, now we've got to start thinking about other things to do. And like the heat adaptation will lead to this kind of stuff. And so like, again, it's one of those things where everything's very contextual. Yeah. But, you know. Yeah, that's actually. Oh yeah, sorry, go ahead. That's actually a good question because this is one of the questions I had. Like, for example.
When you're training for an event or if you were to train for an event coming up in the next six months, what are some things that you would do that you know specifically you would never do with maybe all of your athletes or maybe just a portion of your athletes? Like what are some of the things that you would incorporate? Maybe it's something in the strength realm. Maybe it's something about your recovery. Maybe you do ice baths, even though you know that there's maybe something psychological that you'll get out of it. Maybe, you know what I mean? Just something that, you know.
Is there things out there that you do a little bit differently that benefit you? Maybe not. So I would be going for a sprint competition or I would be doing a one kilometer time trial on the track. So I would go to a kilo. And the difference between what I would do with myself and what I would do with other people is I would try things that I am not sure if they would work. And it's one of those things where...
it would be something that I know would apply to everybody or I would try to apply it to myself and figure out if that kind of thing would work for others like one of the things that I did last time like last time I competed was like 2016 I think for in sprinting and I think one of the things that I was doing was I was trying out when should we go for straight up the most power and because
In sprinting on the track, your cadence is very different, like in a match sprint or on the kilo, like you're not always on the cadence that's going to make you produce the most power because you've only got one gear. So you cannot shift to make things more comfortable for yourself. So what I was doing was I was trying to figure out if I do these certain types of intervals for the most power, regardless of the cadence.
Does that still help me when I get on the track? And the answer was in a way yes and in a way no because of course it always depends. And so I figured out one of those things when we need to target specific cadences and when we don't need to. Like what kind of intervals is it just like go make the most power you can and like maybe get on the road bike and what intervals is it like you need to be in this specific range or you need to like be on your track bike.
because something is a little different and this is what we need to target. So that's really the big difference there is like I'll experiment with things that I'm not sure if they'll work and I'll try to figure out like in what context they would work or not. Yeah, that's super interesting. I think that's like the mind of it shows like your process and the way that it kind of connects to everything else that I see in you. Like you are going to...
You're going up on the cross first. I don't want to offend anyone in that statement, but that's kind of how I see it first is you're sacrificing possibly your own performance to try and understand the process more intimately for others. Yeah, yeah. No, and I've been doing that lately because I've been getting out on the bike more because the doctor gave me a heart all clear, like I'm good to go train again. And so I'm...
I'm going out and riding and I'm like regaining my aerobic fitness very, very slowly. But I'm also relearning what it's like to have these different levels of fatigue and have this different recovery timeline from like strength training and sprinting. Strength training and sprinting, like I go to the gym and I do some heavy lifting. I'll come home and like my brain will just be like fried. Like my nervous system is like, what did you do to me? My muscles are like, I'm kind of hungry.
It's very different than climbing a hill for 30 minutes and coming home and being like, I am starving and I'm going to eat everything in the fridge. I don't care if it's good for me or not. And then sitting down and being able to do work, which I can sometimes do and sometimes not, depending on... I completely missed one of my guys this weekend. He raced on Saturday and I had my weekend wrong and I was like...
Oh yeah, tomorrow, look out for this, this, and the other thing. And he's like, tomorrow? You mean on my long endurance ride where I'm not racing? Are you okay? So anyway, yeah, so that's pretty much what I would do. But I'm actually curious about one of your questions for you, which is, what's your...
area of interest or passion outside of sports stuff because you do so much stuff. I don't know if you have something outside besides like, you know. Oh, dude, it's all outside. Sports is literally like the thing that I, it's like kind of a, it's like a home for me. It's like I can always come back to it. Like I'll have, for example, I'll live with certain questions. Is it actually relative to what we're talking about? So Abdullah Zina,
was an ultra endurance cyclist and he went out and won two of these long self-supported races. I spent like three years with that question in the back of my head. You know what I mean? But I'm not focusing on sports. I'm focusing on other things, but a lot of the things in sports actually just sit in the back of my head. I'm not like actively focusing on them a lot of times. I'm always focusing on things outside of sports for the most part, whether that's like language, you know, I just, so many things. I'm always like,
It sounds, I tell people like some of the stuff that I've done and they're like, you know, how, like, what do you, what is wrong with you? Like, why don't you ever just spend time doing one thing? You know, I was super interested in, oh, where do we get into it? Neurology, psychology, you know, anything that, even gardening, you know what I mean?
Fish respond to different colors in the water and how their vision is different. You know, and it actually works in reverse, like the mercury or the water, certain colors they see better. It's just like anything, I'm just an avid learner. I love learning. And it's funny because like everyone has something really good to offer for the most part. That's something that I've always learned. Like when you're stuck, when I started in the military, you're stuck with certain individuals.
you know in a trench for how many whatever days you're doing some crappy exercise you don't want to be doing you know you find that everyone has a lot to offer you whether it's like maybe they're interested in hunting and you can learn a lot about the processes of how deer go through this cycle every year maybe it's not what you're into but you can understand a lot about a certain creature and how they do these certain things and they have these certain ways of doing something let me just think like
Yeah, like crime. I was into crime, organized crime for a long time, trying to understand how they built up these processes, you know, to integrate with the supporting resources already in their towns and kind of integrate with the supporting structures already in their municipalities and things like that. Or xenoestrogens and how they affect, you know, anything, development. I'm just like, I'm not ever
connected to one thing for a long period of time but I'm always trying to flip the page over like right now I'm really into gait understanding the gait cycle like Bill Hartman stuff and expansion and compression actually if you want to wrap your head around some crazy stuff just go watch one of his videos and you'll be like he's talking about helixes and how the cell and the individual move in the same patterns it's just anything that you know
People have something to offer I'm interested in. So like, that's why I love conversations because if someone's interested in something, I'll always have an open ear to listen and learn from them. Cause I love hearing what people, you know, have to say about whatever it is they're passionate about. Cause you'll learn something from it. Yeah. So, so you're hooked on it. So, so in a way you're like.
We both kind of ignore Dean's advice on focusing on one thing for a little bit. Exactly. But at the same time, I think it sounds like you and I both have a main focus and then we kind of nibble around the edges and kind of go, oh, this is cool. Every time I listen to the Steve Magnus podcast, it's nothing that I've ever really thought about before, but I think by the end of the episode, I'm like, wow, I really learned something. And I hope I can apply it to an athlete someday or apply it well.
Yeah, I think you have to, like if you're a person like yourself that is doing something so intensely, you have to have balance outside of that, right? You have to find kind of your learning through other means sometimes or else you'll literally go mad. I think that's why those people go mad back in the old days. They'd sit in a dungeon with candlelight and read the same thing until they lose their mind. Yeah, the people who can... Those are the people, they might have figured it out. Well, I mean, the people who can really...
focused on something for years, I think are just incredible, like old school mathematicians or scientists or whoever, people who are poor, people not from high society, from the Enlightenment or the Renaissance or anything like that. We're talking about, God, who's a good example? Leonard Euler, maybe? Just like a guy who just didn't care about money, just sat and did math.
all day, every day, and that's that. Those kinds of folks, I'm like, how do you do that? Because if I don't get a chance to switch my brain off for at least a little while every day, I pay the price after a couple days or a couple weeks. Oh, yeah. What about you? Right now, let's just say in the last couple months, what are some things that you've been exploring or honing in on or trying to understand more? Oh, in physiology?
Anything, just anything. Oh, I'm into watches. I love watches. Really? I would be into cars, but I don't have space for cars. I would get like a cheap little Miata, and that's kind of where I'm going to learn to fix it. But instead, for a while, I was taking apart and putting back together pocket watches just to learn how they all work. And I didn't have any education. I just would like...
Take a couple pieces apart, put it back together, click the things, and just go, oh, how does this? And now I understand how a watch works, but I also have an appreciation for high-level manufacturing, like Rolex and Omega. I'm like, how do they make such precision instruments on such a mass scale? Or watches like David Toon, where it's just hundreds of hours of a person polishing this one tiny little thing to a mirror shine.
That kind of stuff fascinates me. And so it would be cars, but time and money. So it's watches instead. Just something mechanical. I just like the mechanical stuff. And it's also one of those things where you can get a cool watch for a couple hundred bucks.
and you can appreciate that it's a mechanical thing and it's not like digital because I mean everybody's got a pocket watch now your phone you take it out of your pocket to look at the time you have a pocket watch pocket watches are back so they're just not they just don't operate like they used to but I think about that kind of stuff sometimes and once in a great while it helps inform something I'm working on with like a research project or physiology and I go oh that's kind of like this so I'll ask like you know the
the ML slash AI guy. I'm like, hey, can we do this? Because this is how this kind of like quartz movement operates. So can we do this to kind of like try to pull out some of this messy data? And he's like, actually, yeah, I think we could do that. Or, oh, it's not going to work because of this, that, and the other thing, but maybe we could do this instead. And so it kind of helps, but it's like anything else I'm into. And every once in a while, you just find a watch that you look at it and you go, I have to have that.
And I don't care about the movement. I don't care about anything else because at the same time, it's a trophy. It's like a car. I had a GT350 for a while and I loved that car. Then Winters in Vermont made that car not so practical. So I sold it and I made a slight profit, enough to pay for tires and oil changes and stuff like that.
because it was, you know, it was, what was it, 2021 or something like that, the big car shorters that we're still experiencing. So I was like, oh, I can get out of this for like even money? Oh, cool. All right. I'll get something practical again. So yeah. Yeah. And it's, and yeah, little, little trophies that you can appreciate for yourself. And once in a while, somebody will go, oh, hey, that's one of those, like the watch I'm wearing now is like one of those, like the watch guy watches. It's a Zinn EZM 1.1 and it's.
It's fascinating to me. The case is hardened steel. It's almost impossible to scratch. You can take a key and scratch it, and it's going to do nothing. It's super hard. And you can also time two events with it. I can do the bezel. It's a countdown bezel, so I can time a crit. And then it's got a stopwatch on it, so I can actually time two events at the same time. I can time gaps between things. That's crazy.
A phone would be so much better, but... Yeah, no, I totally understand. I lost an Instagram on a phone. Just hearing you talk about... Yeah, yeah, yeah. Hearing you talk about it, that's so interesting. Like, I don't know anything about watches, but even from the outside, just hearing you talk about it, understanding the components and the craftsmanship that goes into it. Oh, it's... It's so interesting. It's fascinating. It's super fascinating.
But not everybody's into watches, and that's fine. That's just how I relax, is that. And it used to be I would spend all my spare time with reading and researching and just focused. But after a while, I was just like, I cannot do this anymore. This amount of cognitive processing, it's hurting me. It's unhealthy.
gonna die a few years younger probably well we're almost damn we're coming up on two hours but yeah why don't we kind of take this plane in for a landing so where can folks find you yeah I just came up on Twitter I think I don't really use that much yet but that's Matthew Derosh I think maybe you'll find me there if you look D-E-S-R-O-C-H-E-S yes French Derosh and then on
On Instagram, you can find me at resiliencehbc. You can find me on YouTube at the same handle. And then my website is the same thing, resiliencehbc.ca.
I'm very new, so don't be jealous from my mass following instantly. It's coming back and trying to build it up. I think that you've got some good stuff out there already, and I think you're going to keep putting out some really good stuff. I'm going to be watching it if nobody else is. I appreciate that. It means a lot to me that you've even watched one. Yeah, man. No, it's super cool.
Our last conversation, I was like, we have a very similar mindset. We have slightly different focuses that overlap and don't overlap at some points. I'm always so fascinated to talk to you. I got so many more questions I want to ask, so we'll have to do this again. Yeah, this was great. I feel the same way. You touch on maybe two of the things, but it's good because it saves more for another time.
All right, man. Thanks for coming on. Yeah. Thanks, Cole.
All right. So I want to thank Matt for coming on to the podcast. Fascinating conversation. I had a really fun two hours this morning with him. So if you want to check him out, go to resiliencehpc on Instagram. And of course, resiliencehpc.ca is his website. So if you want to check him out, please do that. I will be following his stuff along and as his YouTube channel grows and as he puts up more stuff. So for the moment, if you head over there, I think you're going to see a lot of stuff that is fairly fascinating.
and if it's not to you you can at least see why it might be for me so go check him out and of course thank you all for listening to the show and share the show obviously
EmpiricalCycling.com slash donate is the place where you can donate to the show to support us with hosting fees and all that kind of fun stuff. We've got show notes up on the website if you want some direct links. And of course, EmpiricalCycling at gmail.com for coaching inquiries, consultation inquiries. We will answer your questions. If you're not sure if you need one, reach out and we can have a chat about it. Of course, Empirical Cycling on Instagram.
We have the weekend AMAs up in the stories and hopefully we'll see you there in a couple days. Bye.