Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore, joined as always by my co-host, Kyle Helson. Thank you, everybody, for listening as always. And we are back after a week hiatus. I am now moved and we are back on normal schedule. So thanks for listening and please subscribe to the podcast and all that normal stuff. Five-star iTunes rating. Thank you all so much for all of those or wherever you listen to podcasts. You can always share the podcast. That is probably the best thing you can do to support us. And we are ad-free. So if you want to support us with...
a couple bucks. That is great. You can do so at empiricalcycling.com slash donate. We have the show notes up on the website. We'll probably, as usual, have none for a 10-minute tips episode. And if you have any coaching and consultation inquiries, shoot me an email at empiricalcycling at gmail.com. We will be taking on all kinds of athletes at all levels. You do not have to be a cat one or a professional athlete to come sign up with us, although...
If you are, you can sign up with us too. So we can also do consultations. We'll look at any of your questions. We'll look at your training. We'll evaluate your plan. We'll kind of do whatever you want the time to be. So just shoot me an email again, empiricalcycling at gmail.com. And of course, up on Instagram at empiricalcycling.
So we have lots of memes. We have lots of Q&As on the weekends. And today's episode is actually inspired by a meme that will be going up tomorrow morning. I'm so sorry for that, but that's what happened. So if you've seen the meme, you will know what I'm talking about. If not, it's basically everything is a depends. So it's obviously now it's become like some sort of running joke, but I mean, it really is. Everything is kind of, it depends.
So, Kyle, I know you've got some thoughts on it depends, because, I mean, you're a, you know, even in your job as a physicist, it depends, you know, you wouldn't think it would depend so often because, like, you know, you've got equations and stuff, there's got to be an answer, right? Yes and no. I think that, yeah, it depends. So, you want everything in,
Life like you go through school and you want everything to have a nice answer. There's an answer key somewhere. But especially once you get into research like my regular day job, there usually isn't necessarily a right answer. There is a this is what people have done before. And so we'll try to do that or we'll try not to do that. But there isn't an answer key somewhere that says this is what you should get out of.
Research and Development. So that's in one aspect where it depends is the answer where you're like, this is what I got. Is it good or bad? It's neither. It just is. Like you can't say that, oh, that was a bad result unless, you know, something broke or something like that. And especially in physics, a null result often is still meaningful. Like they didn't find the Higgs boson for years and years and years, but it wasn't like.
Well, we suck at this and we're bad. It's that it's a hard question to answer. And so you're going to keep getting no result because it's not an easy. It's sort of like looking in the darkness and being like, yes, there's definitely nothing here. We have now confirmed it. Right. Yeah, yeah. And even more so, you can't prove a negative, right? So good luck with that. It reminds me, someone just asked me.
I volunteer for this Ask an Astrophysicist service through work and one of the questions we got today is like how do we know that light is massless versus just having such an extremely small mass that all of the light in the universe added up together weighs one gram and you're like all right well you got me there we don't we can't we cannot say that that for certain photons have exactly zero mass
That is consistent with the theory and then consistent with observation. You are right. It could have some extremely, extremely, extremely non-small, non-zero mass. And so I think that is one example where if you start to ask enough questions, you start to potentially get yourself in trouble where you either run out of your understanding and you're going to have to learn more to better understand the answer that comes next.
Or you're just going to have to accept some answer as being, you know, it's too complex, we can't explain why, but it's not always a yes or no. Or we can't measure it in physics, it would seem. Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. In physics, you run out of measurement ability, but you think about even like...
is a four-year-old asking why, right? Eventually, they exhaust their parents' ability to answer why. It always ends up with like, why are we even here? And it's like, I don't know. I can tell you why you are here, but I don't know why everybody's here. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, it sounds like R&D and physics is a lot like training in a way because in some ways, like training an individual
is also like, okay, this has happened. We're going to go down this path. And it turns out, oh, there's nothing there. That's not the right way to do this. And there are some things in training, I think, that are extremely individualizable, like tapering, for instance. A lot of people have extremely different tapering needs. And that's something that, like, for instance, Coach Katie at Nationals a couple weeks ago,
You know, previous year, she had, you know, she just did the road race, and her legs weren't so great. And this year, it was like, all right, we got to, you know, we got to beat your legs up a little bit first. So she did the time trial and the crit before the road race. And at the road race, she was like, yeah, my legs were good. This was good. And then we had, you know, of course, we come out with other things to work on.
For every person, there's a different path towards success. And we have so many tools potentially at our disposal that there's not always a right or wrong answer with which one to pick up because a lot of the time, you know, we think this is the right tool for the job. But at the same time, it may end up not being the right tool because we're like also like physics, we're heading into the darkness.
and sometimes we find out there's something there. Probably more often than in physics, we find out there's something there. I hope so. But also a lot of the time we go, oh, that wasn't right. And we make some educated guesses about the right path, but it's a long process. And so the reason why everything is, it depends all the time is because there's no right answer for everybody, for a lot of stuff.
I think there are a couple like absolutes, right? Like, like in physics, um, you know, can we say, uh, what is it? What's that like universal constant, like alpha or something, um, or LF or whatever it is that like, okay, let's say, let's say gravity. Are you thinking, okay, sure. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Like, um, gravitational force is like, uh, you know, gravitational constant times the two masses divided by R squared or something like that, right? Um, yeah.
Can we say that that's consistent in the entire universe as far as we know? And by the way, this episode has not taken the piss. I know the last physics episode we did, but this one, no, we're being serious. I will spare you a long explanation, but generally, yes, that is true. In some limit, keep in mind that GMM over R squared equals the gravitational force between two bodies is already a simplification of
General Relativity. So yes, that tends to hold true, assuming you accept certain other things as being true. Well, actually, I think that's something that I didn't anticipate being a topic here, but it might be where a generalization or a simplification, like a training rule of thumb, for instance,
would be like everybody should train sweet spot or everybody should train polarized or you should take one day a week off the bike or you should always do a long ride on Sunday or something like that. Spend all winter in your little ring. These are rules of thumb that I think are very specific examples of a very general principle.
Gravity is a specific example of general relativity. Did I get that right? Yeah, close enough. Okay. I'll take close enough. And so I think part of it is we need to figure out what an individual needs while also thinking about the underlying universal principles.
So for instance, like general aerobic stimulus versus race specific stuff. We can use something like VO2 max and cadence, for example. Like when you are doing VO2 max intervals and the idea, at least the way we do it, the idea is to raise VO2 max, you know, high cadence. Great. Do you race like this? No. But this is an example of how we can use
you know underlying principles to hopefully improve the stimulus on the other hand if you are going to do these efforts going into like a pursuit on the track okay maybe now it's a little more specific you know but it may not be like you may actually be doing all of your like you know quote-unquote vo2 power zones if we want to you know use that shorthand it may be at like 70 75 80 rpm
Do you need to train that? It depends. Some people do, some people don't. So it's all about individualization, right? Yeah. I think another thing within there is you can imagine that the statement of VO2 max is good generally. That's true. If you have aerobic racing, aerobic sports, VO2 max is good. And so does that mean you should train VO2 max? Probably.
Does that mean you should train VO2max at the same specific time as some other person every year? No. Yeah. Or does everybody need to train VO2max? No. Right? Like, Teddy Pigachar is probably not doing a lot of VO2max training. You know, if your VO2max is like, okay, actually, here's a good question. It's like, if your VO2max is like 80, 85, super high, right? Not world class, or not, well, world class, you know.
God. At that level, it's like you certainly could be riding world-class events. But like, you know, in terms of like the upper echelon, the very top 1% of 1% tier of VO2 Max scores are in like the mid to like what, high 90s? I don't think anybody's cracked 100 yet, have they? I don't think so. Like a, you know, like a Husky.
Race Husky for the Editarod has a VO2 Max of like 250, okay? One day we'll maybe find somebody at the one-half Husky VO2 Max level. But here's a good question is, does somebody have potential to improve their VO2 Max if it's already very high? And the same thing goes with threshold and stuff like that. And this is where...
Having a sense of the individual's both short-term and long-term goals and having a sense of their potential to improve, I think, is another component here. Because with somebody like I'm training Corey, and Corey has a ridiculously high FTP, right? Like, you know, when he started with me, it was probably 380, 390, maybe 400, something like that.
Do some training. And now if you have one way of looking at this, you might say 400 watt FTP. Oh man, guy's got no headroom, right? This is, this is all he's probably got. If you had to max, like what, mid 80, something like that. Okay. On the other hand, you don't know if he's got potential there or not. And so that's one of those things where it's worth trying.
and seeing what comes out the other side, right? And in the instance where we get that teeter-totter effect of like VO2 max and FTP, where like, you know, we can get somebody to time trial better. If you do more threshold, they'll race better if you do more threshold. Or if you do more VO2s, they'll like pursuit better on the track. They'll do shorter efforts better, like hill climbs, things like that. You know, UK type hill climbs.
Once we see that teeter-totter, okay, now we're definitely sure that this is all this person has. On the other hand, if we see long-term improvements, like something really bumps up and it sticks, okay, now we have found some really, really good levels of improvement. And that's kind of the individualization thing, right? So like, does everybody need to do VO2max? I would say it's worth trying.
But it's not a hard rule of thumb. So that's another example of the individualizing things. Yeah. And the other thing I would imagine there, too, with individualizing, say you buy some cookie cutter plan and it says you're going to do eight weeks of VO2s or something going into, you know, coming off of doing a lot of threshold and getting to higher intensities. If you're just going to do this cookie cutter plan, you're just going to be like, head down, going to do these eight weeks of training.
Whereas if you could individualize it, you maybe take a look two, three weeks in and say, is this actually doing what you want it to do? And then you say, if yes, maybe keep going. If not, maybe consider not keeping going. It's like one of those choose your own adventure books. Right, yeah, because you expect, and I think people maybe don't consider this enough, is that
You shouldn't be in this sort of situation where you put in 13, 14, 15, some really long number weeks of work over which you see like no improvement just thinking that, oh, but I'm tired. I'm just going to do all this work. And then by the time taper comes, like all this fitness will magically appear. Like if you don't see hints of yourself getting faster after putting in a significant amount of training or getting fitter or whatever your metric is.
The odds that it magically appears after you taper or peak or whatever are low. It's not impossible. You may just be so far in the hole that you need. But that is where this individualization comes of like, well, this program says a VO2 block is eight weeks. So does that mean that I always do VO2s for eight weeks? No.
It depends. Someone asks, I'm 12 weeks away from my first race, what should I do? And they just ask you that, right? And you're like, I know nothing about what you've been doing. Kyle, you're in my Instagram DMs, don't lie. That's probably the most common question I get. And it's like asking, it's like if your parents come to you because they don't understand why their iPad's broken, go like, it's broken, I can't figure it out. And you're like...
I don't know. I haven't seen what you were doing. You can't just present me this broken piece of electronics and be like, fix it. Yeah, some symptoms would be nice. Yeah, I think... Oh, fuck. What were we just talking about? Individualization, trying, not trying. Oh, tapering. Yeah, seeing results. Yeah. Okay, yeah. Well, and that's... I think that's interesting because that's...
kind of what we do as coaches. Well, not you. You refuse to coach anybody. Every time I ask you, Kyle, you want to write a couple of swim workouts? Flat no. No. But yeah, it's like individualizing things and having that objective point of view is always nice. But also, it's like you're talking about with a VO2 max block or something.
being able to see if improvements are happening or to see if it's more fatigued than it's worth. Like, are we really just banging our heads against the wall? Like, is nothing happening here? I've certainly seen that and I've made the call like, okay, we're going to stop this block unless you do X, Y, Z and we see the next workout just like have, you know, this thing that we're looking for. And if it doesn't happen, okay, pull the plug. If it does,
Great, okay, now we've figured out what needs to happen and we're going to keep going. So, you know, so it's like, you know, you're steering the ship at the same time, you're thinking about the long term of, you know, is this stimulus, you know, is this worth the fatigue? Is this like, are we going to get the adaptation that we want out of this? Or is it better for doing something else? And, you know, this is one of those things where, you know, what, looking at what somebody's done in the past,
is good. And of course, a lot of the times, like for instance, when we start training a new client here, a lot of the times they've never really trained the way that we would train somebody. And so it's worth trying a combination, trying our way, trying their old way, putting the pieces together of like, what is the best thing for this person? And I've certainly got a couple of clients now where
you know you know they're a new territory in terms of fitness and it's kind of like you know kind of like relearning to race in some ways because it's like you know you're not tired what everybody else is and normally you'd be as tired as them like you know or it's like oh suddenly I can actually make this climb with the group oh my god that's that's new or oh my god I can actually roll this breakaway for 100 kilometers like
Or maybe like, oh, I'm making it to the sprint, but I'm getting dusted. Is it time to work on the sprint? Okay, cool. Let's talk about it. Yeah, that makes sense. I think that's interesting because that draws the analogy I would draw from there is like debugging or figuring out why something doesn't work. Like, oh, your computer doesn't work, your dryer doesn't work, your air conditioner, whatever, something like that.
You kind of have to have a good survey of all of the different things that could go wrong or the things that you try. And then you try those things, right? And they help to inform the thing that you do next and then the thing that you do next and the thing that you do next. If you were just presented with like, oh, this dryer doesn't work.
Well, it could be hundreds of things wrong, right? And so if you knew nothing, you would maybe use your previous experience and say like, oh, well, I know that this is a very common way that dryers break. Like maybe the breaker is tripped or something, right? And so you start with those things, which like you said, like, oh, maybe we'll try the VO2 max. And if it works, great. And if it doesn't, go on to the next thing.
And so that's like if you could somehow program a way to, you know, oh, you could always fix something by following these seven steps. And every time it will magically fix this like broken piece of electronics or something like that. That also implies that the same thing breaks every time. Right, right. Or that the same steps fix a multitude of things. And assuming those steps aren't like complete overhaul. Couldn't figure out what was wrong with the engine. So we put a new one in and it works great.
right? Like obviously you can't do that with sports training, but yeah, that's funny. Sorry. Yeah. Sorry. You and I keep talking over each other because we've got like a, like a one second delay between us that comes out in the recording. And it sounds like, it sounds like both of us are like, like taking a second to think about the joke the other person made, like in real time, it sounds normal. So, okay. Sorry about that.
So I think another aspect to think about with this in terms of debugging training, actually that's such a great analogy. I don't know how to debug anything, but I do know how to fix some things. So if we're going to debug training, I think one of the other big individualization things is that recovery.
How fast somebody recovers from a certain thing, like either like a bounce back from a big training block or just like day-to-day stuff. Like, you know, if you're doing like VO2max work, how fast do you recover from it? If you're doing race-specific work, if you're doing like hill reps, can you do threshold the next day? A lot of people can't.
but a lot of people can do big endurance ride and so you know there's like I think there's like a middle ground you know in coaching there's like a middle ground I expect like oh okay it'll probably go like this based on what I've seen from other people and based on what I know about this person so far but I'm always ready to be wrong you know and I'm wrong a lot and that's I think that's okay but you know being wrong is sort of like in
Like I said before, I used to be a carpenter. And one of the sayings that we had in carpentry is that everybody's going to make a mistake. Well, we didn't say it politely like that. But what matters, what makes a real professional is how you fix it. And I think that that's kind of part of the it depends.
You can be wrong, but what matters is how you pick yourself up from either this workout or this training block or this race and think about how do I fix this going forward. So with regards to recovery, there are some principles that work pretty much universally.
Food, and Sleep. It's pretty simple. I've thought about doing a podcast on Recovery so much, but it's going to be like, eat and sleep, go away. Go do that. It's going to be really like five minutes long. And then like, I don't know, play a metal album for 45 minutes after that. Yeah. I think that the other big thing that people...
Don't necessarily take into account right away when they think about individualization is the fact that most of us aren't professional athletes and we have a lot of other things competing for our time and our recovery and our mental energy, all this stuff that if you're just thinking, oh, I'll just like chug along and put my head down and not think about.
changing this training plan at all, even though I had a shit day at work and I'm beat up and or I stayed really late and I'm super tired. I'm getting on a bike two hours after I normally do. I ate like shit and all this stuff like that's a recipe for disaster. Like like not saying that you can't get away with it because certainly, you know, sometimes those things happen and that's fine. But in terms of individualization, no one.
Outside of you, and maybe not even you, can predict what next week of work is going to be or life or school or whatever is going to happen. And so to not consider those things when forming a training plan or assuming that maybe you do have a job. I don't know. Maybe you do have a cushy job where you know exactly what it's going to be every day and it's never different. That sounds nice. Yeah. Or would it be? But for the vast majority of people.
Myself included, you don't have that luxury. And so individualization plays a big role in figuring out like, well, you could try to slog through this workout or are you just going to come out worse actually because you slept poorly or something, you know, up late, working, whatever. Yeah. And that's kind of one of those like day-to-day things. That's why.
We don't have, like, contact restrictions, really. And, you know, all of our coaches, we do our damnedest to check training peaks, you know, at least once a day, if not a couple times, and, like, go through everybody's workouts and, like, you know, help steer the ship day to day because that's kind of what, you know, what everything kind of hinges on in the long term. It's like, you know, it's sort of like a course correction, like a short-term course correction.
I've never sailed anything in my life, but I imagine if you were sailing, I don't know why I went to that. All right. Let's say you're walking in a big field, right? And you are trying to get to something on the other side that you cannot see. And you start off in the right direction, right? Nobody's path is 100% straight. I think I saw this on Mythbusters once. And so having a guidepost...
like that you can see far away is helpful where you can look at it and go, oh, I need to go this direction. I need to go this direction. You can keep heading towards it and it's not going to be a straight path. It'll be a little sinusoidal and whatnot, but it's going to be in the right direction, right? And if you have something that gets bumped off the track, now if you just...
If you've got a blindfold on, you just keep going in that direction, you might end up right back where you started. You might end up on the other side of the globe having totally missed the thing that you were going for. It could go wrong in a thousand different ways. And so making sure that all the little things, like especially with, like you said, stress. Stress is a big one. It's a huge one, especially day-to-day with work and family and relationships.
Equipment failures, that's a big one for a lot of people. DI2 blip shifters, please, if you could all just work within the two weeks before people's time trials, it would be excellent. Big source of stress. Multiple complaints this year already. So if that could just work, can we debug those? You're not going to like the answer.
I might love the answer. Millions of wires. No wireless anything. Wires connecting everything. Hard soldered wires from point to point. It's not the worst idea. Really heavy, rugged military connectors connecting everything. Like bayonet and thread together so they can't come out or vibrate loose. And then you can wrench it really tight on the mechanism and it's going to be a direct connection all the way up to your handlebars. How come somebody doesn't invent that?
Yeah. Yeah. So the individualization thing can also go day to day where like, okay, today was really stressful. Tomorrow's going to be stressful. This week's going to be stressful. You're sleeping like shit. You're not eating well. Okay. We're going to like totally delete this week, you know? And like, cause if you go with like your, you know, hard training plan going ahead, that's, you know, next three weeks.
like your hardest training block of the year coincides with your worst three weeks of work and like family stuff. And let's say you're moving. Why not? Um, everything's going to go wrong for you and you are going to like, you were going to rush to your bike. You're not going to be well fed. You're going to be super stressed and everything's going to go wrong. So that's one of those things. Like, should you do this? But this is an, maybe this is a universal. No, you should probably shouldn't do that. The original training week.
That's another version of it depends where whatever you plan initially, however many weeks out, it's probably not going to look exactly like that. Like the number of times it does, I think the most I've planned out for anybody in the last couple of years has been like three or four weeks. And every single time I've done that, I've had to change at least two weeks worth of those workouts.
I think that's another reason that it depends is that this was assuming that those two weeks or however many weeks didn't go well. But say they go really well and say you're surprised. You're like, oh, actually, this went really well. So now we can do something else, right? If you also make great gains, that doesn't always have to be negative. You don't always have to be beat down because life is slowly crushing your soul.
And it could be positive, too. And so that's another way where it depends. Like, oh, I just finished this VO2 max block. Oh, it went better than expected? Oh, well, that means that maybe we do this next. Or that means maybe you went really hard, you got really fit, but now you're actually more tired than you thought you would be. So maybe then you add more rest instead. Who knows? Yes, thank you. So yeah, so like when things go positively,
A lot of the time, that's actually good confirmatory evidence of whatever I think is happening and whatever plan I've had for this person. It's going better than expected, which means they're responding to the training even better than expected, which usually doesn't change the plan. It doesn't change the kind of pathway that I've got laid out in my head for them. But it just means that, like, okay, I can actually start to relax with this person.
I can have only, you know how like on a race day, having a little bit of nerves is always good. I always have like a little bit of nerves when I'm coaching somebody because I'm always ready to like, Oh, what's going wrong here? What, what am I, what am I missing when things are going right? What, what like undercurrent is going to like really bring this plan down? I'm always thinking about that. Um, and so when things are going well, I like to keep that little bit of nerves just in case.
But yeah, like you said, when things go well, it's like, can we lean harder into this is a question that you might be wondering. And I'm not sure sometimes that we can or even should. Because if things are going well, more of the same might not be beneficial. You know what I mean? Yeah. I also think that oftentimes people only step back and say, what's going wrong? Or what should I do next when things go poorly?
They don't, you know, they'll, you'll quickly jump over a success of, oh, that was great. I trained really well. I made a lot of improvement. On to the next thing. Not, is doing better than expected, like consistent with what I had planned and what I want to do next or whatever. Yeah. The, so I think that, and that's probably human nature, right? Like we tend to focus on.
the negative outcomes more than the positive ones. Lots of people out there can recall very embarrassing things they did in elementary school or something, but they probably can't remember that time that the teacher said, oh, you had the best essay or whatever for your fourth grade class or whatever. Oh, God, yeah.
Oh, how many people listening to this just like had that flashback of just like you were cringing at yourself at what you did or said. Anyway. So I think that. Yeah, sorry. So I think that with the training and with the it depends, like some people get probably get a little frustrated or get disappointed. It's a little anticlimactic when you always say it depends. But I had a friend once say that.
Having someone say, okay, it depends, is the sign of someone being an expert when you ask them a question? Because all of a sudden, they think of all of these different factors and can't immediately give you an answer without knowing more information. Whereas if you aren't aware of all these different factors, you think like, oh, if I think that periodization means I have to do...
Long Aerobic Stuff, then Sweet Spotter Threshold, then VO2 Max, and then like, you know, race, then I think I got done with, hey coach, I got done with my VO2 Max, like what's next? Oh, well, you must be close to racing, right? Because you always do VO2 Max when you're closer to races. And so the part of that is that training is complex. And the other part is hopefully that
A lot of different things are going into what is deciding your next training. So when you ask this person, when a person asks in your Instagram stories or whatever, my training's not going well. Like, what's wrong? There are so many things that can go into that. It's so hard. You're not trying to blow people off. You're not trying to be flippant or something like that where you're just like, ah. Well, what I should do more often is say, reach out for a consultation because we will figure this out. Yeah.
And obviously Instagram questions aren't great because you can only fit like 100 characters or whatever into one of those question and answer boxes. So it's obviously would be very different if it was someone you were talking to on the phone or something like that. Yeah, for sure. I have one more example. Everybody should ride more. This is another It Depends. I was just thinking before we started recording, this is not an It Depends. Everybody should just ride more. And that's better for a rubric adaptation. It's good, right?
That is not always the case. If you're riding too hard for your endurance rides, you should not ride more. More junk time. Man, all right, we should do the next 10 minute tips on junk miles. But yeah, that's another one of those things where I was like, yeah, pretty much the only universal it doesn't depend is like, you know, how you execute certain types of intervals to get certain adaptation, right? Like the
Like for instance, FTP. The adaptation we get on the other side is going to differ for certain people and especially where you are in training, right? Like if you are just getting off your couch and you start doing FTP work, your FTP is going to go up and that's great. But if you are super, super, super well trained, like let's imagine like, you know, you're a Roglic or something. If you do FTP work, is your FTP going to go up?
I would love it if that were the case, but probably not. Seven watts per kilo at FTP. Right? But you can definitely build out your TTE. And that is a pretty universal principle. And so, you know, so that's another one of those examples of it depends and it may not depend sometimes. But I did ask on the Instagrams, I said that we were going to do an it depends episode. And I think a lot of people are.
Frankly, they're having fun with us. But I had some really interesting questions on it depends and training individualization. So here's a good question. Does fiber size depend on slow twitch and fast twitch fibers? This is also, it depends. Very good question. Because last time I talked to an actual muscle physiologist, he said that...
that a lot of the time endurance athletes have larger slow twitch fibers than fast twitch fibers because their fast twitch fibers are just not trained, right? If you look at an average sedentary person, okay, these fast twitch fibers are most likely, almost guaranteed to be bigger than their slow twitch. If you look at strength trained people like you and me, we're going to see the same thing. But in endurance trained people, like you look at a triathlete or a marathon or an ultra distance runner or something like that, it's very likely,
According to what I've been told by an expert, so I'm putting my faith in this, that you are going to find slow twitch fibers larger than fast twitch fibers. And especially once you start to taper and those fibers start to grow, like yes, fibers actually hypertrophy during a taper because they are now filling with glycogen and just their raw size is what we, you know, muscle fibers getting bigger, hypertrophy. So that's one of those things where it does indeed depend.
That's interesting too because I think people probably normally associate hypertrophy and fiber size with, yeah, people lifting weights and lifting weights tends to, it hits all the fibers but also really hits the fast twitch ones because you got to produce a lot of force and so that may be counterintuitive to some people. Yeah. But all fibers can grow. It'd be weird if some of them couldn't. Actually, for people like you and me, we probably cannot grow our slow twitch fibers.
All three that we have left. I was going to say, I'm going to go do sets of like, you know, 50 squats or something and see. Yeah, but like, it's one of those funny things because for hypertrophy, we're looking for a certain combination of factors. And if we are just doing stuff that primarily recruits slow twitch fibers, like, you know, doing sets of, I don't know, a thousand reps on a bicycle.
You know, like it's going to work initially, but then it's going to stop. And the reason it's working is because it's just filling with glycogen and whatever. So anyway, all right, here's another good, it depends. 80 kilos and 280 FTP. Can I ever get to four watts per kilo? If you're super, super tall, right? 80 kilos is about as slim as you're ever going to get. Let's say you're like, you know.
8% body fat, just like shredded. Well, if you're a cyclist, maybe you're not shredded. You are so T-Rex. So maybe you just don't have the genetic potential to get there, or maybe you don't have the time to do the training to get there. We don't know what exactly is...
preventing your progress, but you might be able to get there, right? Because if you're like 20% body fat and you're super muscular, especially, you know, upper body, you don't need that to ride a bike. Come on. Yeah. So dieting is probably a good idea. And you may be able to get to four watts per kilo. Yeah. And I think that, yeah, just height and weight stats are one of the things where, you know, people maybe are trying to compare themselves to
has pros, heights, and weights, and things like that. And you're like, that doesn't kind of work so much. You want it to be like, oh, Pogaccia is whatever, 5'10 and 140 pounds. So if I just get to be 5'10 and 140 pounds, I too can have a 400-watt FTP. Unfortunately, it's not that. That is such the middle-of-the-road GC.
like Tour de France GC winner profile, isn't it? Because like that also describes like Contador, that describes Nibali, et cetera, et cetera. So yeah, fascinating. Does it always depend because you still got to make money with your coaching biz? I mean, I think in a way, okay, here's the thing. There's two sides to this. I think the first thing is going back to one of the things you said before, Kyle.
And saying it depends is the sign of being an expert. I think also non-experts can just now start saying, it depends, and then have nothing to back it up. So just to try to look like experts, if you go, it depends, and you go hand-wavy stuff, like I got at the end of Calc 2 about Stokes' theorem, and I'm like, I want to learn it. And they're like, nah, you just, nah. Although I know that person is an expert in math way more than me.
I think the other thing is that when you do have a podcast like this and you are trying to show people the inner workings of training and the inner workings of the physiology behind it, I think people out there start to appreciate just how much stuff there is to have it depends on.
If you're burning more fat, does that make you a better fat burner? It depends. It really depends. And now we've done a whole bunch of podcast episodes. We're going to do a wrap-up episode on the metabolism, by the way. I have to start writing that now that I have all three of my brain cells firing on all one cylinder again. But yeah, it's like...
but the it depends thing is like that's how we coach that's how we found to get the best out of people is to like really individualize everything and not do any like stock cookie cutter training plans as much as I want to have something like that as a passive source of income that would be great but I don't think I could actually count as putting my face and my name on something like that because I
Could not guarantee it's going to go well. And I honestly wouldn't be able to live with myself for stuff like that. So I'd rather work harder at everything else. I think the other thing, too, is that I would hope that if you asked another coach a similarly vague question, they would also not just be like, oh, yes, you have to do X, Y, and Z. I would actually hope that you get
is a similarly complex answer where, well, you've only told me two facts about what you are, your height and your weight, and now you want me to know, your height and your weight and your FTP, and now you want me to be able to predict your training future? Well, it depends, right? I bet he knew that when he asked that question. The very nature of just some of these things of...
you've been staring at this a lot like you've been looking at your data you know all of your training history already whereas when you go up to a person who doesn't know all of these things already they don't know all of the extra information you know so to have the unless they've osmosis it I guess through the air from your brain it depends may just simply be because you need to tell them more information and then maybe there is a
clear answer, but just showing up and being like, here are two facts about myself. Where will I be in 30 years? Hopefully in a good place. Yeah, no, I think, yeah, I think you're right. So hopefully it is, yeah, it's a little tongue in cheek and it's funny because like, listen to the next episode to hear more. It depends.
But it's that everybody is an individual and everybody's needs are a little different and how everybody moves forward, everything's a little different. It's like you could tell people, all right, do two threshold workouts and two long rides this week and three easy days. Okay, great. When should I do them? Okay, it depends. Tell me about your life, right? You can start with something that seems generally individualizable, but at some point,
isn't because it doesn't work for everybody. It's sort of like, okay, I can't do a long ride. I've got two hours. That's the longest I can go. All right, now we've got more decisions to make. Yeah. Or it'd be like if you commute to work every day, you commute generally the same way, but you can't be like, okay, at...
9.05, I get in the car and I drive and then I get in this lane and then I turn left here and then I get in this lane and this road and I'm in this lane for 15 minutes and then I switch over to this lane. Yeah, well this time there's construction in that lane and it's shut down. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. So yes, everyone is going toward the same, generally the same place, like being fitter, being faster, hopefully winning bike races or doing well in bike races.
but and and some of those pieces may be the same like you may be taking similar roads things like that but it depends because all those things could pop up like when you're driving to work that don't normally happen or or there are more people on the road today because there's a construction somewhere else or whatever yeah you know all right here's a good one um and I don't have an answer off the top of my head for this this is a thinker what's one thing it depends on that people often forget
Yeah, exactly. I don't know. Ah, crap. People often forget. Ah, that it, how about, how about that it's still, some part of it still should be fun. Like, like, if you, if you don't like the workouts and don't like, and get nervous and don't like the racing and, you know, if you don't like the process and don't like the thing that you're working toward, like, you should maybe step back. I love that. Same answer.
Perfect. Yeah. That's great. What's the best way to find out the answer to it depends? I think this one's actually easy. I think you need to think about what makes your individual circumstances unique and also what are the underlying principles of what you are trying to do, right? Like if you are trying to like raise your FTP.
And let's say you have somebody asked me this recently. They said, I have my weeks are like on off. I can do 10 hours and then I have infinite time to train like alternating weeks. And I was like, oh, that's interesting. And they said, but somebody told me a long time ago that I shouldn't do the longer weeks because it's not going to help. I should just like just keep my consistent 10 hours.
Is this right? And in this individual's circumstance, I said no. I disagreed with that. If you can ride more, you should ride more even if it's every other week. Like when people have, you know, like let's say somebody gets two vacation weeks a year. God, America sucks, right? And you use both of them to do like a 25-hour training week.
Awesome, right? People still see benefits from this stuff. And so the underlying principle of the stimulus, of the riding more will help you out in the long term, like this applies very much. And what doesn't apply is what you might think about is good training consistency.
Right? So like training consistency is like nailing your workouts week to week and keeping them rather consistent. So that means two hours on Thursdays instead of like two hours and then six hours alternating Thursdays. Ah, yeah. You know, and so the underlying principle is you can add more aerobic stimulation and the more you get over the course of a year or so, right? This is the all training is base training theorem.
The better it's going to be for you in the long term. And I've found this to be more universally true. And so that's an example of what makes your circumstances unique and what are the underlying principles. Yeah, I like that. And I think, keep in mind too, like, yeah, like everyone's life is a little bit different. Like you have to help yourself or help your coach or whomever think about these things that...
that maybe seem normal day-to-day to you, but maybe are not normal day-to-day for everyone else. Yeah. Here's an interesting one. What training aspects are not, it depends, but are absolutes? Oh, we kind of touched on this. This person lists, for example, sleep, carbs, coffee, Sith. What's Sith? Only the Sith deal in absolutes, which is a hilarious oxymoron in and of itself. It's in, what's Star Wars? I forget what.
It's in one of the prequels Oh, I don't think I watched those I saw the Yoda battle on YouTube and that was awesome but that was about it Okay, so sleep and carbs I think are absolutes There's really no question about that I think other absolutes are like what constitutes training stimulus
and they're the same between people. I think one of the things that does depend between people is how well they respond to high intensity stuff and how, you know, kind of tapering stuff and opening up the legs kind of stuff, you know, kind of like a rest strategy of like, oh, if you rest into your race, some people are going to have amazing legs and some people are going to have garbage legs and you've got to figure out which one you are.
But when we're looking at what constitutes good VO2max training, it's like if you are looking for certain stimuli, it's going to be pretty universal. Maybe you're too old for that stimulus to really work on you. If you're 70, you're doing VO2max training. If you've been training for a little while, chances are you're probably not going to be able to raise your VO2max so much. You're really just trying to keep it from dropping too much for the next year at that age.
if we should be so lucky to get there. But yeah, that's the kind of thing where it's like, what makes you an individual and what is the underlying principle? The underlying principle stuff is fairly universal. Yeah, I was going to say, yeah, the other things that are not, it depends, are like the energy systems that your body relies on. Yes.
It seems like one of those oxymorons almost where you're not going to be extraordinary in the sense that for some reason aerobic volume doesn't make this person, riding their bike aerobically doesn't make this person aerobically fitter. That's not going to happen. You don't violate some fundamental laws, but your situation is going to be unique.
So more It Depends stuff from people. Oh, here's a good one. Went to train general adaptations versus race specificity. I kind of like this one because I remember a long, long time ago, probably 2013 or 14, one of my friends in like January or February, his coach was giving him a lot of like one minute efforts. The reason is like in the season or just in general, his one minute like power to weight or whatever it is like.
they determined that that was a weakness. And so he's going to spend six months, you know, once or twice a week hammering one minute intervals in addition to everything else. Um, and he had a really good race season. Is that the right approach? I mean, he probably had, uh, he probably tapped out his anaerobic capacity after a little bit, but, um, you know, it might've helped to some degree. Um, but it's one of those things where
If it worked, I would, you know, well, you know, actually, no, he didn't do it for six months. He did it for like a couple months, then he started racing and then they cut it out. So that made sense. Yeah. Oh, yeah. I mean, but it's like in the long, long term, what's funny about like something like a one minute power is something like FTP can really help your one minute power. The number of people who like post a one minute PR.
After like not doing one minute efforts or any kind of anaerobic capacity work and just doing like endurance and threshold, huge number. Like that's an almost universal one right there. But it's funny because, you know, it's something that you wouldn't expect. But when you are actually, okay, so back to the point. When you are actually trying to train race specificity, you need to think about
Again, what is the underlying limiter of this thing? So if it's your one-minute power, for instance, you might think of something like buffering capacity, something like that. Maybe it's max power. Maybe it's muscle mass. And so those are three limiters off the top of my head. So you're going to think about how do I train this, that, and the other thing. And what is the timeline of training? Because if you want to train muscle mass, like if you want more muscle mass, you want better one-minute power for your...
race in June, you're going to have to start last November. Right. Yeah. And so that's one of those things where sometimes you need to train certain aspects of your limiter a long time in advance and other times less time in advance, right? Like if it's like you need to get better at positioning in a crit, start racing crits.
Once a week, just go race. Work on your process goals. Forget about the result. Work on, okay, today I'm going to work on putting my handlebars in front of somebody else's before a corner. Like, that's it. That's the whole game. I'm going to sit in the middle of the pack, which I'm uncomfortable with, and I'm going to just practice moving up one spot. Like, that can be your whole workout. And hopefully it's only like, you know, 15 bucks to enter a practice crit like that or something.
But, you know, that's one of those things where, you know, because it's a it's something that's not going to cost you in terms of, you know, in terms of workouts, like that's a really good high intensity workout. And you could just do endurance riding and sweet spot or whatever on top of that. And you're going to have yourself a really good training week. How long you do that? Now, that's another question. But it's one of those things where depending on what you need to work on.
for your limiters. Like if it's like, oh, I need more FTP. Everyone needs more FTP. Okay. So now we need to think about like in the long term, like we might think of in terms of years with this kind of stuff and endurance, repeatability. So that's a big, it depends. I like that one. The only thing I would add to that is also
Once you've figured out what the limiters are, you also have to figure out how to tell which the limiter is the problem. Muscle mass may be an obvious one. If you've got 30-inch thighs, well, okay, muscle mass is probably not the problem. But if you've never thought about these limiters before, then taking a step back and figuring out which one, because you might have the same FTP as your buddy, and you both kind of look the same.
But one of you has 50 watts more for a minute than the other person. Like, well, you got to start going down the list of like, okay, what are the differences? How can we explain these things? Yeah. Here's another one. Cadence, spin to win or grind it out? It depends. Well, all right. So here's another good it depends. If you are a track racer.
and you are locked into a certain gear and cadence and you need to accelerate at a certain rate, for instance. It's like, all right, Kyle, let's say you go to a Cat 3 scratch race and you're on 110 gear inches. Are you going to have a good day or a bad day? Probably a bad day. So let's go into why would that be a bad day? So 110 for...
certainly for your local Cat 3 like Wednesday night track racing is going to be a little on the big side maybe by over 10 inches so your cadence at maximum speed your cadence is probably going to be pretty comfortable like coming into the sprint you may not even be tapped out but if this race slows down or speeds up or is surgy or you try to you are not riding at this constant comfortable cadence the whole time
You're going to have to try to accelerate this pretty big gear up from probably a low-ish cadence, like 60, 70, 80 RPMs, try to get back up to speed. And so that is going to be very fatiguing just because you have to, it's like trying to do, you know.
Low Cadence Climbing and then starting up when you slow way down and then all of a sudden that first couple of pedal strokes back if you're doing low cadence climbing is really hard because you have no momentum and you have to generate a lot of force. And that just gets very tiring. And so that's maybe not a good choice. Yeah. And so that's why for certain races,
will target cadence, will target high cadence so that people can get more comfortable with that kind of thing. And once they're comfortable with it, stay comfortable. It's like a lot of the time heading into a sprint, if you're a little undergeared in a track race, you might be pushing 150 RPM. And you should hopefully be fairly comfortable with that. If you feel like you're out of control,
You have no brakes on the track. You probably should sit that one out. It's like, uh-oh, this is a little too fast for me. I can't control my bike. But it's one of those things where if you are always aiming to, like let's say in a road race, if you're always aiming to have your gear just a little too small, you are actually robbing yourself of power. Your body has a very good intuitive sense of where it makes the most power.
It's like, I don't know if I've ever talked about this on the podcast before. I might have. It's like, there's an example from developmental biology of gerboas. And they have giant long rear legs. And they hop, right? But if you block a certain gene that elongates the rear legs, they end up like small. They look like hamsters or something. And they walk.
So the hopping is not actually programmed in their brains. Their brains figures out what is the most efficient way to go forward. Like you ever seen one of those goats born without front legs or like born without hind legs and it's just comfortable walking on the two legs? Let's figure that out. It's not ingrained. And that's the same thing with your body. Like if you start, if you're trying to like just make the most power possible,
You need to look at where are you comfortable and what is your body telling you is comfortable. And that's like, that is so key. Like when, for instance, like Corey, time trialist, here's a good example. When I look at his cadence, like around threshold, you know, he's doing 430 some odd watts. It's amazing, right? It's like, he's like right, like bang on.
in like a very narrow cadence range and has been the whole time. It's like he knows where he makes the most power. He just nails it and that's it. Once we start seeing an issue, for instance, like if he's like, you know, if there's like a climb on a course for a time trial and suddenly he's grinding out at like 60 RPM, okay, overgeared. Now we need to start thinking about gearing.
And that's an easy way to think, okay, we need to bring this cadence up on the low range. Like, you know, and so sometimes, so it's one of those like race specific things is what it depends on. If you are not able to put out the power in your comfortable range, first look at your gearing.
in some places where that's not possible like on the track or if like the road is super steep okay now you might want to think about adding that specific aspect into your training yeah another thing I would say is just like the rule of always riding the little ring all winter I would avoid fun little sayings like spin to win if you don't have a good reason for it like no reason to modern bikes have what 20
Well, 22, sometimes 24 gears on them. I know not all of them are unique individual gears. Some of them overlap. But you have a lot of choices. So don't limit yourself to not using these things that you already have because you think that this fun saying says you should. Even though it is fun and it's nice. Who doesn't like fun sayings? But it's silly to think that, oh,
And this nice rule of thumb tells me how I should race my bike all the time. Yeah. All right. Here's, let's see. Hold on. I want to check. I think this might be the last one. Yeah. Question is, train high VLA max athletes differently than low VLA max athletes. Okay. So first thing to address is VLA max isn't really real.
It doesn't determine anything VLA Max is primarily determined by sprint power and it is subsequently modified by aerobic training but that's going to be about it and there's nothing else so we should rephrase this question in something a little more universal which is should we train
athletes with a big sprint differently than we train athletes without a big sprint. Let's keep it to just like road racing. And given the range of athletes that I train, I would say... I was about to say it's the same, but no, it does depend.
I caught myself so close to a real answer. Sorry, everybody. It was right on the cusp there. So it really depends on their winning strategy and what their job is on the team. Like one of my pros, for instance, he's got a giant sprint, but he's also got a giant engine. And a lot of the time his job is to sit on the front of the race or lead somebody out. He's not the chosen guy to win.
and that's okay. That's his job. And so we're not really thinking about, okay, how do we get you to win? Cause that's, that's like not in his job description. If it were okay, we would be training certain types of efforts and we would maybe taper him into a race a little differently. He would race it differently too. So there's a couple of things there, but when it comes to aerobic training,
just comes to aerobic training and aerobic stimulus. The answer is no, there's no difference. What works with a good sprinter works with somebody without a big sprint. Like a 2000 watt sprinter should train their FTP the same way that a thousand watt sprinter trains their FTP. Like that's it. You might want to modify certain things.
like if you're doing threshold with accelerations or something like that, you're going to tell that good sprinter, maybe you shouldn't send it so hard. Yeah. I can see that going really badly, really quickly. Yeah. But besides that kind of stuff, no. A 20-hour, 30-hour training week is the same for a good sprinter as the same for a bad sprinter.
The aerobic stimulus, if we go down the list of what stimulates aerobic adaptation, it's fairly universal. And being able to just produce more force in itself, which is really what sprinting is, just being able to instantaneously put out more power, contract your muscles harder, and there's a laundry list of reasons you could do that. That doesn't change the underlying adaptation.
you know buy this VLA Max Huey stuff um okay yeah sure it then in that case it would but in my uh in my extensive experience it no there's there's absolutely no difference that'd be interesting though right like you know you'd you'd send uh I don't know Andre Greipel on a different FTP training ride than you'd send you know Bernal
Yeah. Actually, you know what this makes me think of is a long time ago, I had a coach who said a lot of  I think his words were all. I think he said all the big crit guys in the US. And this was like in the early teens. So, you know, the UHC era. It was that all of them were doing their FTP work.
in five-minute blocks. It was like five minutes on, five minutes off for like eight reps or something like that. And I remember going out and doing that workout. And at the end, I was like, I didn't do anything today. Like, I mean, that wasn't work. That didn't work for me. I didn't feel like that was the right stimulus. And subsequently, I actually
I hemorrhaged about 30 watts of FTP while doing that type of FTP training. So if your FTP is just kind of stuck and it's where it is, something like that might be fine for maintenance or to get your legs back under you after some time off. I actually do do that five minutes on, five minutes off for people when they're coming back to training sometimes. But that's just another workout.
And is it the right stimulus? I would say if you want to train like that, that's one of those things where, you know, like it works for some people, sure, but probably, you know, despite the workout, not because of the workout. Yeah, makes sense.
It's another one of those things, just because it's a good workout does not mean that you should do that workout all the time, only that workout. Yeah. Well, it's funny too, because I think when we think about individualization, things like heart rate or power targets, these things, it doesn't take you long being in cycling and like...
thinking about training to realize, oh, my heart rate zones are not the same as this other person's. Like my heart rate, my threshold heart rate, for instance, has probably been like a 170 to 175 for like, I don't know, the entire time I've been training probably. It's still the same. Has not changed a bit. Chris Froome has a max heart rate of 165, right? Like Coach Katie, she has a max heart rate.
of like also about 165. Like if we see like 160 for some efforts for her, it's like, oh, that was a hard day, wasn't it? It's hard. As opposed to me where I'll see like 185 before I realize I'm having a bad day. And so I think that's one of those, like those really low level, it depends that everybody kind of sees.
and doesn't really think about, like, oh, yeah, of course you would have different power targets, you know? Yeah, definitely. So, all right, so probably a longer episode today. What was that, over an hour? Yeah, it's pretty good. Do you have any wrap-up concluding thoughts for us today, Kyle? Yeah, hopefully that people...
Take the it depends thing seriously but not too seriously and also realize that it in some ways has risen to this sort of meme status where ha ha ha it's a joke but realize that it didn't start out to be a joke or start out to be this meme. It comes from a place of good intention.
You want to help people and you want to help them well. You don't want to just give them two cents worth of advice that they could find off of Googling some forum. So the It Depends does come from a good place. And it's also not unique to us. This is not the origin of It Depends.
Oh, for sure. Yeah. Oh, man. No, not at all. How many lawyer friends do you and I have between us where we'll ask them questions and the answer is, well, again, can't we just get a straight answer? Not that I know much about law. You know a lot more than I do. But even sometimes they catch you off guard where you're like, oh, God, what does it depend on this time? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, no, it's true.
It's true. Yeah. All right, everybody. So thank you so much for listening. Glad to be back. I am so happy to have the move done. Still...
Cleaning up odds and ends, but we are back to normal business as usual, finally. So subscribe to the podcast, really share it if you have enjoyed it. Of course, we're ad-free, so empiricalcycling.com slash donate is where you can throw a couple bucks to our coffers that keep us hosting fees and Riverside fees for recording interviews and all that kind of stuff.
and we have show notes. Nope, I'm just kidding. We don't have any show notes up on the website from this episode. Maybe I'll just put up a big gif of it depends, something like that. If you have any coaching or consultation inquiries,
you can send them to empiricalcycling at gmail.com that goes right to me and of course you have any questions or comments also email me and find me on Instagram where we are asking some questions before we record podcasts at empirical cycling also AMAs up in the stories on the weekends and why not a couple of memes because I don't know why not memes I
I bet people are like, is he spending more time coaching or making memes these days? The answer is coaching. That's why he can chew gum and walk at the same time. Only while wearing a helmet. So always chew safely, people. And of course, our water bottle collab. So W-A-T-R-B-O-D-L. It depends. 10% off your order. Although I think they've had some better.
you know Father's Day discounts and whatnot happening so get those if you can otherwise stick with it depends and with that thanks everybody for listening to the show and we will see you next week thanks everyone