Welcome to the Empirical Cycling Podcast. I'm your host, Kolie Moore. We are not joined by Kyle Helson today because we're doing 10-minute tips on drills to perfect your sprint technique. So if you are listening to this podcast and you have subscribed, thank you very much. Please subscribe if you have not. And especially if you are liking the content, please share the podcast. It's really positive and really good for us when you share the podcast with other people. An iTunes rating would not go amiss. And an iTunes review, if you want to leave a nice one, we would really appreciate it.
We are an ad-free podcast, so if you want to donate to the podcast and share your support that way, you can do so at empiricalcycling.com. We have no show notes on the website today, which is empiricalcycling.com, and we also have merch at empiricalcyclingpodcast.threadless.com. If you have any coaching, consultation, inquiries, and questions or comments, you can email empiricalcycling at gmail.com as always.
Also remember that we are on Instagram at Empirical Cycling and we've got weekend AMAs in the Instagram stories and those were a lot of fun. Last Sunday was particularly fun. I had a blast and got a lot of good feedback on that. And no, I am not running for president, but yes, my platform is still that we all need two lunches. So also we are doing an...
AMA episode on Reddit. This is going to be open-ended to celebrate 100,000 podcast listens, which is a number I really never thought we would get to. So I really want to thank everybody for listening and sharing the podcast. We really appreciate it. And so we're going to celebrate that way. So today is 20 October and we're going to try to record somewhere around this coming weekend. So probably 24 October, we're going to hope to record, but it might be the 27th or 28th. Anyway, so head over there. I'll leave a comment when we stop taking questions.
and Record. So head over there to our Reddit Velo, r slash Velo, where a community I've been a part of for a long time. And I want to shout out to our Velo. Everybody there is pretty awesome. But please keep it to one question each. All right. So let's talk about sprint technique and what's happening when we sprint. And this is going to lead us directly to the drills that we should do in, you know, my typical fashion of what's happening.
How do we train it? Okay, obviously, the first thing that we're doing is we're pushing on the pedals as hard as we can. Not too fast or not too slow. We'll talk about cadence and gearing and stuff like that in a future Wattstock episode when we really dig in. But the important thing to consider here is that there are really two things going on that I like to think about training when it comes to technique.
for sprinting. Let's talk about force first because force, the forces involved in stabilizing them is a big component here. So when we put force onto something, we get an equal and opposite reaction, which is obviously Newton's third law. So what happens when we're standing on the ground, say in like a half squat, and we push as hard as we can as fast as possible, we jump.
What we're really trying to do is we're trying to push the earth away from us. Not so good at that. And the earth pushes us straight back away from it with an equal and opposite force. So this is what's happening on a bike when we sprint. We're trying to push hard on the bike and the bike is trying to launch us back off. So if we weren't clipped in, we would just go right off the pedals.
So this is actually one of the functions of holding onto the bars, which is to keep us on the bike and not launching us off when we push hard, right? Okay, so this leads us to our first drill. So how do we stabilize ourselves doing this? So this is a big gear drill. You're going to start from about
20 or 30 RPM on flat ground or a little uphill. You're going to sprint for 10 to 15 seconds and you're going to aim to get your cadence no higher than like 60 to 70 RPM. Watch out if you have knee problems and stuff like that, the obvious warnings. But this is a pretty classic drill I usually see done seated called tractor pulls. But working on standing and sprinting, you really want to be standing for this because this takes the saddle component away from the stabilization.
So the big cues for this drill are to keep your core and your arms very tight because this is the link between your feet and your hands, which are keeping you from, you know, pushing yourself straight off the bike. And we'll discuss, you know, specific strength training stuff for this kind of stabilization later. But right now on the bike technique is obviously important. And we will emphasize that in that episode when we get to that.
So this is something that you always want to make sure that you are trying to do if you're working on this aspect of your sprint. The other thing about these big gears, big gear drills, is that you may not rock the bike under you that much, and that's okay. And also, I think there's another component to this, which is, I'll mention this briefly, which is fit. If you are doing these drills, or any of these drills really, or sprinting at all, and you're finding your saddle,
is between your thighs when the bike is rocking and it's kind of bumping into you, bumping into your butt. It's probably because your fit is not long enough, especially on the track. I see a lot of people with their fits that are too short. So when they stand up, if they get...
If they stand up too much, their center of gravity is too far out over the handlebars and this really creates a weird thing. So make sure you've got the right fit for sprinting. And I usually suggest a long cockpit so that way you can keep your center of gravity kind of in between and give yourself some room to move around. So when do we work on the bike rocking back and forth? Now this is the other drill that we're going to talk about today, which is the small gears drill.
So you want to get into the small chain ring and a medium to small gear on the cassette. And just, by the way, watch out for chain slap. This is a big one for chain slap if you get going really fast. What you're going to do is you're going to stand and start sprinting kind of gently. Start around 90 RPM and slowly increase the cadence until you really can't maintain the technique properly. And what's going to happen is you are naturally going to rock the bike back and forth underneath you in order to maintain
the maintain the cadence. And people who are really good at this can do about 190, 200 RPM standing, you know, in a straight line, not on the track. Track is a little different. So the optimal duration for this drill, I think is about 10 to 20 seconds. And you want to not do it for like three seconds and stop.
because maintaining the duration for this, not a minute, but 10 to 20 seconds, I think, it really lets you feel the technique and bed in the neural patterning, especially if you're not comfortable with this. So you want to spend some time and kind of feel everything kind of start to click for you, if you know what I mean. So like for me, I'm okay at this. I'm not amazing. So I can do about 190 RPM standing maximally.
only for a couple seconds. So when I do these drills, I look for about 10 to 15 seconds, about 170 RPM is usually the sweet spot, maybe a little higher, 175. And the cues for this that you want to think to yourself when you're doing it are, relax. And the second cue is,
really relax. So keeping your body and your muscles too tight means that they're going to lock up and you need to relax quickly between the pedal strokes in order to contract quickly. So this is something where rocking the bike very quickly and feeling the legs go over it, you're going to find your natural rhythm of this very quickly, or hopefully very quickly. But this is one of my favorite drills to get used to this kind of technique.
And, you know, when I get together with people individually, and I teach them to sprint, we usually start with the big gear one, because it's a little easier, it's a little less intimidating, and everybody can just snap and smash a big gear who hasn't done that. And then we move on to the small gear stuff. And then we move on to the big power stuff. So this is our third drill. And this is really going to tie it all together. This drill is going to be...
is going to be a max power drill. So this drill is going to be a max power drill. And this is kind of like a race kind of speed drill also. So it kind of doubles as that if you want to practice like sprinting at high speeds. So what you're going to do is you're going to coast down a hill.
To, you know, for this drill, I usually recommend about 20 to 25 miles an hour or about 40 kph. If you're a really fast sprinter and you want to really get this going, you'll probably get yourself up to higher speeds very quickly. But if you don't want to shift or anything like that, you can probably try to hit like 30 miles an hour, maybe 50 kph, something like that.
and what you're going to do is when you get up to speed you're going to want to coast down onto flat ground at this speed and then you're going to want to make sure you're in the right gear at the right cadence and you're going to stand and sprint and you're going to want to hit peak power within about one or two seconds of standing and sprinting so you want to make sure that you're geared properly and all that kind of stuff you'll get used to it and what you should be able to feel is these two previous drills
Kind of clicking in. Like you should be able to feel when you push really hard on the pedal that you are stabilizing that power, you know, between your foot and your hand really well. Because if, you know, like I said, if you are not really, really tight here, you're going to leak force by, you know, twisting your torso instead of, you know, getting it stabilized by your hand and pushing it into the pedals. The other thing that you should feel
is making sure that you are relaxing while you're pushing this hard. So after you've done a couple sprints at 170 RPM or 150 RPM or wherever your max cadence is, 110 to 120, it really feels like it's really slow. So you're going to be able to think a little bit faster at your actual big power cadence where sprinting at 170 RPM, all you're really thinking about is just turning over the pedals.
and also don't forget keep your head up always look where you're going when you're doing sprint drills so you can actually do one of these or two of these drills during your interval ride warm-ups maybe two to three times a week do one or two of these maybe maybe up to three if you if you have like a big sprint like you know if you get like a
1800 watt sprint or something like that. You're probably going to want to keep these short because a long sprint obviously is going to put you in kind of a hole depending on your aerobic fitness, et cetera, et cetera. So make the right choice for yourself in terms of using these for your warmups. But usually for most people around 900, maybe 800 to 1200 watts doing a couple of these for a warmup is okay. To do these as their own ride, you can either just focus on one drill.
You can focus on the big gear drill or the small gear drill or the big power drill. But if you really want to put them all together, you can do a couple of the big gears or a couple of the small gears first and then wrap it all up with the big power. And hopefully that kind of technique on the same day really helps you with that neural patterning and getting comfortable with your sprint. And also you want to do these when you are fresh.
We'll talk about proper training of that later, you know, sprinting at the end of rides and stuff like that. I recommend that you do these while you're pretty fresh. If you're doing a longer ride with these, if you really want to work on that technique, I suggest you do it in the first like hour to hour and a half or so. Because quality with sprints is way better than quantity. So maybe like 60 seconds or maybe up to 80 seconds or 90 seconds total sprint time for a really good high quality workout.
And with that, we're probably over 10 minutes. But I think it's, I wanted to answer all of the questions that people were going to logically ask. So I don't, I don't probably don't care. So 10 minute tips are probably going to be 15 to 20 minutes, you know, starting in a little bit. I don't think anybody really cares. Regardless, I want to thank everybody for listening as always. 100,000 listens is a big deal. So we really appreciate that.
And so head over to Reddit's Rvelo and ask your questions on the thread. It should be somewhere up near the top for the next couple days at least. So I want to thank everybody for listening as always and happy sprinting.